<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Volatiles from the history of Adam and Eve containing many unquestioned truths and allowable notions of several natures / by Sir John Pettus ...</title>
            <author>Pettus, John, Sir, 1613-1690.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 243 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 100 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A54603</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1912</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7891</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13725211</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13725211</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101580</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A54603)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101580)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 846:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Volatiles from the history of Adam and Eve containing many unquestioned truths and allowable notions of several natures / by Sir John Pettus ...</title>
                  <author>Pettus, John, Sir, 1613-1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 188, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T. Bassett ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption and running title: The history of Adam and Eve.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [7]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Genesis I, 5 --  Commentaries.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101580:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>VOLATILES FROM THE HISTORY OF Adam and Eve: Containing, Many unqueſtioned <hi>Truths,</hi> and allowable <hi>Notions</hi> of ſeveral Natures.</p>
            <p>By Sir <hi>John Pettus,</hi> Knight.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. Baſſett</hi> at the <hi>George</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:101580:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101580:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>LEISTER DEVERE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>X,</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Hereford.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving the Honour of being your <hi>Neighbour</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> it <hi>London,</hi> and in our Publick <hi>Imployments;</hi> and your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> knowing the <hi>occaſion</hi> of my Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, upon this <hi>ſubject,</hi> affords me ſome <hi>reaſons</hi> of Dedicating this to your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> to ſhew you how I ſpent my time (when I had any little leiſure from buſineſs, which I ſeldom neglected) perſuant to <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toninus</hi> advice, that if one ſhould ask me at any time what I was thinking, I might be able to give an account of ſome worthy matter, and therefore I made Choice of this
<pb facs="tcp:101580:3"/>
               <hi>Story,</hi> which hath furniſh'd me with above an <hi>100</hi> ſeveral <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects,</hi> which always fed my Thoughts with ſuch ſafe <hi>Varieties,</hi> that they fenc'd out the Conſideration of other <hi>troubles</hi> which might have perplex'd them: My <hi>Method</hi> of Writing, I borrow'd from <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vezzi</hi> his <hi>Davido perſecutato</hi> my <hi>Extravagant way,</hi> from <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,</hi> who in his <hi>Eſſayes,</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes in one Chapter to write of <hi>Thumbs,</hi> and yet not one word of them in all that Diſcourſe, for have obſerv'd in the Countrey, that when I forſook the <hi>path,</hi> which would have guided me to the place I deſign'd, and croſs'd the Paſtures ſomtimes I ſtarted <hi>Hares,</hi> ſomtimes ſprang <hi>Partridges,</hi> or obſerv'd ſome curious <hi>Plants;</hi> which plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures I had never injoy'd if I had confin'd my ſelf to the path, yet
<pb facs="tcp:101580:3"/>I kept my Eye on <hi>it,</hi> (leaſt I ſhould ſtray too far) and return'd home by <hi>it,</hi> and inliven'd or inrich't my thoughts with the Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of what happen'd by my <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Poſſibly, theſe <hi>Excurſions</hi> might have been more excuſable to me in my Youth, than in my Age; but it is a ſolace to me, that I can be yet youthful in my <hi>notions,</hi> and if your Lordſhip pleaſe to peruſe theſe as a <hi>Recreation,</hi> your Lordſhip will very much Honour,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips moſt humble Servant</hi> Jo. Pettus.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:101580:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101580:4"/>
            <head>The Stationer to the Courteous Reader.</head>
            <p>THere are ſome Errata's occaſion'd by the Indiſpoſition of the Printer, for want of <hi>Orthography, Comma's, Conjunctions, Parentheſis,</hi> expunging of needleſs <hi>Adverbs,</hi> mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtakes of <hi>Singulars</hi> for <hi>Plurals;</hi> which may be amended by the Ingenuity of the Reader upon the intended ſenſe of the Sentence; but the moſt mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial are, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>PAG. 14. l. 5. read <hi>ſixteen,</hi> and l. 18. r. <hi>graines.</hi> p. 18. l. 1. r. <hi>Life,</hi> p. 30. l. 10. r. <hi>Undermines,</hi> and l. 25. r. <hi>humid part,</hi> and l. 28. r. <hi>prae-efficient,</hi> p. 40. l. 21. r. <hi>adjectively,</hi> p. 79. l. 25. r. <hi>feminine,</hi> p. 96. l. 4. r. <hi>tunes,</hi> p. 110. l. 1. r. <hi>of,</hi> p. 125. l. 30. r. <hi>are none,</hi> p. 163. l. 13. r. <hi>Jonathan.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text_and_commentary">
            <pb facs="tcp:101580:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101580:5"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY OF ADAM and EVE.</head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>Introduction.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IN the beginning.</hi> Whilſt all we can apprehend was God, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of his manifeſtation of himſelf by Parts: In the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thoſe Parts, from whence we account the beginning of Time: In the beginning, when that Time was an Emanation of Eternity: In the beginning, when God afforded us Viſibility out of his Inviſibility, <hi>God Created Heaven and Earth.</hi> And from that Maſs of Creation divers other parts were (as we may ſay in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their Comparative Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy) alſo created, as it appears Verſe the 3. <hi>And God ſaid, Let there be Light. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, And God ſaid, Let there be a Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament. Thirdly, And God ſaid, Let the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101580:6"/>Earth appear. Fourthly, And God ſaid, Let the Earth bring forth graſs. Fifthly, And God ſaid, Let there be Lights. Sixth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, And God ſaid, Let the waters bring forth Fowl. Seventhly, And God ſaid, Let the Earth bring forth Cattle.</hi> So that there was a Septenary or ſeven <hi>Fiats,</hi> and no more (ſeven being a perfect number.) And thoſe being done, God begins with Man in another Dialect; for inſtead of <hi>Let there be</hi> God ſaid, <hi>Let us make:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 1. ver. 26.</note> Now whether theſe words <hi>Let us</hi> are to be underſtood as more Majeſtically ſpoken, or an Invocation of the Trinity, imployed in the word <hi>Elohim,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Et dixit Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelis mini ſtrantibus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coram eo, qui creati ſunt die ſecundo creationis mundi. <hi>Targ. Hier.</hi>
                  </note> or a ſummoning of Angels or other ſpiritual Inſtruments: Or <hi>Let us,</hi> that is, let the Creatures which I have Created on the five former days, together with ſuch a Soul as I ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe into Man, <hi>Let us make Man;</hi> that is, let man be conſtituted of Light, Air, Water, and Earth, and of the Qualities and Virtues of thoſe and other Creatures, and of a Soul peculiar to himſelf, yet derivative in ſome man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner from us (his Creator, and my o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Creatures) I ſhall not here diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute; but leave it to other volumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Writers: For not onely the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101580:6"/>(as I ſaid concerning Mans creation) is different, but it is clear that <hi>Moſes</hi> gives only a Conciſe Narrative of the things created before Man, not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting to us any circumſtances uſed in their Creation. But as to Man he gives a full and ample diſcourſe, from the ſeventh Verſe of the ſecond Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to the end of the ſame Chapter, being wholly ſpent in it; and indeed is but a <hi>Parentheſis</hi> proper to be read between the 26 and 27 Verſes of the firſt Chapter: the words, <hi>Let us make Man,</hi> in the 26 verſe, being either the Conſultative part of Mans Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or as Gods declarative Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſo to do; and the words in the 27th. verſe <hi>(So God created man)</hi> ſhews the compleating that deliberation or reſolution. And therefore I ſhall begin with thoſe words of the ſeventh verſe Chapter ſecond, <hi>And the Lord God (made)</hi> as being the beginning of the active part of his Creation, and ſo deſcant upon that whole ſecond Chapter; and that being finiſhed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the 27th. verſe of the firſt Chapter, <hi>(So God created man)</hi> and then to the 28 and 29 verſes, with which I ſhall conclude the firſt part of theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:101580:7"/>
The ſecond part ſhall begin with the 30th. of the firſt Chapter, becauſe it is an Induction to the offences of the Serpent, and thence paſs to the whole third Chapter: to which ſhall be add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo much of the 4th. and 5th. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters as ſhall make the Hiſtory and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of diſcourſes concerning <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> intire and pleaſurable to the Reader, and I hope without the leaſt offence to the ſacred Method, or diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to any.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Notions</hi> which I have us'd here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are chiefly from my Notes out of Dr. <hi>Waltons</hi> Laborious and Learned <hi>Polyglotta,</hi> ſome parts of St. <hi>Auguſtine, Pererius,</hi> Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh,</hi> Dr. <hi>Donne, Paulus Lovatius, Crook,</hi> and ſome others cited on the Margin; and if I have hit upon any others <hi>veins</hi> which I have not cited, it is the error of my Memory not of my Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, ſo that till I know them I may be excus'd: and if the Style and Method be ſomewhat above, or out of the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual road, it may be aſcribed to my Education, which hath been not like a <hi>Pedant,</hi> but a <hi>Gentleman.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="text">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:101580:7"/>
               <head>The Text of the firſt Part.</head>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>Cap. 2.</head>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>Verſe 7.</hi> THe Lord God made Man of the duſt of the ground, and breathed into his Noſtrils the breath of Life, and the Man became a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Soul.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8.</hi> And the Lord God planted a Garden Eaſtward in <hi>Eden,</hi> and there he put the man whom he had formed.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9.</hi> And out of the ground made the Lord to grow every tree that is pleaſant to the ſight, and good for food, the tree of Life alſo in the midſt of the Garden, and the tree of Knowledge of good and evil</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>10.</hi> And a River went out of <hi>Eden</hi> to water the Garden, and from thence it was parted into four Heads.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>11.</hi> The name of the firſt is <hi>Piſon,</hi> that is it which incompaſseth the whole Land of <hi>Havilah,</hi> where is Gold.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>12.</hi> And the Gold of that Land is good: there is <hi>Bdellium,</hi> and the <hi>Onyx Stone.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>13.</hi> And the name of the ſecond River is <hi>Gihon:</hi> the ſame is it which incompaſſeth the whole Land of <hi>Aethiopia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:101580:8"/>
                     <hi>14.</hi> And the name of the third River is <hi>Hidekell,</hi> which is it which goeth towards the Eaſt of <hi>Aſſyria:</hi> and the fourth River is <hi>Euphrates.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>15.</hi> And the Lord God took the man, and put him into the Garden of <hi>Eden</hi> to dreſs it, and to keep it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>16.</hi> And the Lord God commanded the man, ſaying, of every tree of the Garden thou mayſt freely eat:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>17.</hi> But of the tree of Knowledge of Good and Evil thou ſhalt not cat of it, for in the day thou eateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely die.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>18.</hi> And the Lord God ſaid, It is not good that man ſhould be alone, I will make an help meet for him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>19.</hi> And out of the ground the Lord God formed every Beaſt of the field, and every Fowl of the air, and brought them to <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> to ſee what he would call them, and whatever he called every living Creature, that was the name thereof.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>20.</hi> And <hi>Adam</hi> gave names to all Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and to the Fowls of the Air, and to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Beaſt of the field, but for <hi>Adam</hi> there was not found an help meet for him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>21.</hi> And the Lord God cauſed a deep ſleep to fall upon <hi>Adam,</hi> and he ſlept, and he took one of his Ribs and cloſed up the fleſh inſtead thereof.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:101580:8"/>
                     <hi>22.</hi> And of the Rib which the Lord God had taken from man made he a Woman, and brought her unto the man.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>23.</hi> And <hi>Adam</hi> ſaid this is now bone of my bone, and fleſh of my fleſh, ſhe ſhall be called Woman becauſe ſhe was taken out of man.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>24.</hi> Therefore ſhall a man leave his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother, and ſhall cleave unto his Wife, and they ſhall be one fleſh.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>25.</hi> And they were both naked, and were not aſhamed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>Cap. 1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>27.</hi> So God created man in his own Image, in the Image of God created he him, male and female created he them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>28.</hi> And God bleſsed them, and God ſaid unto them, Be fruitful and multiply, and repleniſh the Earth, and ſubdue it, and have Dominion over the fiſh of the Sea, and over the fowl of the Air, and over every living thing that moveth upon the face of the Earth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>29.</hi> And God ſaid, behold I have given you every herb bearing ſeed, which is upon the face of the Earth, and every tree in the which is the fruit of a tree yielding ſeed, to you it ſhall be for meat.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
               <div n="7" type="verse">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:101580:9"/>
                  <head>Cap. 2. Ver. 7.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Lord God.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 1.</note> This is the firſt time that any Additional Attribute is added to the word <hi>God;</hi> for though <hi>Lord God</hi> is twice uſed in the two preceding verſes of this ſecond Chapter, yet the matter of thoſe verſes is ſubſecuent to the Creation of Man: For man was made before the Sabbath, and before the Creation was finiſhed; ſo that this addition of Lord ſhews what delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and power was uſed in Creating and making Man, expreſſed in the words, <hi>Let us make:</hi> and here being made, 'tis ſaid, <hi>the Lord God made Man;</hi> for as God he created Man, as Lord he governs and rules him being made: to which I ſhall add this Obſervation, that <hi>Jehovah</hi> (expreſſing God) hath ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Letters, and ſo hath <hi>Dominus</hi> (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing Lord;) and Lord God joyned conſiſts alſo of ſeven Letters: ſo ſacred is that number of Seven to the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Languages. And the word <hi>God</hi> (conſiſting of a Ternary of Letters) as uſed onely in the general Creation; but in the Creation of Man, <hi>viz.</hi> from the ſeventh verſe to the end of the Chapter, <hi>Lord God</hi> is mentioned nine
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:101580:9"/>times and no more; which two num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſeven and nine are moſt applicable to the buſineſs of Creation.</p>
                  <p>For the Creation conſiſted of ſeven dayes (as ſome Fathers write) ſeven Planets, ſeven properties of the two great Lights, nine Orbes or Sphears (and three times ſeven generations, of which I have writ a particular Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe) and though our Common Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations do not mention the numbers of the parts of Man, yet the <hi>Targum</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſays, the Lord created <hi>Adam</hi> with 248 Membranes, and 365 Nerves, (ſo many it ſeems as there are dayes in the year) and covered all with a Skin which he filled with Fleſh and Blood; ſo that there are but five ſimilar parts here mention'd, but theſe that are more exact (collected alſo from the Text) do make the Body of Man to conſiſt of twice ſeven ſimilar parts, <hi>viz.</hi> Bones, Cartilages, Ligaments, Membranes, Nerves, Arteries, Veins, Fibras, Tuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, Spermaticks, Fat, Blood, Fleſh, Skin; but to ſatisfie the Reader with ſome variety before I proceed in my intended method, I take leave to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert here my ſenſe of <hi>Spencer</hi>'s Stanza, concerning thoſe two numbers of ſeven
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101580:10"/>and nine, and if I differ in the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation thereof from the Learned Sir <hi>Kenelm Digby,</hi> I may be excuſed becauſe I leave it to the Reader to pleaſe himſelf in the allowance or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allowance of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Spencer</hi> in his <hi>Fairy Queen</hi> (Chapter 22th. Of <hi>Temperance</hi>) deſcribes the Caſtle of <hi>Alma</hi> (or Mans <hi>Body</hi> thus:</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>The frame thereof ſeem'd partly Circular,</l>
                     <l>And part Triangular O Work Divine!</l>
                     <l>Theſe two the firſt and laſt Proportions are,</l>
                     <l>The one Immortal, Perfect, Maſculine;</l>
                     <l>The other Mortal, imperfect, Feminine.</l>
                     <l>And 'twixt them both a Quadrate is the Baſe.</l>
                     <l>Proportion'd equally by Seven and Nine:</l>
                     <l>Nine was the Circle ſet in Heavens place,</l>
                     <l>All which compacted make a goodly Diapaſe.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>Which is thus to be underſtood as I conceive,</p>
                  <q>The Frame thereof ſeem'd partly Circular.</q>
                  <p>The Body of a Man or Woman be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exactly extended makes a true Circle, by fixing the Center at the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, and the Circumference to touch the extreame points of the fingers and toes. Then draw a Diametrical Line o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Navel point, ſo that the paſſing over the head touch no further down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards than the Navel Line, and it will be partly Circular, or Semi-circular.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:101580:10"/>
And Part Triangular.</q>
                  <p>Then the inferior part from the Navel (both legs being divided and extended to the Circumferating Line) makes a Triangle, there being as much diſtance from foot to foot, as from the Extream point of each to the Navel; ſo 'tis part Circular and part Triangu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar.</p>
                  <q>O Work Divine!</q>
                  <p>And this is the Divine Work to give all things their Numberand Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, Geometrical Proportion, as ſhall be further ſhewed.</p>
                  <q>Theſe two the firſt and laſt Proportions are.</q>
                  <p>This fully explains, that the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular proportion hath reference to the Superior part of the body, the Trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular to the inferior, calling them the firſt and laſt proportion.</p>
                  <q>The one Immortal, Perfect, Maſculine.</q>
                  <p>Now in the firſt Superior or half Circular proportion, which is from the head to the Navel, is properly ſeated
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101580:11"/>the Soul, (although virtually it oppe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates in all other parts of the Body) and therefore is called the Immortal, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, Maſculine part.</p>
                  <q>The other Mortal, Imperfect, Feminine:</q>
                  <p>In the laſt inferior or Triangular part, which is from the Nave to the feet (alluding to the fleſh) is nothing but Corruption, Imperfection, and the excrementitious parts of Nature, and may juſtly be called the Mortal, Imperfect, Feminine.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>And 'twixt them both a Quadrate is the Baſe,</l>
                     <l>Compoſed equally by Seven and Nine.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>The Exterior extenſive parts of Man being thus compoſed and deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by a Circular and Triangular ſorm, here he ſhews the proportion both of Man and Woman: for for as <hi>Hercules</hi> his whole body was delineated by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king uſe only of his Thumb, ſo may every mans (the exact length of his Face being once known:) for every bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is eight, nine, or ten times as long as his face, according as he is nearer or further from a true proportion.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101580:11"/>But the moſt famous Arciſts agree, that the exact length of a man ought to be but nine faces, of a woman but ſeven: that is, the body of man from the Chin ought to be eight times as long as the face, and of a woman ſix times. And leſt the Error of the face ſhould give an Error to the body, the face ought to be ſo compoſed, that from the top of the forehead to the dint of the Noſe, and from the dint of the Noſe, the length of the Noſe, and from the bottom of the Noſe to the turn of the Chin, ſhould be of an equal meaſure and diſtance. And ſo likewiſe from the dint of the Noſe to the exterior parts of each Eye, and from that part of the Eye to the ſetting on of each Ear of the ſame diſtance; the rule for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion and meaſure of which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ought to be from the top of the thumb to the ſecond joynt of the thumb. Then his bredth ſtom ſide to ſide, and thickneſs from back to ſtomach is anſwerable. And this ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry is not onely in the outward Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neaments, but in the inward; for the Guts of Man do alſo confirm this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of ſeven and nine, being nine
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101580:12"/>or ſeven times the length of the body. Had not this exactneſs been obſerved, the ſixteen <hi>Italian</hi> Artiſts had never agreed; who reſolving each man to make a ſixth part of a Man, without ſeeing each other, or any model gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but what was apprehended by them to be the juſt proportion of Man, when each of them brought their part to be joyned together, it ſeemed as the Act of one intire Artiſt and Workman, and not of many. And 'tis not onely thus in number and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but in weight; for the Heart as I have ſhewed elſewhere (by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures of ſome, for it cannot other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be demonſtrated) weighs two ſtrains at the Birth, and increaſeth to fifty grains, and then decreaſeth by two grains as he declines in years to his Infant Age, if the Almighty thinks fit to give him ſuch a Continuation. And not onely man, but woman is made by this Geometrical proportion of ſeven and nine, which numbers being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned make ſixteen, that is, a <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drat,</hi> a <hi>Quadrat</hi> number being that which is formed of its own parts: and there is a proper and improper <hi>Quadrat,</hi> becauſe it conſiſts of odd
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101580:12"/>parts; as three times three is nine, which is an improper <hi>Quadrat;</hi> but four times four is ſixteen, which is a proper <hi>Quadrat,</hi> becauſe it conſiſts of equal parts, which is the <hi>Quadrat</hi> here meant; and this <hi>Quadrat</hi> is called <hi>Baſe,</hi> which if it be meant according to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> word <hi>Baſe,</hi> (<hi>id eſt,</hi> vile or beaſtly) this Conjunction of Man and Woman ſo improperly uſed, or with ſuch immoderacy, that thereby we weaken or abuſe our Caſtle of <hi>Alma,</hi> or Temperance, it is moſt baſe, ſordid, and beaſtly: Or if from the Geometrical or Muſical word <hi>Baſe</hi> or <hi>Baſis,</hi> which is moſt ſignificant; then if this ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work or Foundation, or Muſical Key be compacted by a divine, chaſte, and ſolemn compact, we make a proper <hi>Quadrat</hi> and perfect <hi>Diapaſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>Nine is the number ſet in Heavens place,</l>
                     <l>All which compacted make a goodly Diapaſe.</l>
                  </q>
                  <p>And this compact is made when nine ſtands in Heavens place; for Man being underſtood by nine, conſiſting (as I ſaid) of nine parts, is oft called God; and as God being himſelf a Trinity governs Man; ſo Man (an Inferior God, having in himſelf a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101580:13"/>Triple Trinity nine, or three times three) ſhould govern the Woman, by keeping the proper diſtance above ſeven, (of which proportion Woman conſiſts) which God hath allowed him, that is two, (ſeven being ſo many ſhort of nine;) rather allowing her one to make her even with him, then either by too much ſubtracting from himſelf, and giving her a number a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove him, or robbing her of leſs then ſhe ſhould have. But this fair compact by allowing her one out of his num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, God himſelf allowed when he made her of one of his Ribs; by the addition of which one, the ſeven be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes eight, ſo there is two eights, which makes the goodly <hi>Diapaſe.</hi> The ſweeteſt, the moſt Harmonious and Myſtical concord in Muſick, as we ſee by two Lutes or ſilver Bowls, the one being ſtruck, the other anſwers an eight without ſtriking. Thus num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers from oddneſs become even; when <hi>Circles, Triangles, Genders, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection</hi> and <hi>Imperfection, Mortality</hi> and <hi>Immortality</hi> concurred and were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined in ſo Divine a Work.</p>
                  <p>But to return to the word of our Tranſlation. <hi>The Lord God</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:101580:13"/>
                     <hi>Made.</hi> Tranſlators do promiſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onſly render theſe words, viz.<note place="margin">§ 3.</note> 
                     <hi>Made, Formed, Framed,</hi> and <hi>Created:</hi> But where the word Created is uſed after the general Maſs of Creation (as in the zith. verſe, <hi>God created the Whale;</hi> and in the 27th. verſe, <hi>God created Man</hi>) it is to be underſtood, that God created ſome ſingular and more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Piece, beſides the original Maſs; and ſo ſaith the <hi>Targum</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem, Creavit eum duabus creationibus,</hi> i. e. He created Man by two ſingular and univerſal Creations. Now the word <hi>Made</hi> ſignifies a Temperament of that ſingular Creation with the univerſal; <hi>Framed</hi> relates to the proportions; and <hi>Formed</hi> to the Life or Soul of the thing created: ſo that Man was crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with other Creatures out of the main Maſs; then he was created with ſome peculiar additions; after which he was made into Quantities and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities in groſs; then Framed into cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain regular dimenſions and proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and laſtly Formed, or (as the Schools call it) informed with a Soul. Now whether God did all this in order of Time I ſhall not diſpute; for in te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Gods Works they have no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101580:14"/>of Time, but in reſpect of Man we may ſo apprehend them (without offence;) becauſe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Gods Omnipotency cannot clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be conceived by mans capacity.</p>
                  <p>But as to theſe words <hi>made, framed,</hi> and <hi>formed,</hi> (as they are notionally di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt inct from <hi>Created</hi>) they may be thus conſiderable, <hi>viz. made</hi> into a Vegeta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive (intimated by the duſt of the Earth) <hi>framed</hi> into a Senſitive life (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated by the breath of Lile) and <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi> into a rational life (intimated by a Living Soul:) ſo that in this notion we may apprehend alſo our ſimilitude to God by a <hi>Trinity in Unity.</hi> And that theſe words ought to be diſtinctly underſtood, appears from the words in the ſecond Chapter, verſe 2. <hi>And God reſted from all his works which he had creaded and made;</hi> and likewiſe in the fourth verſe, <hi>Theſe are the Generations of the heavens and the earth, when they were created, in the day that God made the earth and the heavens.</hi> And the words <hi>framed</hi> and <hi>formed</hi> are uſed in other places in different ſenſes; but I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the word <hi>made</hi> is moſt proper to be uſed here, becauſe it is onely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to Creatures of the greateſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minency,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101580:14"/>and that nine times. 1. To the <hi>firmament.</hi> 2. To the two great <hi>lights.</hi> 3. To the <hi>ſtars;</hi> and four times in the ſecond and third verſes of this Chapter, where the word is expreſt by way of Enumeration, of what was <hi>created</hi> and <hi>made:</hi> and then it is twice more named by change of the number, as in the 27th. verſe, <hi>Let us make;</hi> and in the 18th. verſe of the ſecond Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>I will make: Let us make</hi> deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting either the <hi>Trinity</hi> or <hi>Angels,</hi> or the compoſition of his Qualities aſſimila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting God; <hi>And I will make</hi> denoting his peculiar care. But however here 'tis ſaid, <hi>The Lord God</hi> made man; which are plural appellations, though the verb be ſingular; ſo that <hi>Let us make,</hi> and <hi>the Lord God made,</hi> do anſwer each other as to the Trinity, or what concerns the eminency of mans being made.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Man.</hi> If <hi>David</hi> ask'd the queſtion,<note place="margin">§ 4.</note> 
                     <hi>Lord, what is man?</hi> ſo many hundred years after he was made, and anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelf, that <hi>man is altogether vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> or <hi>is nothing, and his days as a ſhadow;</hi> what can we imagine man to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was made? he was nothing as the word Creation implys; and being
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101580:15"/>made, he was made of little more then nothing; for he was made of the duſt of the earth, and yet ſtill continuing in this Compact of duſt, he is ſtill but vanity or nothing. And ſo we may Collect from his four names, for he is called <hi>Adam, Enoch, Iſhe, Chebor;</hi> the firſt name <hi>Adam</hi> ſignifies earth, or red earth, that ſeems to have ſome colour of a ſubſtance; and yet when we ſee how changeable it is into other Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the earth it ſelf is but a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary ſomething. Secondly <hi>Enoch,</hi> which ſignifies ſickneſs or calamity, we feel ſomething of that, and yet that vaniſheth; <hi>for pain or calamity may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure for a night, but joy cometh in the morning.</hi> The third is <hi>Iſhe,</hi> which ſignifies crying or laughing, both of which are ſo oft expreſt in one wind (as the Proverb ſaith) they are ſcarce diſtinguiſhable. And for the laſt <hi>Chebor,</hi> ſignifying Excellency, it is ſaid that <hi>man being in honour hath no under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> but is compared to <hi>the beaſts that periſh.</hi> So that we may well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive theſe four words ſignifie the four Elements of which he is Compacted; <hi>Adam,</hi> Earth, the groſſer part of his body: <hi>Enoch,</hi> Water, the redundancy
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101580:15"/>of which cauſeth ſickneſs and deluges of Rhumes: <hi>Iſhe,</hi> Air, from whence allſo unds are procreated: and <hi>Cheber,</hi> Fire, which is the moſt excellent of all the Elements, and ſo is either com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and culinary, or ſuperceleſtial, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of Love, or au intellect, or ſuch properties as belong to an Angelical Nature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of the duſt of the ground.</hi> Man is ſaid to be made of <hi>the duſt of the ground;</hi> and in the ninth verſe 'tis ſaid, <hi>Out of the ground the Lord God made to grow every tree;</hi> and verſe 19th. <hi>Out of the ground the Lord God formed every beaſt,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Out;</hi> here it is meerly <hi>out</hi> of the <hi>duſt</hi> of the <hi>ground,</hi> to ſhew that there was a difference between Man and other Creatures in their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king; ſo that by the <hi>duſt</hi> of the <hi>ground</hi> is to be underſtood the ſuperficial part of the earth, of which man onely was made; for all Creatures are ſaid to be made <hi>out</hi> of the <hi>ground,</hi> but not <hi>of the duſt</hi> of the <hi>ground;</hi> but Man <hi>of the duſt</hi> of the <hi>ground</hi> or earth. Now whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this duſt was made by a peculiar omnipotent Calcination, or other Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification is not demonſtrated; but we may conceive it of the moſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuated
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101580:16"/>part of the earth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the more Noble part, becauſe capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the moſt activity; for if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider our <hi>commonduſt,</hi> it flies like Atoms over the Surface of the earth, oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times being raiſed into as many dry Clouds as there are moiſt, and by the co-operation of theſe two, dry and wet, thoſe varieties of Naturals and Preternaturals (which are ſo oft ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red down upon us, and ſeen among us, as Moths and other flies, Mice and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Vermine) are produced. And moſtly they are Agile creatures, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we reſpect their volatile or rep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, or aquatick natures; which I mention to ſhew, that if the ordinary <hi>duſt</hi> produceth ſuch agile Creatures, we may collect that our Creator hath adapted to our more agaile body (in relation to our Souls) far more agile <hi>duſt</hi> the to other Creatures. For the <hi>Targum</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> adds to our honor, that we are made <hi>ex palvere Sanctuarii,</hi> i. e. of holy <hi>duſt,</hi> differing from all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>duſts:</hi> which ſhould raiſe this Contemplation in us, that as we are not like beaſts or other Creatures in our Temperaments, they made of the ground, that is, of the <hi>faeces</hi> or dregs
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101580:16"/>of the Earth, we of the Superficies (or of ſome peculiar <hi>ſanctify'd duſt;</hi>) ſo ought the habits of our bodies to be ſublime, and alwaies aſcending to an higher ſphere, and not to be alloyed and turned into various Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And breathed the breath of life.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 6.</note> God at firſt <hi>breathed</hi> upon the face of the waters: this was the firſt univerſal Vegetative and Senſitive life and moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which he infuſed into the Maſs of Creation, of which Man was alſo par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker. But this <hi>breath</hi> which God breathed into man, was of a higher na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, not onely giving life and motion (for Man had that by <hi>univerſal breath,</hi> but by this <hi>man</hi> became a living Soul.) And as our bloud within us (for all things have a bloud or ſpirit of the nature of bloud) is ſaid to be the Vehi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle or Conveyor of the Vegetative or Senſitive life; ſo the Air without us, in which is the <hi>univerſal breath,</hi> may be ſaid to be the Vehicle of that life in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us; and the ſpirit or life is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hicle of our rational life, or of that divine Soul which flows into us; for God works all things by fit Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: ſo that our Soul is conveyed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101580:17"/>to us by this ſpirit or <hi>breath</hi> of life; the ſpirit of life paſſes by air, the air, by bloud (and other parts adapted for ſuch receprions;) ſo traverſing the whole body by Circulation, returns again to the place from whence it came; for we ſee when the bloud and air (which are more evident to us) meet with any obſtructions either by nature or accident, the Soul thereby is deprived of all its faculties.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Into his Noſtrils.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 7.</note> The <hi>Egptians</hi> were wont to ſignifie a wiſe and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent mind by the figure of a <hi>Noſe,</hi> and of ſtrength to his wiſdom by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion of the <hi>Noſtrils;</hi> for here it is that the breath of life firſt enters, and conſequently wiſdom and ſtrength. The Anatomiſts call them <hi>Nares,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Spirits of the air do <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re</hi> or <hi>Swim</hi> continually in them; nor is the mouth or pores fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for ſuch receptions. The three properties of Inſpiration, Expiration, and Reſpiration, being peculiar onely to the <hi>Noſtrils;</hi> for if the <hi>Noſtrils</hi> be not clear, the mouth will be foul, the breath ſtinking, and the pores unapt for ſudation: for the <hi>Noſtrils</hi> having through its little hairs ſuckt in the air
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101580:17"/>free from commixtures, it paſſeth from thence to certain ſpungy bones, and from thence into Mammillary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, or things like the teats of <hi>Udders,</hi> and ſo immediately to the Brain, where the commonſenſe ſits as Judge, and reſolves to pleaſure the body with what is fit for the ſenſes, or by certain perforations does again diſtil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the mouth, or throws them out by efflations as obnoxious. Now it is certain (as Anatomiſts find) that there are two Nervous inductions, which go from the noſtrils to the very middle of the brain, whereby the Life and Soul firſt enters by the help of the air into the <hi>Noſtrils,</hi> and thence to the brain, and from thence by the breath of life is virtually transfuſed into all parts of the body; but the <hi>Noſtrils</hi> muſt have the honor of the firſt ingreſs of life, and of the firſt infuſed Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Created infuſion of the Soul.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And Man became a Living Soul.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 8.</note> The <hi>Arabick</hi> renders it a <hi>Rational Soul,</hi> which properly diſtinguiſheth it from the Soul of other Creatures. But the word <hi>Living</hi> is ſufficient: for all Creatures have a ſhare in the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101580:18"/>breath of life, but Man onely is ſaid to be a <hi>Living</hi> Soul, or a Soul which is alwaies <hi>Living:</hi> It lives here under a notion of <hi>Mortality</hi> in reſpect of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, but lives here in reſpect of it ſelf under a certain notion of <hi>Immortality,</hi> dying as to the body, but always li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to its ſelf. The bloud returns it through the brain and noſtrils to the <hi>ſpirit</hi> of life, that <hi>univerſal ſpirit of life</hi> to the <hi>peculiar ſpirit</hi> of humanity, to be diſpoſed into individual Glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 2. Ver. 8.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the Lord God planted a Garden Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in Eden.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 9.</note> The <hi>garden</hi> here is not meerly to be underſtood in our uſual phraſe, a place of Flowers, or Orchard for Plants, but <hi>a place</hi> which contains all ſorts of plants and Flowers from the Hyſop to the Cedar, from the leaſt to the greateſt, as the Seminary and Nurſery for all future Plantations: and this <hi>place</hi> was Eaſtward, which the Sun ſaluted in the morning; to ſet us an example of our duty to all orderly motions. A <hi>place</hi> where no Edifices were to hide our lazy or ſurfeited bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; a <hi>place</hi> where was no bed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101580:18"/>on, but the lap of our Mother Earth; no Valences or Curtains but the ſhade of trees; no covering to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent nakedneſs, but their leaves; no mixtures to heighten our taſts; all pure ſimples; no Penſils to deceive or flatter our eyes; all true natural, and a perfect repreſentation of what a Country life ſhould be. And this is as the word ſignifies the true <hi>Garden of Eden,</hi> in which happy ſolitude or ſafe pleaſure, ſee what <hi>Adam</hi> enjoyed; <hi>He</hi> had every tree that was pleaſant to the ſight, or good for the taſte, but princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally a tree for Life, a tree for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. There was alſo flowing and enriching Rivers: Beſides there was gold and precious ſtones enough to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie a contented mind, not Avarice: And above all <hi>he</hi> had opportunity there to expreſs a harmleſs induſtry (it ſeems one of the pleaſures of <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe</hi>)</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And there he put the Man whom he had formed.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 10.</note> Not the <hi>man</hi> whom he had Created out of nothing, and by meer Creation could do nothing; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing formed, or a Soul infuſed into that lump of Creation, he was thereby im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered to act; and that he might
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101580:19"/>have ſome materials to work upon, he was there <hi>put</hi> or placed. And certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly not onely <hi>Adam,</hi> but every man hath his native <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> every part of the World hath its varieties, and may afford us ſatisfaction for the body and the mind. And it is either the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal Itch in us, or want of true Education or Inſtruction, or curious ambition, or an uncontented mind, or a continued puniſhment upon us mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, that no <hi>place,</hi> no <hi>ſtation</hi> where we are, can hold us, nor no <hi>Paradiſe</hi> or pleaſure retain us from further inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. It is not ſaid he <hi>put</hi> the Man there whom he had <hi>created,</hi> or <hi>made,</hi> or <hi>fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med;</hi> but the <hi>Man</hi> that he had <hi>formed,</hi> to ſhew that the Mind or Soul of Man whereſoever <hi>placed</hi> with the body might make any <hi>place</hi> contenting, if it transgreſſed not its Rules and Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 2. Ver. 9.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And out of the ground.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 11.</note> Man (as I ſhewed in the ſeventh verſe) is ſaid to be made not onely of the <hi>ground,</hi> but of the <hi>duſt</hi> of the <hi>ground;</hi> and here e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very tree is ſaid to be made out of the <hi>ground,</hi> but not of the <hi>duſt;</hi> ſo that Man
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101580:19"/>hath a Conſtitution by himſelf, and yet as made of the ground, he partakes of all plants; for <hi>homo eſt Arbor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſa,</hi> i. e. <hi>man is a tree invers'd:</hi> and is called <hi>homo,</hi> becauſe he is <hi>ex humo,</hi> or <hi>ex humida parte terrae,</hi> i. e. out of the humid part of the earth. He hath his duſt and moiſture, <hi>i. e.</hi> he is agile and apt for motion, yet fixt in his mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials; whereas plants are not ſo they are fixed in the <hi>ground,</hi> and have no motion but of Vegetation, except what is ſaid of the Mandrake and the feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lamb;<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Perkinſon,</hi> p. 118.</note> yet they alſo die if the fibras that oblige them to the earth be cut aſunder. And Man hath very little advantage, when we conſider that in all his poſtures, ſitting, lying, or ſtanding, ſtill he is fixed to the earth or to ſome materials made of the earth, (ſwimiming in the water, leap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the air, being but forced moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and of no continuance.) And this is called our Vegetative life; although in a plant there is alſo a ſenſitive life,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> as is ſeen in the ſenſible and other known plants of that nature. Now as man is made of the <hi>duſt</hi> of the <hi>ground,</hi> plants are more proper <hi>out of the ground,</hi> and they have two advantages
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:101580:20"/>over Man, firſt in their heighth above ground, 300 foot and more high; and next by perforation in the ground, ſome conceiving that the ſap root of an Oak will run 9 foot perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicular downward, which is as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectured is in ſolid earth the uttermoſt Orb of the Liquid Element: But Man by his ingenuity mounts the heigheſt and mines the deepeſt rooted plants.</p>
                  <p>Now the other part of the earth further from the ſuperficies is more compact and ſolid, affording Quarries, Mines, and Precious Stones; but yet all varieties of colours, taſts, odours, Inſtruments of Harmony, and indeed all things which pleaſe the ſenſes, are produced out of this ſuperficies of the humid part of the earth, being in the middle between air and Minerals, which have their colours and vertues onely by attraction, then conſolida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Lord made to grow.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 12.</note> That is, they had their energy of <hi>growth</hi> from his humid part; for we muſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh between Creation and Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the one being an exiſtency out of no p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> efficient matter, the other the motion or operation of that exiſtency,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101580:20"/>according to the ſeveral natures of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral kinds, adapted for various O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations, always moving in the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Soul, being the ſpring of the World, which makes the wheels to move in order, if we conſider the whole; but if we conſider the parts, 'tis more difficult to apprehend the Connexion of all things as it were in one: but we can look on it no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then as a Watch, the ſpring gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving motion to every wheel, where the nimbler motion of the balance is as conſiderable as the Majeſtick grada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the great wheel, both ſerving to one end. Thus the little Mite of the Cheeſe hath its proportioned uſe, as the great Crocodile produced out of the ſlime of <hi>Nile;</hi> the little Wren, as the <hi>Oſtridgae</hi> or the great bird <hi>Ibis;</hi> the harmleſs Lamb, as the Elephant, or the great beaſt that devours Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries; the Pigmy, as the Giant; the Hyſop as the Cedar; the pleaſant Southern air, as the the great Diapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Saturn,</hi> (accounting the motion of this lower air to move harmoniouſly with the other ſeven Orbs.) So that in the whole Creation this <hi>growing</hi> is no other then the <hi>motion</hi> of the <hi>univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:101580:21"/>ſpirit</hi> diverſifyed by various Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans for ſeveral uſes to one common end.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Every Tree.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 13.</note> We muſt apprehend this garden called <hi>Paradiſe</hi> to be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then Geographers do allow it; or elſe we muſt (as Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> doth with the beaſts that went into the Ark) confine them to their origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal kinds, and then leſs ground may be affigned; or otherwiſe the whole Earth is but ſufficient to contain the ſeveral Species: for if we admit of ſuch exuberant <hi>Plants</hi> as ſome Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors mention, few <hi>trees</hi> might fill ſuch a Garden: for the <hi>Jewiſh Targuns</hi> tells us, that the <hi>tree of life</hi> therein was 500 years journey high (the bredth they mention not,<note n="*" place="margin">Cujus al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudo erat Iteneris quingento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norum. <hi>Targ. Hier.</hi>
                     </note> but proportions therein muſt be alſo admitted.) And others<note n="†" place="margin">
                        <hi>Sir</hi> W. Rawleigh.</note> ſpeak of an <hi>Indian Figtree,</hi> which extends it ſelf in ſome Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries twenty or thirty miles: nor need we much doubt of the latter, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect it is poſſible by art of ſeveral in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layings to make a <hi>Vine,</hi> or any other exuberant <hi>Plant</hi> to extend as far. But we may ſuppoſe here was the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary of all beneficial <hi>plants;</hi> from whence the reſt of the world had their
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:101580:21"/>
                     <hi>Seeds, Cions,</hi> or <hi>Tranſplantations</hi> by winds or birds, or exhalations to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey their ſeeds into other Regions; and after by nature, art and induſtry, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſifyed into Plants preternatural to their originals.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That is pleaſant to the ſight,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 14.</note> 
                     <hi>or good for food.</hi> The <hi>Eye</hi> is the nobleſt part of man, being the Index of the Soul; and food is not onely a ſubject or ſuſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our whole, but eſpecially our <hi>Ocular</hi> part. The <hi>Eye</hi> is the firſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coverer of want or ſuperſluity of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenance; the <hi>eye</hi> is the firſt Judge of what is offenſive or inoffenſive to our appetite; for if the <hi>eye</hi> diſlike, we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, if approves, we eat, though it proves our poyſon; for the ſtomach oft ſurfets by the pleaſure of the <hi>eye,</hi> when the appetite takes its dimenſion from what the <hi>eye</hi> fees, and not what the little bag of the ſtomach contains; for nature is content with a little, if that little be good. And ſince nature hath confined her ſelf to certain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptacles for food, it were againſt its rules to fill thoſe with the unlimited appetites of the <hi>eye,</hi> unleſs we make our ſtomach to imitate our <hi>eyes,</hi> which are meerly ſatisfied with outward ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects;
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:101580:22"/>yet ſomething muſt be to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port their ſpirits. And therefore the <hi>eye</hi> may be pleaſed with what it ſees, the ſtomach ſatisfied not with what the <hi>eye</hi> ſees or <hi>pleaſant to the ſight,</hi> but with that which is <hi>good for food</hi> or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Tree of of Life in the midſt of the Garden.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 15.</note> I do not apprehend this tree to be planted <hi>in the midſt</hi> of the <hi>garden,</hi> as the Center to a Circumference, but rather as vertue is ſaid to be <hi>in the midſt,</hi> or to conſiſt in the mean or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diocrity, or temperance. To ſhew that if <hi>Adam</hi> could have been ſo temperate as not to aſpire to life till it were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed to him what kind of life he ſhould enjoy, or what Knowledge he ſhould know, he had been happy; for we ſhall find by the ſubſequent, that God imparted life and knowledge to him by degrees. Or poſſibly <hi>in the midſt</hi> may be taken for the <hi>chief,</hi> namely that among all the trees of the garden the <hi>tree of life</hi> was the chief; the garden being an Emblem of our bodies, our Heart being as is thought the ſeat of life <hi>in the midſt</hi> of our body. But it may well be ſaid alſo in the <hi>midſt,</hi> becauſe a tree of that ſtupendious
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:101580:22"/>height, as to be 500 years journey to the top as before mentioned, muſt needs be ſeen in all parts of the garden, the proper and true diſtance undiſcernable to the eye.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the tree of knowledge of good and evil.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 16.</note> This was not placed in the midſt as the tree of life, but as it were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed till God thought fit to impart the knowledge of its vertues, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid the uſe of it as he did: And though <hi>Adam</hi> did eat of it, yet it produced no ſuch Science as was ſatisfactory; for by eating he knew <hi>good and evil</hi> ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſedly, that he and we know not how to diſtinguiſh them, many things being good or bad according to doubting In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teations or Commands. But I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive as the vertue of one tree was to enliven, a Man to a ſound Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the other was a fruit of a marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, luxurious nature, and provoked <hi>Adam</hi> to the evil of Concupiſcence and Carnal deſires and actions; and ſo by eating knew both <hi>good</hi> and <hi>evil,</hi> that is, good whilſt they knew not <hi>Carna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity;</hi> evil in the knowing <hi>Carnalty:</hi> and Man hath the reward of his Libi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinous diſobedience, his body being ſo full of Diſeaſes and Infirmities, that
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:101580:23"/>the means of propagation ſeems to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get more Diſeaſes then Children.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 2. Ver. 10.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And a River went out of Eden to water the garden,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 17.</note> 
                     <hi>and from thence divided into four Chanels or Heads. Adam</hi> had ſeen the pleaſure of the Heavens in their glorious ornaments, and the pleaſures of the Earth in its various tapiſtry, whoſe odoriferous influence offorded alſo a moſt pleaſing breath; he was now ſhewed the pleaſures of the <hi>waters</hi> in <hi>Eden,</hi> where was a preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant River, or rather <hi>Fountain,</hi> which iſſued forth ſuch abundance of delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful waters, that they divided into four <hi>Chanels, Heads</hi> or <hi>Rivers;</hi> the Earth gave way to their gentle motions, and as it were left the rich valleys for them to dance upon whilſt it ſelf ſtill roſe higher and higher into Hills and Mountains meerly to overlook their pleaſures. And it is to be obſerved here that four is the next number re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated after 1.2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, as being the firſt Quadrat number of great uſe in Phyſical proportions; and poſſibly theſe three, <hi>Gold, Bdellium,</hi> and the <hi>Onyx,</hi> were only mention'd, &amp; no more to make
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:101580:23"/>the four ſtreams in the ſame Narrative ſeven, to ſhew the perfection of this <hi>Fountain.</hi> But ſome allude the four <hi>Chanels</hi> to the four parts of the Earth, <hi>Europe, Aſia, Africa</hi> and <hi>America:</hi> But doubtleſs they were neither known nor ſo divided in <hi>Moſes</hi> time, certainly not in <hi>Adams.</hi> Others allude them to the four Cardinal Vertues, but vertue was then ſo intire, that there needed no diſtinction; for pure vertue is not diviſible; for he that is truely juſt, muſt be Stout, Temperate and Prudent; and he that is ſtout muſt be temperate, and prudent muſt have the other ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. True vertue can admit of no ſeparation from it ſelf. The ſtreams of vertue come out of the Spring Head in <hi>Eden;</hi> and though it may ſeem to divide, yet every ſtream is contiguous to the Fountain, and ſo is vertue. Now where this <hi>Eden</hi> may properly be placed, and from whence theſe waters flow and return, I ſhall afford a larger Diſcourſe ſomething different from former notions both in Hiſtory and Philoſophy, and yet I hope rational.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="verse">
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:101580:24"/>
                  <head>Cap. 2. Ver. 11.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The name of the firſt is Piſon:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 18.</note> 
                     <hi>that is it which compaſseth Havilah, where there Gold.</hi> See my Introduction in my Book called <hi>Fodinae Regales.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 2. Ver. 12.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the gold of that land is good:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 19.</note> 
                     <hi>there is Bdellium and the Onyx Stone.</hi> I remember not my Author who ſaith that there are three eminent ſtones in the nature of Minerals, which were known to <hi>Adam;</hi> the one is a ſtone that hath a vertue of tranſmutation of Metals, and poſſibly this may be meant by gold; the other hath a vertue to diſcover the quality of all Senſibles and Vegetables, and this may be meant by Bdellium; and the third of a more tranſcending nature, by im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting to us all Angelical operations, and this may be meant by the Onyx: But whether or no there were or are ſuch ſtones by nature or art, the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs labours of others ſhall ceaſe my further inquiry. I confeſs there are ſuch admirable qualities in ſuch as are of common uſe, that I can run very high in my Credit, that in reſpect of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:101580:24"/>their ſolid temper they are more fit to retain ſuch Excellent vertues: As in the Loadſtone for Navigation and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence, the Saphire againſt Poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the Vitriol againſt Corruptions; and above all the <hi>Bolonian</hi> ſtone which upon Calcining receives and the beams of the Sun, and conſtantly after affords a ſoft light like the Gloworm. But whatever this Bdel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium was, which Sir <hi>Walter Rawleigh</hi> ſaith was a tree bearing Gum and Pearl, or what the Onyx or Beril were, the Text ſaith, <hi>the gold was good,</hi> and if ever ſince there hath been in Man ſuch a <hi>Sacra fames auri,</hi> a ſacred hunger of gold, I hope it is onely to get that gold which <hi>Piſon</hi> embraced, which gold onely is ſaid to be good; 'tis good whilſt it is here, but whether it be good to be got or carried from thence is the queſtion: but admit we have it, 'tis ſtill good ſo as it be not adulterated by the bad uſe of it. In ſhort, it is the Cordial to all humane Commerce, and therefore ſaid to be near a River, as more fitted for tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſportation; for as <hi>Adam</hi> was to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour at home, ſo upon the increaſe of his Poſterity he was to traffick abroad.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:101580:25"/>And it may be obſervable upon the number 3, that as <hi>Gold, Bdellium,</hi> and <hi>Onyx,</hi> were the firſt Jewels that nature offered to <hi>Adam</hi> before his fall; ſo <hi>Gold, Myrrh,</hi> and <hi>Frankincenſe</hi> were the firſt offers which were made to the ſecond <hi>Adam;</hi> the firſt by a wiſe God, the other by Wiſe men.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13,14" type="verses">
                  <head>Cap. 2. Ver. 13, 14.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the name of the ſecond River is Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hon:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 20.</note> 
                     <hi>the ſame is it which compaſſeth the Land of Aethiopia. The name of the third River is Hiddekel: that is in which goeth towards the Eaſt of Aſsyria: And the fourth River is Euphrates.</hi> Though the <hi>Scriptures</hi> differ in the names of the Countrys where theſe four <hi>Rivers</hi> are, as the Land of <hi>Havi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lah,</hi> call'd alſo <hi>Evilat,</hi> and <hi>Indies,</hi> ſo <hi>Aethiopia</hi> call'd <hi>Chuſh,</hi> and what thoſe Countrys contains; viz. <hi>Gold,</hi> which ſome adjutively call <hi>Bonum &amp; Electum,</hi> and others <hi>Electrum</hi> (which is the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſt compoſition of Gold:) and for <hi>Bdellium,</hi> which ſome eſteem a <hi>tree</hi> yielding ſweet <hi>Gum,</hi> others render it <hi>Carbuncules,</hi> and <hi>Oniones, Pearls:</hi> and for the <hi>Onyx,</hi> others render <hi>Beril, Lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des Chryſtali,</hi> or Chryſtal, and Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:101580:25"/>And though they differ as much in the Rivers <hi>Hiddekel</hi> (which ſome call <hi>Tygris</hi> and <hi>Diglath</hi>) and <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrates (Perath;)</hi> yet theſe ſeeming dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences are but noble <hi>invitations</hi> to the Study of <hi>Geography, Hydrography,</hi> and other <hi>Sciences,</hi> thereby to learn the Wonders of the <hi>Land</hi> and <hi>Deeps;</hi> inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuating alſo to us the richeſt <hi>Minerals, Plants,</hi> and <hi>Precious Stones;</hi> and that the natural progreſs of <hi>Creation</hi> may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily conduct us to them, for the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains direct us to their Streams or Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, thoſe Rivers to the Seas, the Sea carries us into and from other Creeks by Fluxes and Refluxes; and ſo the Art of <hi>Navigation</hi> is known and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd, and <hi>Merchandizing</hi> thereby en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encouraged: and it may not be amiſs to think that thoſe Names and Places of <hi>Territories, Rivers, Minerals, Plants,</hi> and <hi>Precious Jemms,</hi> and <hi>Stones,</hi> were purpoſely render'd <hi>ambiguous,</hi> that we may not be lazy in our Inquiries after them; for miſtakes are many times <hi>clews</hi> to guide us into certainties; and therefore it may be inquir'd whither the four great Rivers (as <hi>Ortelius</hi> tells us) which come from the <hi>Artic Pole,</hi> and are the <hi>origin</hi> and <hi>ſource</hi> of all Seas
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:101580:26"/>and Waters, were not thoſe four Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers here intended; and whether the <hi>circle</hi> of thoſe impaſſable Mountains about that <hi>Pole</hi> was not the defending <hi>Angel</hi> to the place of <hi>Paradice,</hi> the Sun keeping always an equal diſtance and heat from that <hi>Pole</hi> or <hi>Point;</hi> and though it be called the <hi>Frigid Zone,</hi> and the <hi>Antartick</hi> the <hi>Torrid,</hi> yet thoſe are but as <hi>imaginary</hi> as the <hi>Circles.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Text alſo teacheth us the <hi>Eaſt</hi> Point of the <hi>Compaſs;</hi> which though certain to every Countrey, yet every Countrey hath a different Eaſt from another according to its poſition, from the firſt appearance of the Sun upon their ſeveral <hi>Horizons:</hi> The next Point is <hi>Weſt, Gen.</hi> 12.8. which is oppoſite to every Eaſt or Riſing of the Sun to that <hi>Horizon</hi> where it appears. And Verſe the 9th. the <hi>South</hi> is mention'd, which is the middle Point when the Sun is at its heighth between its appearance or <hi>Aſcenſion,</hi> and diſappearance or <hi>Deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> upon any <hi>Horizon.</hi> Then in the 13th. Chapter verſe 14. the <hi>North,</hi> which is the oppoſite Point to the <hi>South,</hi> is mentioned, and placed before the other three as the moſt principal and certain Point, <hi>viz. Northward,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:101580:26"/>Southward, Eaſtward, Weſtward;</hi> that is, <hi>toward the North, South, Eaſt, Weſt.</hi> For I queſtion whether <hi>Moſes</hi> then knew the exact <hi>Points</hi> (as now we do by the uſe of the <hi>Loadſtone</hi>) which now are alſo taught us from the natural incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of all things to that <hi>North point</hi> by <hi>Plants,</hi> other <hi>Stones, Birds, Fiſhes, Waters, &amp;c.</hi> though poſſibly they might know the <hi>Load Star</hi> or <hi>North Star,</hi> yet I do not find that the Uſe of the <hi>Compaſs</hi> was known till about <hi>Chriſts</hi> Time, as I collect from the 27th. of the <hi>Acts</hi> verſe 12. where the <hi>Southweſt</hi> and <hi>Northweſt</hi> are mentioned; by which time they had got two Points more of the thirty two, which <hi>Compaſs</hi> now is the Seamans Alphabet. However we have ſufficient hints from this Text to traverſe the world for the better <hi>mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation</hi> of our <hi>Creators glory,</hi> by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight and benefit of his various and wonderful <hi>Operations</hi> and <hi>Products</hi> in the <hi>Elements.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 2. Verſe 15.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the Lord God took the man,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 21.</note> 
                     <hi>and put him into the garden to dreſs it, and to keep it.</hi> God knew that Idleneſs corrupts the beſt natures, and therefore Man
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:101580:27"/>was imployed in that humble vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;<note place="margin">Vt coleret legem &amp; obſervaret mandata ejus. <hi>Targ. Hier.</hi>
                     </note> for though God did at firſt create the kinds of all Plants, yet doubtleſs man had and yet hath an honeſt Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance to procreate a Diverſity of <hi>Species</hi> by Tranſplantations, Ingraſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Inoculatings, and other various Cultivations, which were Inceſtuous in other Creatures; but as I conceive allowed from the words here <hi>to dreſs and keep it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nature is of her ſelf rude in Exube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancies, ſo that if Art do not polite it, even the <hi>Winds, Froſts, Birds,</hi> and <hi>Beaſts</hi> do ſupply their Prunings. And 'tis not onely thus in Plants but other Creatures: the <hi>Eagle</hi> with her art breaks off her overgrown Beak, and renews her age; and Man himſelf would ſcarce be diſcerned from Beaſt, if Art and Care did not preſerve his Excreſcencies from defacing him. Nature is dull and idle; Art is the Soul of Nature; and Sedulity the Spirit or Mind that unites them. It is Motion that keeps all things Celeſtial and Sublunary in order; ſhould that ceaſe, 'tis thought the upper World would be in a flame, and our lower World a rude <hi>Chaos.</hi> That which we
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:101580:27"/>call Quiet is onely the reſult of a Lazy Mind, true Quiet is onely our Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in all orderly and allowable mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to the improving and preſerving Nature in her beſt form, whither con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered as to Individuals or Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16,17" type="verses">
                  <head>Cap. 2. Verſe 16, 17.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the Lord God commanded the man ſaying, Of every tree, &amp;c. thou mayeſt eat,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 22.</note> 
                     <hi>but of the tree of the knowledge of good and evil thou ſhalt not eat.</hi> Beſides the Law of Nature, whereby God had fixed to every Creature its order, as the Sun to rule the Day, and the Moon the Night, and Man next under God to have the Dominion of all Terreſtrial Creatures, God did think fit to exhibit to Man a Law of Trial, or rather a Command of Reaſon; for what need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God to command whenas there was nothing could have power but from him to diſobey? yet that Man might not think all things ſo tied to the order of Nature without variation, as that his Poſterity, which were not to have ſuch immediate converſation with God, might eaſily judge by the rule of Trial or Reaſon what was expedient
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:101580:28"/>for ſuch a Creature to perform to a Creator. And therefore did God command this Law of Trial or Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for it was but reaſon that God ſhould be obeyed (even in ſeeming Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vials) ſeeing Nature it ſelf, which he hath conſtituted, invites us to the ſame. 'Tis true, ſin came not till the Law: Now the Law is but the Memorials of Nature, which are that every thing ſhould be kept in order, Servants obey Maſters, Wives Husbands, Children Parents, Subjects their Superior Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates; (accoeding to ſeveral or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders:) and for want of which, Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions in States, Commotions in Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, do ariſe. God did know Man would diſobey, and God permitted him to diſobey, that by <hi>Adams</hi> example all his Poſterity might ſee the effect of Diſobedience to the Law of Reaſon; for it was moſt rational and juſt, that Man ſhould obey whatever God impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, eſpecially ſeeing God had given him ſuch a latitude, and ſo ſmall a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation.</p>
                  <p>And though we may think this Law of Reaſon too ſtrictly impoſed upon us, yet upon due inquiry we had no other way left us in our Creation to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:101580:28"/>expreſs our gratitude, but by this Law of Trial or Reaſon: for though we know not exactly what God hath im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered us to do or not do, what to act, or what to forbear; yet now by the rules of Reaſon we may judge what things are not fit to be done, and as much as in us lieth retire our Wills, Deſires, or Acts from them. As for example, <hi>Adam</hi> might thus have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed: I may eat of all Fruits except one or two; I have ſufficient by this freedom to pleaſe my taſt and ſight; why ſhould I be ſo ambitious by eating of the Tree of Life to live another life, whereas that wherein I live enjoys ſo many varieties? Why ſhould I be ſo curious to know more by eating of the Tree of Knowledge, whenas already I know ſo much as God thinks fit to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and I find that he is ſtill inſtructing me? And thus may every man judge by the Law of Reaſon whether he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeys God or no. The firſt examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is from the rules of Nature in the point of Obedience, and therefore 'tis ſaid, that <hi>Obedieuce is better then ſacrifice:</hi> for thoſe Rules which we have of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality or Chriſtianity are but the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of the Rules of Nature formed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:101580:29"/>rational Doctrines. I do not here include the Rules of Faith, and yet theſe are Rules of Trial and Reaſon; for what can be a ſafer Trial then to believe becauſe he commands? and then in reaſon how ſafe is it to believe that which may be hazardous to our Souls if we do not believe? And even here do we follow the Dictates of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, rather in obeying what is ſaid to be his command, then in diſobeying in thoſe things wherein we have not his command; but eſpecially in ſuch things wherein both in Nature and Reaſon we find Natural, Rational, and Chriſtian Injunctions. So that Gods command (how mean ſoever the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand may ſeem) was but to ſhew, that beſides the Law of Nature he did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit unto us a Law of Reaſon; and unleſs we return to his commands as well a rational ſubjection as a natural, we ſubmit as Irrational Creatures, but not as Men: and though poſſibly we cannot do otherwiſe then what is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, yet to will, to deſire, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the doing what we are command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to do, or prohibited from doing, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but prove <hi>an acceptable ſacrifice.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="verse">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:101580:29"/>
                  <head>Cap. 2. Verſe 17.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For in the day thou cateſt thereof.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 23.</note> I cannot but admire that the God of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ſhould ordain Diſunions, ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Sympathies</hi> and <hi>Antipathies,</hi> Even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Morning, Day and Night, Light and Darkneſs, Life and Death, Good and Evil: But when I conſider, that the Morning could not be known but by the terminating it with the Even, or the Day but by terminating it with Night, or the Light but by terminating it with Darkneſs, or Life but by terminating it by Death, or Good but by terminating it with Evil; I find that theſe terminations were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to our knowledge: for the ſeveral appellations of Light had been infinite, and thereby not fitted for a manifeſtation to us; and we muſt in their knowledge have been made coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual with God in glory and eternity, if they had not been thus manifeſted. But theſe appellations of Darkneſs were the Foils to ſet off the ſplendor of the Creation, and Evil was no other then as the evening to the morn, or as night to the day, or as darkneſs to the light; nor was death any other then
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:101580:30"/>the ſmooth tranſition to immortality, without fear, pain, or trouble, or onely a ſudden rapture or exſtacy in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effable change from terreſtrial con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments to ſuperceleſtial beatitudes. But from the breach of this command ariſeth the evil of evils, death of death, evening, night, and darkneſs. It is wonderful that <hi>Adam</hi> ſhould ſo much erre in the firſt trial which God made upon his obedience, and it is as won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful that God did command <hi>Adam</hi> to forbear that which was the beſt piece of Mankind, the Knowledge of good, and the termination of it; which was all the evil which then could be called evil: But Man was forbidden it doubtleſs that he might not conceit within himſelf that he had attained Knowledge from the virtue or nature of that Plant, but from the immediate gift and inſtruction of God; for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly God did inform him of the whole ſyſtem of the Creation, (by what we may collect by the foregoing and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing verſes) which was a ſufficient Knowledge; ſo that the Knowledge he had by this Tree was onely a Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Intoxication, and Knowledge of the termination of Life, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:101580:30"/>Knowledge of Diſtinction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween good and evil, (which Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges were forbidden;) his Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge before being a complete Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge conſiſting of a perpetual bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: for his Knowledge thereof was onely this, that goodneſs did now ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate by his diſobedience, and that life ſhould have a period or terminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which was a death; for by this Knowledge he got a Critical Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as we find by <hi>Eves</hi> Diſpute, that Diſobedience was the extreme of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, Death the extreme of Life; whereas whileſt he was under Gods teaching and inſtruction, he knew no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a quiet obedience, and an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent life, free from thoughts of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order, or fear of what ſhould happen; but now he knew the termination of that life, and that ſentence, <hi>In the day thou cateſt thereof thou ſhalt ſurely die.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thou ſhalt ſurely die.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 24.</note> If it be true what ſome Divines affirm, that <hi>Adam</hi> continued but ſix hours in Paradice, three before the eating the Fruit, and three after; I ſhould wonder how <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> ſhould be made ſenſible of death, ſeeing before his eating he was in a
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:101580:31"/>perfect and immortal condition; for a Blind man cannot underſtand a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, nor he that had never ſeen the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of Soul and Body know the effects of it; but certainly God did ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhew him the Horary Plant, (or other Creatures of the like nature) that hath its birth, flouriſh, and cloſe, in an hour, and is never ſeen after; or elſe taught him the way of Sacrificing Beaſts, and by their expiration to know his own, in caſe he diſobeyed this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; or elſe the nature of the Death was repreſented unto him, not as an immediate ſeparation of the Soul and Body, (for we find he lived many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years after) but his death, feretold here was a certainty of a future dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 2. Verſe 18.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the Lord God.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 25.</note> God is ſeven times repeated in the firſt Chapter, and the eighth time in the 26th. verſe; but in the ſecond Chapter verſe 7. where the Narrative of Mans Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is more fully deſcribed, it is expreſt that not God alone, but <hi>the Lord God ſaid.</hi> And ſo here concerning Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, the words <hi>Lord God</hi> are alſo uſed
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:101580:31"/>to teſtifie, that in the Creation and Making of both of them God did aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume another Title to himſelf then the ſingle word <hi>God; God</hi> ſeeming to be a name relating to all his Creatures, but <hi>Lord</hi> more peculiarly to Man and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, as before is hinted concerning Man onely.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Said.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 26.</note> This word <hi>ſaid</hi> is repeated ſeven times in the firſt Chapter, viz. verſe 3, 6, 9, 11, 14, 20, and 24. Now where it is thus expreſſed that God ſaid, <hi>Let there be,</hi> we muſt apprehend rather as an act, then a diſcourſe or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberation; for though we diſcuſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we act, proceeding from the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection of our Knowledge, and want of power to act (things being known to us onely in the abſtract) and when we do know them, we are uncertain of our Abilities to put them in action; yet God knows all things in the concrete, and his perfect Wiſdom and Power re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires no diſcourſe or deliberation: ſo that it muſt be underſtood in the ſeven other places, that God <hi>ſaid and did</hi> at one and the ſame inſtant; but in the eighth and ninth places the word <hi>ſaid</hi> is not to be underſtood as a <hi>fiat</hi> onely, but as a word of deliberation rather
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:101580:32"/>then action, which is inferred from the words <hi>Lord God,</hi> and <hi>Let us,</hi> and <hi>I will:</hi> for in all the entrances of the other parts of Creation it is ſaid onely <hi>Let there be;</hi> but in the 7th. and 18th. ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes (being the eighth and ninth time) <hi>the Lord God ſaid, Let us make,</hi> and <hi>I will make.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is not good for man to be alone.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 27.</note> Man is a noble and ſociable creature; a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſe and monaſtick temper neither be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes him, nor was ſafe in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and moſt eminent time of <hi>Adam,</hi> much leſs in ours: for it oft produceth ſuch prodigious Copulations, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tranatural Reſtrictions, as Nature is as much injur'd in the one as in the other; therefore to be avoided as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not good for <hi>Adam</hi> nor his Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And of all Societies ſurely that is moſt complacent that conſiſts of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Tempers.</p>
                  <p>Yet ſome of the Fathers hold, that Man is never alone when he is alone; Angels or Spirits that attend his moſt private meditations are ſuch contenting Companions, that though he conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth with no other body, yet his Mind hath the fruition of an ineffable Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: ſo that in reſpect of the Mind it is
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:101580:32"/>good to be alone, but in reſpect of the Body it is not good to be alone. And therefore to prevent that ſolitarineſs or other beaſtial ſociety, God did make the Woman to be the Wife or Conſort to Man. And it is not good for either to be ſeparate, as to leave the other to be alone; he or ſhe that doth it is guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the breach of that originally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted good thus provided for them by a Conjunction: for when it is ſaid, <hi>They ſhall be as one,</hi> that is, of one ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; he is not to be alone, nor ſhe alone, but both to make an unſeparable ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſo as to leave all other Relations or Intereſts to be two, all one, or two alone, and yet not alone ſo long as they two concenter in an happy and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Unity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I will make an help meet for him.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 28.</note> That is, I will make him into ſuch a poſture or condition, that a meet help ſhall be extracted from him, and ſo to be to him as his Companion.</p>
                  <p>Here I muſt obſerve, that in all the Works of Creation the words <hi>Let there be,</hi> and <hi>Let us,</hi> ſeem to be reſults of plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, and may relate to the Trinity or Angels, or ſome ſubordinate Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; but in making Woman God
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:101580:33"/>ſpeaks it in the Singular Number, <hi>I will make;</hi> to ſhew, that God did more appropriate to himſelf the making of Woman then any Creature of the whole Creation; for ſhe cannot but be apprehended the moſt ſingular and unexpreſſible piece: for when <hi>Adam</hi> had ſeen the Light, Firmament, Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, Earth, with all their Ornaments, and all the varieties of Fowl and Beaſts, and could diſcourſe with them in their own Dialects, (and doubtleſs ſome of them might have afforded a ſatisfacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry contentment in a Converſation;) yet (I ſay) none of thoſe glorious Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (either Celeſtial or Terreſtrial) were thought fit Helps for him: and therefore <hi>the Lord God ſaid,</hi> (it muſt be ſo implied) <hi>I will make</hi> a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent piece then all my former pieces, a Woman; which ſhall be a more meet Help for Man then all thoſe glorious things which I have created: and God ſeems to appropriate the Womans making more peculiarly to himſelf; for <hi>fecit (he made)</hi> is applied to the uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality of all Creatures; <hi>faciamus (let us make)</hi> applied to Man; but <hi>faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am (I will make)</hi> applied onely to Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. I ſhall adde this, that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductive
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:101580:33"/>Maſs of all Creatures was made out of nothing, and Man in his Elementary Parts was made out of that Maſs which was made out of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and Woman was made out of him, who was made out of them, that were made out of nothing: ſo that <hi>Ex nihilo nil fit;</hi> ſhe, and we, and all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in their moſt beauteous appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances, are ſtill but appearances, mere nothings; and yet nothing is, nothing ought to be, more helpful to Man then Woman; for whileſt that nothing is ſomething, ſhe is to be a meet Help,<note place="margin">Faciamus ei mulie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, ut ſit ſuſtentacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſa ejus. <hi>Targ. Hier.</hi>
                     </note> a Help meet, for him for whom ſhe is made, &amp; to whom ſhe is conjoyned, and that is her duty; and to this end woman was made, to be a Help meet for him, <hi>(adjutorium)</hi> an helper, a delight and eaſe to Man, and that in the moſt meet, apt, fit, and agreeable manner. The <hi>Arabick</hi> adde to <hi>adjutorium (e regione ejus)</hi> that is, an Help, but ſtill ſuch an Help as ſhould keep within the bounds, limits, or <hi>region</hi> of Mans government: and that certainly was the intent of Gods making of her. And if ſhe proves otherwiſe, methinks I hear God ſay, I will make her to be a meet Help for Man; if ſhe will not, ſhe ſhall know
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:101580:34"/>more ſorrow then <hi>Eve.</hi> And certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Man is to take care that he lays no ſervile (or ſuch other) Impoſitions upon her, then ſhe is able to bear: ſhe is to be a meet Help, to go hand in hand in helping and ſupporting their mutual Intereſts. This is all the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference I can obſerve; an help does imply that one is to be aſſiſted, ſo that it is his part to give the firſt motion to all affairs, and ſhe is to help without diſpute, and not to run away or ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from the burthen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19,20" type="verses">
                  <head>Cap. 2. Verſe 19, 20.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And out of the ground the Lord God formed every beaſt of the field,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 29.</note> 
                     <hi>and every fowl of the air, and brought them unto A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, to ſee what he would call them: and whatſoever Adam called every living crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that was the name thereof. And Adam gave names to all cattel, and to the fowl of the air, and to every beaſt of the field.</hi> Man being made of a cleer <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellect</hi> and inſight into all Creatures un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his ſubjection, <hi>God</hi> as a perfect Workman having made ſo exquiſite an <hi>engine</hi> to put in motion thoſe vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous parts of Creation, <hi>tried</hi> how thoſe excellencies with which he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:101580:34"/>him would <hi>operate;</hi> for the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del</hi> or <hi>framing</hi> of any piece to ſuch an end as it was deſigned, ſhews onely its outſide and not its <hi>vertue,</hi> till it doth <hi>operate</hi> to that end. And certainly as <hi>Adam</hi> was ſo <hi>qualified</hi> in his <hi>Intellects,</hi> ſo are we in ſome proportion; for could we but follow old <hi>Bias</hi> his Rule of <hi>Noſce teipſum, Know thy ſelf,</hi> we ſhould find by <hi>Anatomy</hi> the perfect compoſure of all <hi>mechanick engines:</hi> For inſtance, by the <hi>circulation</hi> of the <hi>bloud</hi> (more clearly diſcovered to us by Dr. <hi>Harvey</hi> then in former ancient Authors) which <hi>circulation</hi> muſt not be underſtood as moving by the rule and juſt proportion of a <hi>circle,</hi> but rather by <hi>retrogreſſions;</hi> for very few are <hi>circular,</hi> but rather <hi>perpendicular oblique, &amp;c.</hi> and thoſe who will buſie their brains about a <hi>perpetual motion,</hi> may ſooner obtain it for ſixty or eighty years from <hi>perpendicular</hi> and <hi>oblique</hi> motions of our bloud for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years, then by any <hi>circular motion</hi> to <hi>perpetuity.</hi> And if I have time to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt my notions into <hi>practical</hi> rules, I doubt not but to make as evident a <hi>Syſtem</hi> of <hi>Philoſophy</hi> as <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> (who makes the <hi>Sun</hi> go round, and the <hi>Earth</hi> ſtand ſtill;) or <hi>Copernicus</hi> (who makes
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:101580:35"/>the <hi>Sun</hi> ſtand ſtill, and the <hi>Earth</hi> turn round;) and therein ſhew that the cauſe of <hi>Fluxes</hi> and <hi>Refluxes</hi> of the Sea, and the <hi>Circular</hi> motions of the <hi>Planets,</hi> are moſtly <hi>deceptions,</hi> and thoſe caus'd from <hi>perpendicular</hi> and <hi>oblique impreſſions</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing their <hi>vertiginations.</hi> Alſo by this inquiry into our ſelves we may learn the uſe of the <hi>Almbecks,</hi> and all ſorts of <hi>diſtillations,</hi> and indeed all the <hi>Seven Liberal Sciences,</hi> and <hi>Seven Mechanick Arts.</hi> And thoſe who are ſo large in their Conſtitutions, as to drive at a more <hi>univerſal knowledge</hi> of Creatures, may by a due inſpection into them gain the whole Body of <hi>Philoſophy;</hi> which doubtleſs were ſooner obtained if we could be informed of the true <hi>primitive Names</hi> of all Creatures, and the <hi>myſtical Interpretations</hi> of theoſe <hi>Names;</hi> which ſome ſay <hi>Selomon</hi> attained to as far as concerned <hi>Plants,</hi> and thereby under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the nature of them even from the <hi>Cedar</hi> to the <hi>Hyſop;</hi> which Book of his is mentioned in the <hi>Holy Writ,</hi> but is either utterly loſt or conceal'd, (which is equal to us) and is the great error of Mankind in not <hi>communicating</hi> what we know; for by wanting theſe <hi>impartments</hi> we make moſt things <hi>dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolical</hi>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:101580:35"/>which are onely <hi>Secrets of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture unrevealed:</hi> and thus we wilfully baniſh our ſelves out of the <hi>Paradice</hi> of Knowledge, either by not <hi>ſeeing, try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or inquiring</hi> into the nature of our ſelves or other Creatures, or not freely <hi>imparting</hi> what we do know, or fooliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>condemning</hi> or <hi>cenſuring</hi> the kind and laborious <hi>impartments</hi> of others. And hereupon even ſome of the pious <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> of our <hi>Church</hi> were condemned as <hi>Hereticks</hi> for aſſerting the <hi>Antipodes,</hi> which no <hi>Geographers</hi> now diſpute: and hence the <hi>Loadſtone,</hi> and other marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous effects of the natures of other pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Creation,</hi> were at firſt eſteemed <hi>Witchery,</hi> which now are ſafely allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and hence came the loſs of thoſe <hi>Impartments,</hi> of which <hi>Pancirollus</hi> hath writ a Book called <hi>De rebus perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Some are of opinion, that if the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal names of thoſe Creatures were known, we alſo ſhould know their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive and intrinſick natures; which <hi>Adam</hi> did know when he firſt fix'd their diſtinct and different names. And herein did God as it were entertain <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> and enrich his Knowledge by all the ways and progreſſes of the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:101580:36"/>teaching him the nature and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of all things: ſo that there was no need of any addition but what God himſeſt imparted; the other (as I ſaid) was but Intoxicated Knowledge, or a Fruit that would rather blind his Knowledge then improve it. And yet for all theſe impartments and ſociety, God did not think Beaſts fitting Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions for Man, for he was to have the dominion over them, and therefore not fit to be equal or meet Helpers to him: ſo that (as it were upon further conſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration) <hi>God ſaith</hi> again, <hi>But as for A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam there was not found an Help meet for him.</hi> So then in order to ſuch an Helper:</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 2. Verſe 21.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the Lord God cauſed a deep ſleep to fall upon Adam,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 30.</note> 
                     <hi>and he ſlept.</hi> Here ſeems to be a ſupernatural and a natural ſleep; the ſupernatural (which <hi>Adam</hi> fell into being cauſed by God for the end which was deſign'd, the producing of <hi>Eve;</hi>) the natural ſleep, <hi>and he ſlept;</hi> ſleep being as adequate to nature as night to day, or darkneſs to light. In our natural we have Dreams, in our ſupernatural Revelations; and every
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:101580:36"/>ſuch Revelation (when true) is an <hi>Eve,</hi> or an Helper either in our Devotions or Actions. But all the difficulty is to judge them; and certainly they ought to be as evident and manifeſt to us, as <hi>Eve</hi> was to <hi>Adam</hi> after he awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: for Phancy does ſo deceive men, that we take thoſe repreſentations which we have in our ſleep to be real, which are but imaginary, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations which Nature affords us du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the receſs of our Spirits to be Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelations, which in truth are nothing but <hi>Chymera's.</hi> I cannot ſay but God may impart ſuch truths to us; but then they will be always attended with ſome real and warrantable ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences: But here we find tht is leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſened <hi>Adams</hi> Perfection, after a nap he loſt a Rib, to ſhew that ſleep in our beſt Conſtitution takes ſomething from us in the abbreviation of our Lives.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And he took out one of his ribs, and cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up the fleſh inſtead thereof.</hi> The cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity of <hi>Anatomiſts</hi> concerning our Ribs is not to be a rule to our belief in the Text; or whether we ſhould diſpute of the truth from the number of thoſe which remain, for it is impoſſible to know what the Original of the number
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:101580:37"/>of Ribs were.<note place="margin">Deus acce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit unam ex coſtis ejus, illa eſt coſta de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cima ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia lateris dextri. <hi>Targ. Hier.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Gallen</hi> affirms, that Man hath now but eleven, but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Jewiſh Targum Adam</hi> had thirteen; and then the odd Rib being taken out, twelve remain: now <hi>Eve</hi> being made like to him, ſhe had then twelve Ribs alſo, equal in number to thoſe were left to him; but accounting her whole ſelf one Rib, ſhe had thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen. But to paſs this; the more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Anatomiſts</hi> hold that Man hath twelve Ribs, whereof five are called true or perfect Ribs, becauſe they are Circular; ſeven baſtard or imperfect Ribs, becauſe they want that proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Now there may be made a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, Whether <hi>Eve</hi> were made of one of thoſe which were perfect and circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, or thoſe which were imperfect; for had he not parted with ſome of his perfection, he could not ſo eaſily have fallen into error. On the other fide, had ſhe been partaker of his perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhe would not ſo eaſily have been tempted; or rather by dividing their perfection, both of them became ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to imperfection.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="verse">
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:101580:37"/>
                  <head>Cap. 2. verſe 22.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And of the Rib,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 32.</note> 
                     <hi>which the Lord God had taken from Man, made he a Woman.</hi> The <hi>Latines</hi> uſe the word <hi>aedificavit,</hi> or built, to ſhew that ſhe was to be an houſe, or manſion place; but the <hi>Engliſh</hi> tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors uſe the word <hi>made.</hi> And it is here obſervable, that ſhe was not ſaid to be created as Man, in the Image of God, or after his likeneſs, nor for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, nor framed; but Made, a word of a leſſer ſignification, relating to the temperament of her body only. Nor was ſhe made of the duſt or purer part of the Earth, but of a Bone, which is the hardeſt, dryeſt, coldeſt, and moſt terreſtrial part of Man, according to Phyſicks. Nor had ſhe the Breath of Life breathed into her Noſtrills, but that Life <hi>Eve</hi> had went with the Bone. Nor is it ſaid ſhe became a Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſoul, her ſoul being as it were the ſame, or a Ray of his: the truth is, ſhe was abſtracted either out of a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poriferous temper, which is all Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, or from ſome ſuparnatural <hi>efflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vium;</hi> or that ſhe was like him in his Creation, unlike after the ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But this may be obſerved, that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:101580:38"/>when God made <hi>Eve</hi> he took a Rib from <hi>Adam,</hi> and of it made Woman; ſo that he could not but fall, being leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſened in the perfection of his Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Now when <hi>Jeſus</hi> was born of a Virgin, God took that part from her which the woman had before from <hi>Adam,</hi> ſo he became perfect; as by this, God did in a manner bring forth ſuch a ſubſtantial revelation from <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam's</hi> ſleep, that it ſeemed to be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued divine Apparition. But (as I ſaid) that there are two ſorts of ſleep, ſo there are two ſorts of Women, the one Snpernatural and moſt civinely qualified, the other meer Natural, Fantaſtical, and <hi>Quelque choſe:</hi> the firſt a revealed bleſſing from God, the other only diſturbers of the mind, and diſtraction to mans quiet ſleep and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſement.</p>
                  <p>But ſhe was made of a Rib; from whence it happens that mans, heart which was ſurrounded all with Bones, now lyes open; ſo that all its Loves and deſires had no fence againſt her; for we ſee even <hi>Adam, when God brought her to him,</hi> ſo ſoon as he ſaw her was immediately tranſported: and <hi>Adam
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:101580:38"/>ſaid</hi> with a divine implicite aſſeverati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Hac tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re non rar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus creabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur mulier ex viro. <hi>Targ. Hier</hi>
                     </note> This glorious piece which thou haſt brought to me <hi>is Bone of my bone, and Fleſh of my fleſh.</hi> As if he ſhould have added, this is ſhe that (like my Bones) is to be my helper, and ſupporter to all my regular motions; ſhe that (like my bones) ought to give ſtability, rectitude, and form to all my actions; This is ſhe that (like my fleſh) is to be the Pillow of my Body; this is ſhe which is to be as a Wall or Safeguard to all my Vital functions; this is ſhe that according to the property of Fleſh, is to allay the rage of all my natural heates. Now it is here to be obſerved, that God brought all Beaſts to <hi>Adam,</hi> who only gave Names to them, but no Inſtructions, they being uncapable of reaſon; but when God brought the Woman to <hi>Adam, Adam</hi> began firſt with inſtruction, and taught her her duty towards him, which was in ſhort, that Look of what ever uſe the bone is within us, or the Fleſh without us, ſhe is to act theſe parts for mans pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And brought her unto the man.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 33.</note> From hence probably came the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> and <hi>Roman</hi> Cuſtoms, to lead the Spouſe
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:101580:39"/>between two to the Nuptialls: and the <hi>Latins</hi> ſtill continue the phraſe of <hi>duce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re uxorem,</hi> which we call <hi>Marrying,</hi> and is a kind of tacit compulſion on her part, more to repreſent her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty towards that ceremony, then any diſinclination of Nature in operating to a mutual contact, there being a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Sympathy lodgd in the progreſſes of propagation, which tends to coi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which future, times have made more ceremonial, reſtrictive, or coer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 2. Ver 23.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And Adam ſaid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 34.</note> 
                     <hi>this is now Bone of my Bone, and Fleſh of my fleſh.</hi> Anatomiſts reckon 302 Bones in Mans body; ſo that this Rib it ſeems was the bone of all theſe bones, or the ſpring of all the reſt; and they are the moſt inflexible of all the parts of the body; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to aſſiſt that temper he adds, that ſhe was alſo fleſh of his fleſh (though there is no mention of any fleſh ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from him.) Now the Fleſh is the moſt ſoft and tender part, conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a pleaſing ruddy colour, to ſhew that ſhe ſhould not only be ſteady in her affections, but tender, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:101580:39"/>gentle, and amiable in all her proceedings towards him.</p>
                  <p>And when he had thus declard her Conſtitution, he gave her a name, and ſaid,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>She ſhall be called Woman becauſe ſhe came out of Man.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 35.</note> She was not named like to the beaſts,<note place="margin">Hanc deus vult voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re viragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem quia ex viro de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumpta est<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Targ. Hier</hi>
                     </note> who had names giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en them without any reaſon given for impoſing their names upon them; but here is a reaſon given, <hi>i. e. ſhe ſhall be called Woman,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Becauſe ſhe came out of man:</hi> And this was to teach her her original, and alſo how ſhe ſhould demeane her ſelf towards him. It ſhews Mans ſuperiority to the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; becauſe that which is derived cannot be equall to that from which it was derived: it ſhews alſo her uſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by obedience; and this is not an humane, (as ſome Woman would have it) but a meer Natural, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a divine impoſition upon the ſex; for the Bone cannot but move when it is incited, nor the Fleſh cannot but expoſe it ſelf to outward accidents; ſo thoſe pieces of natural Kindneſſes which we call Obedience, (and 'tis pitty any Woman ſhould ſtumble at the word) are but the Inſtruments of
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:101580:40"/>Nature, &amp; would prove eaſy and natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral if it were not for a wilful reſiſtance which deſtroys the Fabrick, Harmony, &amp; Cooperation of the Union between Man and Woman, as is between the whole Man and his Fleſh and Bones. From which diſunion the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb comes, that <hi>Woman is a Woe to Man;</hi> but the Latine conceit is more kind, and makes <hi>Mulier quaſi Mollior,</hi> a more ſoft, tender, and delicate Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture then Man; and the <hi>Hebrew Eva,</hi> fignifying <hi>Viva</hi> or <hi>Vivens,</hi> being as it were the life or living part of Man, that is, when they execute the Duty which belongs to the preſervation of Man, and when they do thus perform their function.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 2. Ver 24.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore (or for that cauſe) a Man ſhall leave his Father and Mother,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 36.</note> 
                     <hi>and cleave to his Wife, and they two ſhall be one Fleſh.</hi> This ſeems to be ſpoken in an exſtacy upon <hi>Adams</hi> beholding of her Excellencies;<note place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>perabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ex do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ipſius cubilis pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris ſui &amp; matris ſuae. <hi>Targ Hier</hi>
                     </note> for <hi>Adam</hi> had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Father but God, nor no other Mother but Earth, both of which he forſook when he was tempted by her to Eat the Fruit which God his Father
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:101580:40"/>had forbidden to eat, and neglected his Mother Earth, which he ſhould have been dreſſing and keeping, when he ſpent his time in deſputing the queſtion with her and the Serpent. But this was intended rather for a Law to them that were to ſucceed him, for neither he nor we are to make our Kindneſs to a Wife ſuperintendent to the Commands of God: we owe a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive duty to one, Conjunctive duty to the other. For though 'tis ſaid the man and his Wife ſhall be one Fleſh, yet the Father, Mother, and Child are one fleſh alſo. The myſtery that is to be enquired is, which hath the greater Unity of Fleſh, the Parent and Child, or the Man and Wife; the Child is but the effect of the Woman, the ſubject of propagation, and when the effect is effected, the cauſe, Liga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and vertue of producing the effect, is as it were loſt and Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated in the ſubſtantialls of the effect; but the Husband and Wife, ſo long as the Union Continues, have conſtant deſires to produce the effects of their deſires; and deſires, ſo long as they are in any ability to effect, are far more ſtrong and fervent, then
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:101580:41"/>thoſe are which have received the end or ſatisfaction to their deſire. So that upon the continuance of this Love or deſire they may juſtly be ſaid to have a more proper conjunction and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, of Fleſh then Parents and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and God and Nature ties them to a more ſecret affection then can be had to Father and Mother. And that which may fitly be added is, that man is not to forſake his Wiſe with his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, nor his Parents which his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; and this Command to Man belongs to the Wowan alſo; for we may ſee a ſad example not onely in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> but <hi>Eve,</hi> in forſaking God and his precepts; for although the man was only forbidden to eat of the Fruit, yet they two being one, the Command to one was the Law to both; nor did the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent ſo much as tempt her with this Argument. And this may be added, that the <hi>Latin</hi> calls Fleſh <hi>Carv,</hi> and <hi>Chara</hi> (Deer) in the Adjective; and <hi>Charitas,</hi> which is a relative word to them both, ſhews that this deareneſs or fleſhly affection between Man and Wife ought to conſiſt of perfect Love and Charity towards each other.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="verse">
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:101580:41"/>
                  <head>Cap. 2. verſe 25.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And they were both Naked,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 37.</note> 
                     <hi>and were not aſhamed.</hi> Shame (as I conceive) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds either from Pride or ſenſe of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or inward imperfections: Now they had not the Armor of the <hi>Rheno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceros,</hi> nor the Furrs of the <hi>Ermine,</hi> or Wool of the tender <hi>Lambe,</hi> or the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of Plumes which adorn the Fowls of the <hi>Aire:</hi> But they had a perfect reaſon to continue naked or covered ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the nature of ſituation, from which the other could not depart were they never ſo burthenſome, when ere they changed their Climates.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Adam</hi> well knowing that thoſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward coverings were but the Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their tempers, ſo that <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> could not be aſhamed in the want of theſe ſuperfluities, nor could they be guilty of imperfections being perfectly formed; their minde could repreſent nothing to them but harmleſs thoughts, their ſhape nothing but exact proportions, the motion of their Blood was according to the Courſe of nature, no obſtructions from the ſpleen, or diffidence of their mutual goodneſs, to raiſe or alter the Current of nature
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:101580:42"/>(to a bluſh, or dejection of their eyes, filled onely with the Beames of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and conſtancy to God and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.) A Condition of life apt to meet with envious and ſubtil diſturbers of ſo happy a Calme and quiet: they were united in perfect Innocency, and being made Male and Female, <hi>Moſes</hi> renders them to us in the moſt eminent expreſſion,<note place="margin">Et erunt ambo ipſt Japienties. <hi>Targ. Hier</hi>
                     </note> as in the firſt Chapter, to which I return for the Reaſons in the Proem.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="27" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 1. Veſe 27.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>So God created Man.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 38.</note> That is, after he was made,<note place="margin">ſed non mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rari fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt in gloria. <hi>Targ Hier</hi>
                     </note> framed, and formed out of nothing, he was ſaid to be Created, the matter or form, or both, of which he was made, being peculiar to Man, or more eminent in him then in any other Creature: for the word Created is mentioned but to 3 opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; 1ſt. to the Heavens and the Earth, next to the <hi>Whale,</hi> and 3ly. to Man; and they that would advance the invocation of the Trintiy in the Conſultative part of Mans Creation from the words <hi>Let us</hi> in the 7. Verſe, may be aſſiſted from this conſummative Verſe (where the word <hi>Created</hi> is three
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:101580:42"/>times repeated, viz. <hi>ſo God Created Man in his own Image,</hi> (referring to the firſt perſon;) 2ly. <hi>In the Image of God Created he him,</hi> (referring to the ſecond Perſon;) 3ly. <hi>Male and Female Created he them,</hi> (referring to the Holy Ghoſt.)</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In his own Image.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 39.</note> After his <hi>like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> as in the 26. verſe, being here left out; which ſhews that it inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded one and the ſame thing. Now what this Image or Likeneſs is I may borrow from <hi>Plato,</hi> who ſaith, that there was a certain <hi>Idea,</hi> platform, or inward repreſentation of all things in God before they were; according to which the matter being created, the formes by which things were diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed were alſo made: ſo that this Image and Likeneſs ſignifies no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then that Man ſhould be made like to that <hi>Idea</hi> or imagination which God deſigned to that Creature; or as I conceive that this World (as <hi>Spagne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> in his <hi>Enchiridion Phyſicae</hi>) is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but God manifeſted, and ſo ſaw himſelf as in a Glaſs; &amp; Man the little World is his Image or Likneſs in the Epitome of that great Image or mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of God, <hi>Tanquam in minori ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo;</hi> but to conceit any Figuratine or
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:101580:43"/>Lineamentive Image of God St. <hi>Agu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Let him be curſed that referreth the Deity of God to the Lineaments of mans Body;</hi> and <hi>Philo</hi> ſaith, <hi>That God is not partaker of humane formes, nor can humane bodies be partakers of the form divine:</hi> but as Sir <hi>Walter Rawliegh</hi> ſaith from ſome other, <hi>that if any thing comes neer the ſimilitude of God, it is more the virtue that is in Man then the figure.</hi> Right Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is the Image of God, and Man hath in his mind a certain ſimilitude of God; and this is ſafe to believe, ſafe to continue in by a vertuons &amp; good life. But according to the Context of the words, <hi>So God created Man in his Image,</hi> may be conſidered that he was Created according to his Geometrical Image in all things conſiſting of number, weight, and meaſure. <hi>In his Image,</hi> even of the duſt, being within the Image of the repreſentative World: <hi>In his Image,</hi> participating of the univerſal breath and peculiar ſoul: <hi>In his Image,</hi> by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipating of his general manifeſtation and enjoyment of all Creatures: <hi>In his Image,</hi> by a ſocial and Communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive nature: <hi>In his Image,</hi> by a peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar Love to his Elect: And <hi>in his Image,</hi> by multiplication and dominion: So
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:101580:43"/>that God is Man in great, and Man is God in Little.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Male and Female Created he them.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 40.</note> Some do from hence conceit: that they were Created <hi>Hermaphrodites;</hi> but whoever conſults rightly with Phyſicks will find almoſt an impoſſibility in that Conceit, for the intent of Male and Female was propagation, which would rather be hindred then advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by ſuch improbable Copulation, where the Agent and Patient muſt at one time naturally have a mutal ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration or deſire with each other; and by this preternatural form which are in ſome, they would make a perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the imperfection, or rather exu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burancy, which happens to others of Humane race. So that by Male and Female is to be underſtood, that Man was made the Male, or Maſculine, or Agent; Woman, or the Wife, the Feminine, or the Patient: And though it is ſaid that God created them Male and Femane, yet Grammarians know, that where an Adjective hath relation to two Subſtantives (apt for life) of the ſingular number, and different gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, the Adjective ſhall be of the plural, and of the gender of the moſt
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:101580:44"/>principal word; ſo it is ſaid, <hi>Creavit eos,</hi> not <hi>eas;</hi> they were not both Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Males and Females, but man was Created male, and Woman the femal, and ſo created he then. And here is to be obſerved, that the word Created is applied to the Woman, though in the whole order of her pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction it is only ſaid that ſhe was made; which ſhews, that when ſhe was united, and made one with man as man and wife, ſhe was adopted into that title of Creation, and that not ſingle but united; for Creating is a Maſculine word, making or Produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction femine: And God did think fit to Crown the Conjugal union of Man and Wife with the Title of Creation, when as ſhe being not joyned muſt be content without that Title; yet this may be ſaid for her, that Man by Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation was made out of nothing, or at moſt out of the duſt, but ſhe was made out of ſomthing, or Duſt enlive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Jews</hi> in one of their <hi>Targums</hi> are moſt exact, who ſay, that <hi>God made Man in his Image, according to the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of God Created he him, with</hi> 248. <hi>members, and</hi> 365 <hi>Nerves, and covered
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:101580:44"/>him over with a Skin, and filled it with Fleſh and Blood, Male and Female crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted he them;</hi> in noble form, &amp; diſtinct ſexes, of whoſe excellency and geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trical proportions I have writ in the preceding Chapters; but being crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, made, framed, formed, whether in that manner which I have menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, I ſhall not diſpute.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="28" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 1. Verſe 28.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And God bleſſed them and ſaid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 41.</note> 
                     <hi>Be fruitful and multiply.</hi> I have obſerved that the word <hi>Created</hi> is uſed onely in the univerſal Creation in the works of the 5. days, and in the 6th. day in the Creation of Man; ſo here I obſerve, that this <hi>Benediction</hi> is onely uſed in this place, &amp; in the 5th. daies work, and in no other parts of the ſeven daies, but only in the ſeaventh day, where 'tis ſaid, <hi>God bleſſed &amp; ſanctified it.</hi> The reaſon of this is, that all the works of the other days either produced no ſutable <hi>ſpecies,</hi> as the <hi>Sun, Stars,</hi> &amp;c. or if they did, yet it was by a natural production, without any Local action or copulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as Trees, Herbs, &amp;c. but Fiſh, Foul, and Man have Local and active motions of production, one only natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:101580:45"/>the other natural and voluntary. Now to the ſeventh day or Sabbath there is a benediction or ſanctification, but not the addition of fructification or multiplication for reſt; or the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath doth only quiet and preſerve the Creation, but Action continues it with multitudes of <hi>ſpecies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>However this was the firſt Joynt Commiſſion which was given to man and wife, and if we may believe the <hi>Jews, Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> had in their chaſte Wedlock 30. Sons and 30. Daughters; whereas extravagant tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers ſeldom enjoy ſuch a multiplying Condition: and we ſee that in thoſe countries, where Laws of Wedlock are ſacredly obſerved, the people are more numerous then in other Countries where there is a greater Liberty; for the Wombe is quickly vitiated, by Commixtures, and either deſtroyed by heat, or over cooled by diverſities.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And repleniſh the Earth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 42.</note> 
                     <hi>and ſubdue it.</hi> In the <hi>Syriack</hi> it is, <hi>Fill the Earth</hi> inſtead of <hi>repleniſh;</hi> and in the <hi>Arabick, Poſſeſs it</hi> inſtead of <hi>Subdue it;</hi> which are bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the other, for <hi>repleniſh</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies a filling of that which was once full and now empty, and <hi>ſubduing</hi> that
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:101580:45"/>which was once conquered and rebeld again, which here could not be, if we believe that there was no Man till <hi>Adam,</hi> or Cultivations till he practiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them; or elſe it muſt be thus under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, that beſides the productions of nature (I mean as to terreſtrial things) there are productions of Art; the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions of nature are thoſe properly which were at firſt created, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions of Art are thoſe with which mans Induſtery (under the title of till<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Earth) <hi>Adam</hi> did, and man ſince doth, <hi>repleniſh</hi> the Earth; as by Sow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Seed and Planting Trees he cauſed Herbs and Trees to grow, which is a repleniſhment to the firſt Creation; and by plowing, digging, dreſſing, &amp;c. of grounds, he may be ſaid to ſubdue the Earth, or conquer thoſe extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangancies of nature, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe without mans aſſiſtance would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy thoſe Vegetables which are moſt profitable for mans uſe; and thus he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhes and ſubdues it, or thus fills &amp; poſſeſſeth the earth. And this was the ſecond joynt Commiſſion to <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> wherein both were enjoyned from Idleneſs; the Man was not to work a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, nor the Woman alone, but he to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:101580:46"/>ſet on the work, and ſhe to help and aſſiſt him in proſecution of it.</p>
                  <p>The third clauſe of their Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was, to</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Have dominion over the Fiſh of the Sea,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 43.</note> 
                     <hi>and over the Fowls of the Air, and over every Living thing that creepeth or moveth upon the face of the Earth.</hi> The word Dominion ſignifies the chief authority or power of ruling or taming, all which man hath over all other creatures; God did not give them a natural power to reſiſt, but man either by his ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our reaſon, ingenuity, or ſtrength per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades or ſorceth them to a ſubjection. When they endeavour to violate this original ſupremacy given to Man, they may for a time fly, run, ſwim, or creep from his Commands; but he hath a Stand for the Eagle, a Toyl for the Lyon, a Hook for the Fiſh, and a Spade for the Mole: or when he deſires to make his Soveraignty a pleaſure, he ſends the Hawk to fetch the Hern and the Partridge, the Hound to bring the Woolf, the Hart, and the Hare; the Cormorant and the Otter to fetch the Fiſh, and the Ferret the Coney; ſo that they are not only ſubmiſſive to his will, but obey all his ſubordinate
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:101580:46"/>commands. I conceive at this time the domination did not extend, that they ſhould be food for man: This, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant appetites brought into uſe; and when they begun to make Gods of men, they offered theſe creatures to their bellies God, which were deſigned for ſacrifices to the only true God and Creator.</p>
                  <p>And it is obſervable, that the Earth, and all that moveth in the Sea, Air, and Earth, were given to mans domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; but not the Sea, nor the Air, nor ſo much as mention of Fire. One Element is ſufficient for us, the other three have a dominion over us, yet ſubordinate to Gods diſpoſe; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore why ſhould we too much wade in their Curioſities, or be troubled like <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle</hi> at our ignorance of them, ſeeing they are not within our Commiſſion.</p>
                  <p>The fourth Joynt Commiffion was for their ſuſtenance, and for that,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="29" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 1. Ver. 29.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God ſaid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 44.</note> 
                     <hi>Behold I have given you every Herb bearing Seed, and every Tree bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fruit; to you it ſhall be for meat.</hi> Herbs and its ſeed, trees and their fruit, in which are Comprehended all Roots,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:101580:47"/>afford ſo great varieties to pleaſe the Pallat and fill the Appetite, that we need not ſeek for any other natriment; eſpecially under thoſe Climats where their vertues are more excellent. And when at firſt that food was aſſigned to our Forefathers, it was ſufficient, and I conceive there was no edible uſe made of living Creatures, but only for ſacrifices, till after <hi>Noah</hi> came out of the Ark; and I am apt to think that God was angry with <hi>Cain</hi> (not as <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> ſaith; for offering things extract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the ground) but for offering the fruit of the ground to God, which God himſelf had clearly diſpoſed off to man, having appropriated beaſts to be ſacrifices to himſelf, as may be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected by <hi>Abels</hi> offering of the Firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings; which was therefore ſo accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, becauſe God reſerved them for himſelf; but <hi>Cains</hi> was not accepted, becauſe they were given to man: ſo it was a mere breach of Gods diſpoſure. We are not to croſs Gods order; thoſe things which he ſeperates to himſelf ought to be devoted to him; thoſe things which he allows us, are not ſo fit for him: we are neither to rob <hi>Peter</hi> that we may be enabled to pay <hi>Paul,</hi>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:101580:47"/>nor to ſatisfy God with the fruits of our worldly imployments, and omit the offering of thoſe oblations which are more peculiar to himſelf.</p>
                  <p>But whether this was <hi>Cains</hi> offence or not I ſhall not diſpute with <hi>Joſephus:</hi> I do not find that mans dominion did, extend to the eating of Fleſh till after <hi>Noah</hi> went out of the Ark, and then it was permitted: but certainly if we could return to our Primitive diet, that life we ſhould live by that food would be more full of health and vigour. But I will ſay no more to this Point, leſt I offend the Chemical Doctors; onely that man and beaſt did participate of one food, Mans with a pleaſurabe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry (for ſo it was doubtleſs before the fall) where 'tis ſaid, <hi>God put man into the garden to dreſs it and to keep it;</hi> but beaſts with eaſe only, without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry. And therein man had the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage; for what food man produced by his induſtry, ſatisfyed his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge equal to his appetite; &amp; certainly the knowledge of the nature of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductions, and then the uſe of them to pleaſe all the ſenfes with their nutri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture &amp; medicine, was a gift as magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent as reaſon is beyond inſenfibility.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text_and_commentary">
            <pb facs="tcp:101580:48"/>
            <pb n="88" facs="tcp:101580:48"/>
            <head>PARS SECUNDA.</head>
            <div type="text">
               <head>The Text of the ſecond Part.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>Cap. 1.</head>
                  <p>ANd to every beaſt of the earth,<note place="margin">Verſe 30.</note> &amp; to every fowl of the air, and to every thing that creepeth upon the earth wherein there is life, I have given every green herb for meat, and it was ſo.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>Cap. 3. Verſe 1.</head>
                  <p>Now the ſerpent was more ſubtile then any beaſt of the field which the Lord God had made, and he ſaid unto the woman, Yea, hath God ſaid ye ſhall not eat of every tree of the garden?</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2</hi> And the woman ſaid to the Serpent, We may eat of the fruit of the trees of the garden:</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> But of the fruit of the tree which is in the midſt of the garden God hath ſaid, Ye ſhall not eat of it, neither ſhall ye touch it, leſt ye dye.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> And the Serpent ſaid unto the woman, Yea ſhall not ſurely dye;</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:101580:49"/>
                     <hi>5</hi> For God doth know that in the day you eat thereof then your eyes ſhall be opened, and ye ſhall be as God knowing good and evil.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> And when the woman ſaw that the tree was good for food, and that it was pleaſant to the eyes, and a tree to be deſired to make one wiſe, ſhe took of the fruit thereof, and did eat, and gave alſo to her husband with her, and he did eat.</p>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> And the eyes of them both were open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and they knew that they were naked, and they ſowed fig leaves together: and made themſelves aprons.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> And they heard the voice of the Lord God walking in the garden in the cool <hi>(or wind)</hi> of the day, and Adam and his wife hid themſelves from the preſence of the Lord God among the trees of the garden.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> And the Lord God called to Adam, &amp; ſaid unto him, Where art thou?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>10</hi> And he ſaid I heard thy voyce in the garden, and I was afraid becauſe I was naked, and I hid myſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>11</hi> And he ſaid, Who told thee that thou waſt naked? haſt thou eaten of the tree whereof I commanded thee, that thou ſhouldſt not eat?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>12</hi> And the Man ſaid, The woman thou gaveſt to be with me, ſhe gave me of the tree, and I did eat.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:101580:49"/>
                     <hi>13</hi> And the Lord ſaid unto the Woman, What is this that thou haſt done? and the Woman ſaid, The Serpent beguiled me, and I did eat.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>14</hi> And the Lord ſaid unto Serpent, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt done this, thou art curſed above all the cattel, and above every beaſt of the field; upon thy belly ſhalt thou go, and duſt ſhalt thou eat all the daies of thy life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>15</hi> And I will put enmity between thee and the woman, and between thy ſeed and her ſeed; it ſhall bruiſe thy head, and thou ſhalt bruiſe his heel.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>16</hi> And to the woman he ſaid, I will greatly multiply thy ſorrows and thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception; in ſorrow ſhalt thou bring forth Children, and thy deſire ſhall be to thy husband, and he ſhall rule over thee.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>16</hi> And unto Adam he ſaid, Becauſe thou haſt harkned to the voice of thy wife, and haſt eaten of the tree of the which I commanded thee, ſaying thou ſhalt not eat of it: Curſed is the ground for thy ſake, in ſorrow ſhalt thou eat of it all the daie: of thy life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>18</hi> Thornes alſo and thiſtles ſhall it bring forth to thee, and thou ſhalt eat the herbs of the field.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>19</hi> In the ſweat of thy face ſhalt thou eat bread, till thou return unto the ground;
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:101580:50"/>for out of it waſt thou taken, for duſt thou art and unto duſt thou ſhalt return.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>20</hi> And Adam called his wifes name Eve, becauſe ſhe was the mother of all liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>21</hi> Unto Adam alſo and his wife aid the Lord God make coats of skins, and cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>22</hi> And the Lord God ſaid, Behold the man is become like one of us to know good and evil; and now leſt he put forth his hand and take alſo of the tree of life, and live for ever.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>23</hi> Therefore the Lord God ſent him forth from the garden of Eden to till the ground from whence he was taken.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>24</hi> So he drove out the man, and he pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced at the Eaſt end of the garden of Eden Cherubims &amp; a flaming ſword, which turnd every way to keep the way of the tree of life.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>Cap. 4. Ver. 1.</head>
                  <p>And Adam knew his wife, and ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and bare Cain; and ſhe ſaid, I have gotten a man from the Lord. And ſhe again bore his brother Abel, and Abel was a keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Sheep, and Cain a tiller of the ground.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>Cap. 5. Ver. 3, 4, 5.</head>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3.</hi> And Adam lived a hundred and thirty
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:101580:50"/>years, and knew his wife again, and begat a ſon in his likeneſs, after his Image, and called his name Seth, for ſhe ſaid, God hath appointed me another ſeed inſtead of Abel, whom Cain ſlew.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4.</hi> And the daies of Adam after he begat Seth were eight hundred years, and he begat ſons and daughters.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> And all the days that Adam lived were nine hundred and thirty yeares, and he dyed.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
               <div n="30" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 1. Ver. 30.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And to every Beaſt of the Earth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 1.</note> 
                     <hi>and to every Fowl of the air, and to every thing that creepeth upon the Earth, wherein there is life, I have given every Green Herb for meat.</hi> Beaſts &amp; Man being created as is ſuppoſed much about one time, their food alſo was appointed the ſame; there is only this differance, that we find not any food aſſigned to them, until Man was firſt ſerved; and then to ſhew the difference of their Appetites, it is ſaid to Man, <hi>Behold, I have given you every herb, &amp;c.</hi> But to Beaſts, Fowls, and creepers, <hi>every green herb;</hi> to ſhew that Beaſts were led to their Food by Sence, but Man by his Intellect. If the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:101580:51"/>vertue of the Plant do not ſatisfy his knowledge of it, the Colour is not to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, the Eye is not to be judge of his Appetite, though allowed to Beaſts.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Green</hi> is the firſt Colour that is mentioned in Scripture, and this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the firſt place; and indeed no co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour is ſo pleaſing to nature, and ſo ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pifies the underſtanding, it being im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to find out why nature ſhould mantle her ſelf more univerſally with this colour then any other; unleſs it be admitted that the beams of the Sun on the ſudden reflecting upon Earth, do uſually produce a Yellow colour, which being mixt with the Azure colour of the Air, and contemperd with the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid part of the Earth, ſends forth a <hi>Green:</hi> For the mixture of Yellows and Blues produceth Greens. And where it is denied to the ſuperficies of the earth by ſhades or otherwiſe, it unites its force, and runs into the bodies of trees, &amp; after aſecret aſcention mounts to the higheſt branches with a more ſublime verdure. And theſe green Vegetables were to invite the appetite of <hi>Beaſts</hi> without inquiry; it was <hi>Mans</hi> part properly to know their Natures and vertues.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="verse">
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:101580:51"/>
                  <head>Cap. 3. Verſe 1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now the ſerpent was more ſubtil then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Beaſt of the field which the Lord God had made.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 2.</note> It is conceived that beaſts were made the Evening before man, being the very fore-recited piece to Man, ſo as they had the very aſſimilation of man by way of approximation to his creation; and doubtleſs they did underſtand each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Dialects, and God had them in ſo great regard above other Terreſtrial Creatures, that when he gave Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to Man, Cap. 1. Verſe 28. It was over Fiſh, and Fowl, and creep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing things, but not over beaſts, ſo that that <hi>Now,</hi> whilſt there was this Amity, this conjugation of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and Diſpoſition between Man and Beaſt, even <hi>Now,</hi> That is, Then <hi>The ſerpent was more ſubtile,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Whether this mas really a Serpent,<note place="margin">§ 3.</note> or the Devil in the Serpents ſhape, I diſpute not; but conceive the Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion might be by either: for thoſe who writ of Serpents, make ſome of them (even known to our age, as the <hi>Baſilisk</hi> and <hi>Scytala</hi>) ſo beautiful and cunning, that by their beauty, ſplendor, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:101580:52"/>entice many into deſtruſtion: and there is an other ſort, as the <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard,</hi> that are ſo affectionate to Man, that is preſerves him from all dangers. As for the firſt ſort, it was not likely that <hi>Eve</hi> in the ſtate of Innocency ſhould meet with ſuch Nocent creatures; and as to the other ſort, their nature diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not them to nocency. But poſſibly the fruit being pleaſant, and the ſerpent diſcourſive, the one might allurethe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, perſwade her to eat out of no evil intention, but as incredulous that God would deny <hi>Eve</hi> the eating of ſo deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate a fruit. But if it were the Devil in the Serpents ſhape, then indeed he was <hi>Serpens Verſatilis,</hi> as the <hi>Vulgar</hi> read it; that is, <hi>Viro ſubtilior,</hi> and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſubtileſt Beaſt of the field.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And he ſaid to the woman,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 4.</note> 
                     <hi>Yea, hath God ſaid, Ye ſhall not eat of every tree of the garden?</hi> What Language the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil or Serpent ſpake is not material, but that which was natural to either was underſtood by both: For it ſeems by the Text, that that which was ſaid by the Serpent was but as a reply to the Woman: For ſaith the Serpent, <hi>Yea, hath God ſaid</hi> (as you tell me) <hi>that you are not to eat of every tree of the garden?</hi> So
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:101580:52"/>we ſee here were diſcourſes tending to a temptation, and ſhe muſt be more Innocent then <hi>Eve</hi> in her Innocency who admits of ſuch. For methinks I hear the ſerpent ſay, Hath that God who hath made you ſo beautiful, endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you with all perfections, given you all pleaſures for your ſenſes, plac'd you in ſo ſweet a garden where nothing is wanting to content your Mind, or recreate your Body; and can that God be ſo unkind after all his kindneſs to forbid you the Eating of a fruit ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable? Yea, hath God ſaid ſo? ſurely I will not believe it. And ſo ſhe takes the Devils Argument as granted, without conſulting her husband, (to whom the Command was given, though incluſively to both:) By which means the Temptation went gently on. Now though this diſcourſe of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent may ſeem ſtrange to remoter A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges; yet I apprehend that in that time of Perfection Man could not be a ſtranger to the Dialect of all Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, I mean in the higheſt conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of comparing the Chaps, and the Lips, or other Tendons, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward intentions or deſires; and this is done by the judgment of the Eye. But
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:101580:53"/>for that which we uſe by the judgment of the Ear, we read that ſome in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry age have attained to ſuch diverſities of times, calls, cryes, expreſſing the mirth, aſſiſtance, acclamations, joys, or ſorrows of ſeveral Birds and Beaſts; that Men, Birds and Beaſts have enjoyed a mutual intercourſe of affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: And the meaneſt Capacity finds, that every kind of Creature which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords a ſound, is known not only in its diſtinct kind by its tone, but every individual <hi>ſpecies</hi> of each kind is alſo known by their Guttural, Labial, Dental, or Roſtral ſounds. Nor is it prodigious to me, that the Serpent ſhould afford ſuch perſwaſive diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, finding by Common obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations that all Beaſts, Birds, &amp;c. have a certain Raticination, and a Language to expreſs it; the Horſe ſpeaks for his Provender, the Dog for his meat, and the Bird in the Cage for its ſeeds.</p>
                  <p>But I wonder more that <hi>Eve</hi> having doubtleſs a more perfect reaſon as yet in her unſpotted Innocency, could be perſwaded by a beaſt (or the Devil him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf) from neglecting her husband. But they that will ſuffer their ſenſes to
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:101580:53"/>maſter their Reaſon, Love, and Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pience, will quickly prove wholly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious: And therefore without her husband ſhe replies,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2,3" type="verses">
                  <head>Cap. 3. Verſe 2. &amp; 3.</head>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>And the Woman ſaid to the Serpent, We may eat of the trees of the garden:</hi> 3. <hi>But of the fruit of the tree which is in the midſt of the Garden, God hath ſaid, Ye ſhall not eat thereof.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ <hi>5.</hi> See Part <hi>1.</hi> Sect <hi>15.</hi>
                     </note> I Obſerve that the Command was given to <hi>Adam</hi> before <hi>Eve</hi> was made of his Rib, but it ſeems <hi>Adam</hi> had imparted that Command to <hi>Eve,</hi> and that Command and in uncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was ſufficient for her to ſay, that We may eat, or we may not eat. The wifes obedience (implicitly) depending upon the husbands: He is to obey God, and ſhe him; and in that ſhe hath a double reward from God and him: But when ſhe ſtrays from her husbands dictates (for ſhe had none from God) we ſee what a curſe ſhe brought upon her ſelf, and on her tender and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying husband, yea and upon the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent which (if not the Devil.) It may be meant only a piece of Courtſhip to her. And therefore it is dangerous to admit of Temptations againſt poſitive Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:101580:54"/>
                     <hi>Neither ſhall ye touch it leſt ye dye.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 6.</note> Here ſhe gave the Serpent (or Devil) the firſt advantage by a falſe reply: For firſt, God had Commanded <hi>Adam</hi> that he ſhould not eat of the tree, cap. 2.17. and no mention in that Text of the fruit. Secondly, Nor did God e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver command that he ſhould not touch it Thirdly, the tree of life was ſaid to be in the mioſt of the garden, which was not forbidden; but the place of the tree of Knowledge is not mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and he had Liberty to eat of the tree of life, but not of the tree of Knowledge: So that the Serpent had ſufficient Advantage by the Miſtake of the command. Whereupon,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 2. Verſe 4.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Serpent ſaid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Ye ſhall not ſurely dye.</hi> You ſhall not dye, either for eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Fruit (which was not mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) or for touching the tree (which is not Commanded) or for eating of the Tree in the midſt of the garden (which was the Tree of life) and not forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. And when the Serpent had thus poſſeſt her, that ſhe ſhould not dye for eating or touching of that which was not forbidden, he returns to the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:101580:54"/>truth of puniſhment, yet depending upon the former aſſeveration, and ſaith, <hi>ye ſhall not ſurely dye.</hi> For the Serpent had got ſo much advantage by the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with <hi>Eve,</hi> and underſtanding the Nature of her death, not to be a ſeperation of the Soul and Body, but a deprivatian of Gods Love, did tell her to this effect; ſo good a God would not inflict ſo rigorous a puniſhment up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her; for ſhe ſhould not dye, but Live, and live now with farr more ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction: For her eyes which were only as Senſes, ſhall then repreſent all thing in their perfect Knowledge of them, <hi>For ye ſhall be like Gods knowing good and evil.</hi> But in this diſcourſe hitherto both the Devil and <hi>Eve</hi> left out one expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in that command, namely, <hi>In the day thou eateſt;</hi> they were both willing it ſeems to omit the point of time. And well may Procraſtination continue as a puniſhment upon our humane Nature; ſhe thought God would not be ſo pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual to a day, or it may be ſhe did not underſtand what a day was, or it may be ſhe had too various opinions of it, and not Conſidered as intended <hi>in Pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto temporis,</hi> either 12. or 24. hours, or a year, according to the Natural mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:101580:55"/>of the Sut: But it may be ſhe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivd the day to be a <hi>Thouſand years, which are but as a day with God.</hi> So that the day ſhe ſhould die ſhould be a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years after the Eating, or a time undeterminable. Some of theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions might make them omit the day; for it is certain, he neither ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the laſt day of his life, nor dyed the firſt day of his death. So that we may underſtand it to be a death Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted, but not inſtantly inflicted; and in ſtead of <hi>Morte Morieris,</hi> we may read <hi>Mortalis eris; Thou ſhalt dye the death,</hi> that is, thou ſhalt be Mortal, or have a daily diſpoſition in thee to death.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 3. Verſe 5.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For God doth know,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 8.</note> 
                     <hi>that in the day you eat thereof then your eyes ſhall be opened, and you ſhall be like God's knowing good and Evil.</hi> Now the Devil boldly menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons the day, when by his ſubtile intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling diſcourſes he had gotten the day of the Woman: But (poor ſoul!) it prov'd her night; Their Eyes which till now were open to ſee all ſorts of Felicity, are now dimmed with the ſhades of enſuing Mortality; ſo that though they have Eyes, yet they can
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:101580:55"/>ſee nothing, but the effects of their Ambition. For that knowledge of goodneſs which they had in perfection, by continuing in obedience to Gods Commands, is now turned by their diſobedience to an imperfect know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which is the greateſt Evil at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending human Nature: For by this imperfection we ſcarce know what good is to be followed, or what evil to be ſhunned. Regions, Climes, Tempers, Accidents, and even Laws of Nations, giving Latitudes or Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſcriptions enough to puzzle the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouteſt ſouls; and doubtleſs this is no ſimilitude of a Divine knowledge, or to know as God, who I preſume knows Evil no otherwiſe, then by ſuffering our Knowledge to be puzzled in at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the unſpeakable Myſtery of goodneſs. And therefore the <hi>Targum</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> being tender, I ſuppoſe, in aſcribing the knowledge of Evil to God, inſtead of <hi>you ſhall be like Gods, knowing Good and Evil;</hi> ſay, <hi>you ſhall be like the great Angels, who are indued with Wiſdome to determin good and evil.</hi> And if the Planets and Spheres have their operations from the Angels, then the aſtrologians have the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:101580:56"/>of knowing good and evil by Collection: however, it is an equal infelicity not to know the diſtinction of good &amp; evil, as not to be able to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the one, or prevent the other. And the <hi>Chaldee</hi> Paraphraſe ſays, <hi>Ye ſhall be like Princes;</hi> as if Princes were to be the Judges of Good and Evil: For good or bad things (which ſome call indifferent) are made good or bad according to the Nature and obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Command.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 3. Ver. 6.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And when the Woman ſaw that the Tree was good for food,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 9.</note> 
                     <hi>and that it was Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to the Eyes, and a tree to be deſired to make one wiſe</hi> Here we ſee the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of diſobedience: We firſt ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue from neceſſity, <hi>It is good for Food;</hi> and without Food we cannot ſuſteine Nature: and who hath more reaſon to be Careful of that then our ſelves? And why did God exhibit us the view of Food, yea and good food, if we may not be our own Carvers? Then we argue from Pleaſure; does God (ſay we) Create in us organs of ſight, and thoſe attended with ſuch Agents, that we are pleaſed and diſpleaſed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:101580:56"/>to our objects; &amp; ſeeing content gives life to every fruition why ſhould we not injoy what is moſt pleaſurable? and at once pleaſe our taſte and ſight? And then ſteps in Ambition, and ſays, We ſhall not only pleaſe our ſenſes, but our Intellectuals: We ſhall be wiſe as God, Angels, or Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; that is, as any of our ſuperiours. And thus by theſe inſinuations we give our ſelves Latitude to our own deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and this is the ground of ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine to Families as well as to States: The Servant would evade the Maſters Commands, the Wife the Husbands, the Subject the Princes; Judging the Commands to be of ſmall conſequence, and ſo the breach eaſily forgiven, or advantagious to our ſelves, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore naturally diſpenſibe. But doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the leſs the command be the more we are obliged to perform, becauſe the performance ſeems more in our Power; and the more advantagious it is to our private Capacities the greater affront we give to the publick by our diſobedience, and ingroſſing that which ſhould be either common or reſtrained, by ſo being perſwaded and reſolved to diſobey.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:101580:57"/>
                     <hi>She took of the Fruit thereof,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 10.</note> 
                     <hi>and did eat.</hi> This Fruit which <hi>Eve</hi> did eat is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly taken for an Apple, but I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell for what reaſon, unleſs that <hi>Malum</hi> is Latine for an Apple, as alſo for Evil. And then the next doubt is (<hi>for none knew</hi> the <hi>original of Latine</hi>) whether <hi>Eve</hi> did ſpeak <hi>Latine</hi> in Paradiſe. But the ſmall reaſon that I have heard for the Apple is, becauſe if one Cut an Apple croſs the Core, that is, beteen the ſtalk and the top, the Beds of the Seeds are juſt ten in number, repreſenting the ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments; all which <hi>Eve</hi> did at once break by eating the Apple, and that Fruit continues ſtill which thoſe ten marks. But whether it were an Apple eaten, or any other Fruit, as <hi>Ficu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicus, &amp;c.</hi> is not meterial; the breach of a command is that which is denoted to us, and our Ambitious Curioſity in medling or inſpecting ſuch things, though ſeeming trivial, yet are the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cana Imperii,</hi> and not to be toucht but by God, or Angels, or Princes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Let the tree of Knowledge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone; 'tis meat only for our ſuperiors: you who are Subjects be content to
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:101580:57"/>plant your Gardens, and ſow your Fields, and converſe with the innocent Beaſts thereof, The Woman muſt not prattle her ſelf into temptations, nor be courted by the ſubtilty of thoſe who would beguile her into forbidden Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. We ſee the Conſequence; her diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience breaks the Conjugal Bond of obedience, and proves to be both the ruine of her ſelf and her Superior. And as 'tis in private Families, ſo in States, Schiſmes beget Faction, Faction Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, Sedition Rebellion, Rebellion Wars, Wars Murders, Depopulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and even ruine to themſelves and the whole Fabrick of which they are Compos'd. So that certainly the great ſin againſt God and Nature is diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and the greateſt Ignorance is not to know the true Nature and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendences of obedience, from a Child to his Parent, from a Servant to his Maſter, from a Souldier to his Captain, from a Wife to her Husband, from a Subject to his Prince; and not to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic'd, or go out of the Limits of either, till the guidance of Superiours directs us; wherein God is to be ſerved in the firſt place, Princes in the next, and the other degrees according to ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinations.
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:101580:58"/>Yet the great deceit in theſe gradations is, that we are apt to ſay, That God would not have done what our Superiours Command, or would have done what they forbid. Wherein the ſafeſt and juſteſt Rule is, Not to think our ſelves wiſer then our Superiours, for they and we have our very orders and ſtations from God; and Angels, Princes, and Superiors are nearer to him in thier ſeveral degrees, then thoſe who are ſubordinate to them. And he is a dangerous Caſuiſt, who undertakes to cleave a Hair be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a Superiours poſitive Command and his own private Judgment, of what is fit or not fit to be done therein. For the Orders of all Men, yea even of all Creatures, are ſo Known and aſcertained, that it is only a Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſme tending to Rebellion, when by ſubtil perſwaſions of others, which is meant by the Serpent, or our own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations, we are diverted from that harmonious Method which God hath conſtituted in the Government of the World, and more eſpecially of Men: And it is much better to err in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, then in the Repugnancie. If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one in his own time makes but a due
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:101580:58"/>Collection of what Rewards he hath ſeen to the one, and what inflictions to the other, he ſhall need no other ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument for the one, or diſſwaſions from the other.</p>
                  <p n="6">6.<note place="margin">§ 11.</note> 
                     <hi>And gave alſo to her Husband with her, who did eat.</hi> What Moral man can ſay, but <hi>Eve</hi> was a kind Wife to let her Husband pertake of the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of her Eye, taſt, and great expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of Knowledge? For with theſe three arguments did <hi>Eve</hi> preſent to him the fruit: And it was from a Wife, whoſe very Beauties (ſhe being then in perfection) were temptation ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to receive a meaner Preſent from ſo fair a hand, whoſe kindneſs was ſo full of duty and goodneſs, that he could not doubt of incurring the leaſt prejudice from the tenders of her Love. And how could he, who had the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to forſake Father and Mother and cleave to his Wife, be ſo unkind, as to make the leaſt expoſtulation or denyal of the Teſtimonies of her af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection? And poſſibly, (if the ſtory be not altogether <hi>Allegorical</hi>) as ſome Fathers would have it, or Chemical, (according to <hi>Paracelſus</hi>) the Serpent might whiſper in the Ear of <hi>Eve</hi> to
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:101580:59"/>this effect: <hi>Well, you think Adam Loves you, when poſſibly he only pretends this Commnnd from God merely to deprive you of ſo great advantage as you may have by eating that fruit, and thereby be equal in Knowledge with him. Or it may be he is Jealous of you, becauſe I have been ſo long diſcourſing with you; and therefore it may be he will deny you, becauſe I have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded you to it. Upon the whole matter, it is an evident Teſtimony of his want of Love to you if he deny you ſo Kind an offer, or the grant of that wherein there is no trouble, but ſeeming advantages to you both by your Condeſcention.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Who at her perſwaſion did eat.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 12.</note> It is a riddle to my thoughts, when I conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that the fulfilling of the Law, and the breach of the Law, have both of them their foundation from Love. And in thoſe the <hi>Jews</hi> were ſo Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, that they accounted the number of the <hi>Moſaical</hi> Precepts to be ſeven hundred ninety and three, whereof four hundred twenty and eight affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, which were what we ſhould do; and three hundred ſixty and five Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives, which were what we ſhould not do. And the <hi>Moraliſts</hi> call thoſe Virtues, and theſe Vices. And the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:101580:59"/>truth is, in theſe there are no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions Real or formal; for even Luſt and drunkenneſs, &amp;c. are but the Exceſſes of Love: ſo that the ſame God, who bids us Love, and gives us Variety of amiable enjoyments, Bids us alſo forbear Love. Now, how can the Temper of one Man give Law or proportion to the temper of another, and make that Luſt which is but a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of a different Temper; or that Drunkenneſs, which is but the natural ſatisfaction of thirſt? And therefore are to forbear too ſevere a Cenſure, for every Man hath a proportion'd Love, ſome but ſparks, ſome Coals, and ſome Flames; and it is (or ought to be) the wiſdom of every Man to know the Temper of his own Love, and not thereby to bound or limit anothers; &amp; his own (once known) not to ſuffer his Love either to injure others by a breach of Commutative Juſtice, or prejudice himſelf in not giving a true balance to his affections, by making that neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to his Conſtitution, which is but adventitious either by habit, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting temptations, or willful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations. But herein we ſhew our true Love, when our Love is fixed in
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:101580:60"/>obedience to the Lawes ſuperiours, and by reſtraining our Appetites to ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate Loves, and bringing our Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers to obſerve ſuperior Commands: for God commanded <hi>Adam</hi> that he ſhould not eat; ſo the delights of the Eyes, the pleaſures of the taſt, the Inticements of the Woman ought to have been ſubſervient Loves to the love of his command; and though there are certain natural and inherent Loves, as to ſee, and taſte, even things deſirable in themſelves; yet he is moſt happy that can make his Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Loves ſubſervient to the affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of higher Powers, and ſuch Law as are made intentionally equal.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 3. Ver. 7.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the eyes of them both were opened,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 13.</note> 
                     <hi>and they knew that they were naked.</hi> We muſt not think that <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eves</hi> eyes were ſhut in their Perfection, and opened by their tranſgreſſion; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſaw each other in their full Accompliſhments of Nature, and had no cauſe to bluſh or be aſhamed: But being now ſenſible of their Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and not knowing how to blame one another, her for tempting, and he
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:101580:60"/>for yielding, they now not onely bluſh, and are aſhamed of their Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but like the Beaſt, that by hiding his head thinks his body undiſcerned; ſo they by making themſelves Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments thought that their fault ſhould not be diſcovered. And it ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues in the Nature of Man to find out ſhifts, clokes, and umbrages for his offences.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And they ſowed fig-leaves together,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 14.</note> 
                     <hi>and made themſelves aprons.</hi> It is probable <hi>Adam</hi> made choice of theſe fig-leaves rather then any other, both for the breadth, ſubſtance, and excellent qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities of repelling all Tumours; but whether of them they made Aprons, Coats, or Girdles, or Breeches, Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flators differ: But the <hi>Targum</hi> of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nudati erant a veſte Onychi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, in qua creati erant;</hi> that is, They were diſrobed of their Garment, which in the time of their Perfection was made of the <hi>Onyx</hi> ſtone. For there are ſtones in <hi>Italy</hi> of which they make moſt curious threds, and thoſe ſpun into Cloth reſembling our fineſt flexen Linen: and the like might be made of this. Now this <hi>Onyx</hi> ſtone hath a peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar quality (as Authors write) to ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:101580:61"/>the Spirits, and heighten Venery: And whether their offence was Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reous, adumbraged under the name of <hi>forbidden Fruit,</hi> may be Conſidered on. And great Reaſon had God to be An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, if they injoyed that forbidden Fruit, till God (as it were) had fully conſidered whether it had been more advantageous to Man to ariſe from the ground like the <hi>Mandrake,</hi> or the <hi>Senſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Lamb,</hi> or like <hi>Barnacles</hi> from trees or ſhells) or that there ſhould have been Incubents and Succubents to diſpoſe of their Nocturnal ejacula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or decoſtations, without pain to Male or Female: like that of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> he only in the loſs of a rib, ſhe in being one.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 3. Verſe 8.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And they heard the voice of the Lord God walking in the Garden.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 15.</note> This voice and walking is not to be Conſidered in an humane ſenſe, but every incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation to good, or declination of what is evil, is a voice from God to incite or prohibit; And every Motion which tends to an act of goodneſs, or devia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from evil, is within the Compaſs of Gods perambulation. He walks in
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:101580:61"/>this world as his Garden, where we injoy all pleaſing objects to the Eyes, and other ſenſes, and by our ſenſes we improve our Knowledge, both in Moral and Divine Concerns; his Voyce ſtill attends, and his Motion gently perſwades us. And yet miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Men as we are, we ſee and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of the beſt things, but purſue the Worſt. And it ſeems a ſtrange Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation to be puniſht for our inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and tryal of all things, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as by ſacred Writ we are adviſed ſo to do; and that thoſe things which are good for us to injoy, yet are made deſtruction to us, by (as it were) a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Inhibition. So that our Tryal of all Things conſiſteth even of Nothing but Circumſpections, leſt in the moſt ſeeming Innocent Actions we ſhould offend: For our Eating, Drinking, Sleeping, and inquiries into Lawful Knowledge, have in them almoſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſervedly both a Neceſſity and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence: And therefore the Apoſtle might juſtly tell us, that we are to <hi>work out out Salvation with Fear and Trembling.</hi> And it is remarkable, that as God is ſaid to be walking in a Garden, where <hi>Adam</hi> Committed his offence: So
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:101580:62"/>Chriſt himſelf (as Religion teaches us) was walking in a Garden, and as Man he was Crucified for that ſin in a Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den. And he that will obſerve the Divine Motion of puniſhment ſhall find (both in Sacred and Profane Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries) Examples enough to teach, that God is (as it were) punctual in his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, both as to Time, Place, and Circumſtance, even to the third and fourth Generation of them who hate him; which Third and Fourth I take to be a ſeptenary time. And as <hi>Adam</hi> &amp; <hi>Eve</hi> conſiſts of ſeaven Letters, ſo their enſuing puniſhment was upon the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Ages of mankind, whether Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered Individually to Man, or General<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the ſeaven Ages of the World.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Walking in the cool of the day.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 16.</note> God is ſaid to be the <hi>Lord of hoſts,</hi> to ſhew his courage; and a <hi>God of anger;</hi> and yet a <hi>God of patience, though provoked eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day.</hi> And even now when <hi>Adam</hi> had offended, and his offence known, yet he ſhewed not his anger, but walked without any ſeeming paſſion <hi>in the cool of the day.</hi> And it is of great uſe in Morality, when we know our temper to be inclined to wrath, or that we have juſt provocations thereunto, that
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:101580:62"/>we endeavour to allay them by ſome outward or inward temperament; by walking, that is, by a private diſcuſſing of the matter; or by arguments of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearance, to mould our thoughts from anger or revenge. And in a <hi>garden,</hi> that is, by Diverſions; and <hi>in the cool of the day,</hi> that is, by mollifying or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frigerating of that heat, unto which the Sun of Paſſion would otherwiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And Adam and his wife hid themſelves from the preſence of the Lord God among the trees of the garden.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 17.</note> I wonder that <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve,</hi> who had ſo lately eat of the tree of Knowledge, ſhould ſo ſoon loſe their Knowledge, to think that Gods Omnipreſence could be ſheltered by the ſhade of trees. And we are more fooliſh in following their ſteps thus; when we have done amiſs, we run as it were from Gods preſence, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of imploring his forgiveneſs or aſſiſtance, we ſtudy which way to um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brage our faults, and mix our ſelves with the ſociety of others; as if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the innocence of others ſhould be a plea for our ſelves, or the diverſions which Company affords ſhould oblite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the ſenſe of our tranſgreſſions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="verse">
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:101580:63"/>
                  <head>Cap. 3. Ver. 9.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the Lord God called to Adam,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 18.</note> 
                     <hi>and ſaid to him, Where art thou?</hi> It is ſaid that King <hi>Mithridates</hi> underſtood ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty two Languages, yet he had thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands more to learn: for every indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual Creature hath a language, and that language (though diverſified by Organs) is univerſally the ſame, for if ſeveral men of ſeveral Nations ſtand near a Tree, which by the force of the Hewers is ready to fall, the univerſal language is <hi>Take heed.</hi> And though men differ in Letters and Articulations, yet we differ not in the ſenſe which the Tree kindly ſpeaks to us, and the Standers by are Interpreters. And thus upon all occaſions the voice of God by his ſeveral Organs calls upon us, and his voice is <hi>labial, dental,</hi> and <hi>guttural,</hi> even as ours; for if he ſpeak from his lips, that is, things pleaſing to us; or from his teeth, that is, things diſpleaſing to us; or from his throat, that is, things indifferent; yet ſtill in all he affords an intelligible voice to us, which <hi>Adam</hi> well underſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God ſaid in expreſs terms, <hi>Adam, where art thou?</hi> And doubtleſs the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:101580:63"/>expoſtulations between them were to this effect: <hi>How now, Adam? Thou, whom I created from nothing; thou, whom after Creation I made ſuperintendent of all Creatures, and for whoſe ſake I made them all to be a pleaſure to thee; thou, who wert to Prune &amp; Dreſs thoſe delicacies which I had Planted in the Garden; Thou, who hadſt the freedome of Art to imitate and imbelliſh what I had fixt in the nature of each Plant; Thou who hadſt the Knowledge of all Creatures, and a more particular, neerneſs to the Creator; muſt thou ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude thy ſelf, that I muſt ſay, Where art thou? Art thou performing thy duty? art thou injoying what I allow thee, or doing what I Commanded thee?</hi> And to this effect did the voice of God ſpeak to <hi>Adam;</hi> who anſwered;</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 3. Verſe 10.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And Adam ſaid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 19.</note> 
                     <hi>I heard thy voice in the Garden, &amp;c.</hi> It is not enough to heare Gods reproving voice, but Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines ſay, that to repentance there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs Confeſſion, Contrition, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction. He confeſt his fear, but not his fault; nor was there any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, but for his Nakedneſs, not his Crime: and for ſatisfaction, it
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:101580:64"/>was impoſſible, for he having diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey'd in eating what was forbidden, he could not ſatisfie by uneating what he had eat. Vomit is not a diſcharge of drunkenneſs, but an additional Crime. Charitable Actions do not ſatisfie for extortion, but rather adds a greater Crime, by getting and doſpoſing of that which ought not juſtly to be at his diſpoſition. So that he heard Gods voice, and ſhewed his Terror, but no Confeſſion, de diſcovered his guilt, but no Contrition; he gives Excuſes, but no ſatisfaction to a God who had been ſo kind, ſo liberal, ſo indulgent to him.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And I was affeard.</hi> The proper <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> word expreſſing Fear is <hi>affeard,</hi> not <hi>affraid;</hi> for <hi>affraid</hi> comes from Fray or Fraction of that Unity which ought to be with men; but <hi>affeard</hi> is from <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre,</hi> or a ſuppoſition that ſomething ſhall be taken from us. And the <hi>Latin</hi> word for Fear is <hi>timor,</hi> that is, a preſent apprehenſion <hi>te mori,</hi> that the object of fear will produce death to the event: for though we do not diſcourſively (as here) dilate upon the Circumſtances, yet whatever happens to a man by loſs or croſs, yet the reſult is immediately
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:101580:64"/>in the breaſt of man, <hi>timor,</hi> or <hi>te mori,</hi> that ſuch an accident will occaſion death. And I find it in the <hi>Syriac,</hi> (of which I have writ in my Preface to the <hi>Proverbs</hi>) where 'tis ſaid, <hi>The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wiſdom;</hi> 'tis tranſlated <hi>Timor Mortis,</hi> The fear of death is the beginning of wiſdom. And this was the beginning of <hi>Adams</hi> Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in his imperfections; for whilſt he was in Perfection he neither feared nor was aſhamed of his Actions, or that Death would enſue: And Doubtles the nearer our Actions are done to ſuch uprightneſs, the nearer wee are to his primitive perfection: But ſin, or diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, either to God or Man, cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth both ſhame and fear. Now the reaſon of his fear is given;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe I was naked.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 20.</note> He was depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved (ſays the <hi>Chaldee</hi>) <hi>De veſte Ony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>china,</hi> of his garment of vertue which was reſtrained to obedience, in not eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Fruit, or forbearing to do what was forbidden; in not dreſſing the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, or purſuing juſt, honeſt and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial imployments to himſelf and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and thereby not doing what was Commanded, and being ſenſible that he had diveſted himſelf of his garment
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:101580:65"/>Perfection, and that he had no defence for his diſobedience, he tryed what the Shades of the evening and the trees would do.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And I hid my ſelf.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 21.</note> The Text ſaith not in what manner he hid himſelf, but it is much that neither the Tincture of his former perfection, nor the <hi>fear of God</hi> which <hi>is the beginning of Wiſdom,</hi> which certainly he knew as well as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon.</hi> And we may ſee by this Text, that he had <hi>the fear of the Lord,</hi> yet it did not teach him <hi>Davids</hi> leſſon, <hi>If</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>I aſcend up to Heaven thou art there; if into the deep, thou art there alſo, &amp;c.</hi> For then he could not have been, ſo ignorant of Gods omnipreſence, as to think that a few trees, or buſhes, or caves, or the night could hide him. For my part I think his hiding an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional ſin equal to the eating the Fruit: firſt, by diſtruſt of Gods kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, who might have pardoned him, if he had not fled from the offence; for this in our Laws Conſummates the Crime: and next as great a diſtruſt, that God could or would not cloath him in his nakedneſs. And it continues ſtill an Error in his poſterity, who (in Want, or Poverty, or in our offences) betake
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:101580:65"/>our ſelves to ſubterfuges, which aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vates the crime even with God and Man.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 3. Ver. 11.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And God ſaid, Who told thee that thou waſt naked?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 22.</note> 
                     <hi>Haſt thou eat of the tree whereof I commanded thee that thou ſhould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt not eat?</hi> This word <hi>Who</hi> might be an argument for the <hi>Prae-Adamite;</hi> as if there were ſome other man to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe with, had not God explained him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the ſequel of the queſtion, <hi>Haſt thou eaten of the tree? &amp;c.</hi> To ſhew, that even dumb Creatures may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince us of our errors, and the virtues which are in them correct us of our vices. Things which are of a ſanative nature tell us our charitable duty to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; things of a deſtructive nature tell us we are to avoid the doing of what is prejudicial to others. And it ſeems this tree had a double nature; it had a virtue to tell him the goodneſs he had loſt by his diſobedience, and an evil quality to teach him excuſes. And 'tis no wonder this tree ſhould have this double quality, when we ſee the Bee ſuck out of every herb Honey, full of good and medicinal virtues; and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:101580:66"/>her ſting with a matter poiſonous, hurtful, and evil. And the truth is, not this Tree onely, but all individual Creatures have their good and evil in them. The good of the Tree was in the preſent pleaſure to the eye and taſte, the evil was in ſome poiſonous quality, which not onely infected him and <hi>Eve</hi> with all their infirmities, but by a traductive quality hath made us deſire and do thoſe things we ſhould not. Nor need we wonder at this continuing quality, when we ſee the Gums of Trees continue a Balſom for an hundred years: And the <hi>Italians</hi> hold, that the longer ſome Poiſons are kept, they are the more efficacious. And both of them have not onely pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er over the Body, but the very Mind, (which is very near of kin to the Soul.) So that the virtues of ſome things make men good by rectifying their tempers, the vicious quality of the ſame intoxicate, and make men mad or worſe: Nay, the virtues of the ſame individual Creature reſtores to life, the vicious part a preſent death. But that which is more conſiderable, is the Nicety between good and evil things; many times good things prove poiſons
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:101580:66"/>by their ill uſe, and Poiſons or ill things prove ſometimes the beſt Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 3. Ver. 12.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the man ſaid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 23.</note> 
                     <hi>The woman thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt to be with me, ſhe gave me of the tree to eat, and I did eat.</hi> Diſobedience is the Nurſe of Ingratitude, and Ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Impudence. Thus <hi>Adam</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of thanks for his Meet helper im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicitly reviles God, who gave her; not conſidering that ſhe was given rather to help then adviſe; or if to adviſe, yet he had the deliberative part in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to do or not to do, as he thought moſt prudent; but without debating that with God, he with impudence told God as it were, that it was Gods fault to give her to him; and ſince he had given her, and that he was to ſhew all expreſſions of kindneſs unto her, who had recommended it to him, he thought himſelf obliged rather to obſerve her then him: and thereupon without any more circumſtance or excuſe heard, <hi>She gave it me, and I did eat.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 3. Verſe 13.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the Lord God ſaid to the woman,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 24.</note> 
                     <hi>What is this that thou haſt done?</hi> God
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:101580:67"/>ſaid to <hi>Adam, Where art thou?</hi> though he knew where he was; and to the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>What haſt thou done?</hi> though he knew what; yet neither of theſe kind Queſtions could beget a civil or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſive anſwer, but the Man ſaid, <hi>the Woman gave it to me;</hi> and the Woman ſaid, <hi>the Serpent beguiled her:</hi> but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them, though they knew they had done the fact, would acknowledge their own diſobedience in doing it; for then poſſibly God would have raiſed ſome Antidote from that, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tree, without a future Saviour, to have Cured the infection of the Evil, and to have fixt the benefit of the good. But ſhe ungrateful and Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent as he, Replies, <hi>that the Serpent beguiled her, and ſhe did eat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the Woman ſaid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 25.</note> 
                     <hi>The Serpent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled me.</hi> There need no inquiry into the Hiſtory of Nature, to know what kind of Serpent that was which beguil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Eve,</hi> when as we ſee every Man is daily ſubject to be tempted by the ſame or the like Serpent. Pride is this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent that tempts us to Ambitious acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; Covetouſneſs this Serpent that tempts us to injure others; Luxury this Serpent that tempts us into forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:101580:67" rendition="simple:additions"/>Embraces; Wine this Serpent that ſteales into our veines with argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Collour and Taſte, Improv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſpirits, and ſolacing our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, until at laſt it ſo Captivates our Reaſon, that when God asks where we are, we cannot anſwer; or what we have done, we can only ſay with <hi>Eve, The Serpent hath beguiled us.</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly it is a great puniſhment on our Natures that we cannot Judge; or if we do, that we connot refrain from Excuſes, and make thoſe offences, which in themſelves are none. For Ambition rightly placed is a vertue, Covetouſneſs Frugality, Luxury (if derived from the Conſtitution) is but a more natural deſire, Wine a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter. He is happy who can carry a Balance alwayes in his Mind to weigh his intentions and actions: And what is thought or done, not to be too Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious of himſelf or others. For there are certain poſitives wherein our Judgments connot err, and therein to ſay the Serpent beguiled, is no juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Excuſe, but in things indifferent.<note place="margin">Ecel. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Solomons</hi> Rule is very good, <hi>My Son, let not thy mouth accuſe thy ſelf of ſin:</hi> make not thoſe things ſins which are, more;
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:101580:68"/>and Commit not thoſe, which Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly are.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 3. 14.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Lord ſaid unto the Serpent.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 26.</note> The Serpent is call'd the ſubtileſt Beaſt, yet doubtleſs every Creature hath a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable underſtanding of Gods voice. Pſal. 19. <hi>The Heavens declare</hi> (or ſpeak) <hi>the Glory of God;</hi> (which he firſt Communicates to them) <hi>the Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament ſpeaks his handy work: one day tells another what is to be done</hi> the next, &amp; <hi>one night certifie another</hi> what deeds are done therein, <hi>there is neither ſpeech nor Language but their Voice is heard through the world.</hi> Every individual thing ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in its operation or virtual Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication ſpeaks that to others which God ſpeaks to them: For <hi>ſpeech</hi> is not only that of which the Ear par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipates, but the other ſenſes do (as it were) heare it equally with the Ear. We ſee the flowers ſpeak their various colours; this flower ſays, I am Red, another Yellow, a third Mixt; and we do but repeat their ſpeech in ſaying what Colour they bear. And beſides, what individuals do afford our ſenſes, they alſo adminiſter diſcourſes to our
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:101580:68"/>Reaſon and Judgment; how this or that is to be virtually applyed: from one we get a letter, from another a ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable, from a third a word, from a fourth a ſentence, from a fifth an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual ſpeech. And all Creatures, though we know not how they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand their proportion of ſpeech which God ſpeaks to them, yet they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, and only Man hath the diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative part granted to him; for though the Serpent was the ſubtileſt Beaſt, yet God would hear none of his ſubtile re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications or Evaſions. But God ſaid to <hi>Adam, Where art thou?</hi> And, <hi>Who told thee that thou wert naked?</hi> And, <hi>Haſt thou eaten? &amp;c.</hi> To which three queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>Adam</hi> gave three anſwers; <hi>Thou gaveſt me the Woman; ſhe gave it me, and and I did eat.</hi> Then he put but one Queſtion to <hi>Eve, What haſt thou done?</hi> To which ſhe made two anſwers, <hi>The Serpent beguiled we, And I did eat:</hi> to ſhew that ſhe alſo was Limited in her tongue, though ſhe would give two an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers to one queſtion. So that by this Text we ſee, that Man may enjoy a certain diſcourſe, or ratiocination with God (for this was after <hi>Adams</hi> fall) but the Woman a very little. But other
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:101580:69" rendition="simple:additions"/>Creatures are Subject to his Voyce without ratiocinating, for without An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer from the Serpent <hi>The Lord ſaid to the Serpent,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe thou haſt done this,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 27.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is not ſufficient to refrain from Evil our ſelves, but we are not to tempt others to it either by precept, ſuggeſtion, or Example. That this Serpent had a Cunning wit the Text ſhews, that he was Beautiful, ſome Writers affirm; Whether he eat or not let Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tators agree; for if conſidered as a Serpent, what good was the knowledg of good to him? if Conſidered as the Devil, the eating could not add to his Knowledge of goodneſs, becauſe he knew more in his Primitive perfection then could be added to him by ſecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dare meanes. However we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, either by remembrance of his former Condition, or by eating this, he knew goodneſs notionally, not practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally; but the Evil he not only knew, but tempted <hi>Eve</hi> to the Knowledge of it. And this by his ſubtilty and Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, two ſuch temptations to that ſex, that their vertues muſt ſeem to reſiſt the harmony of Nature by reſiſting of them, eſpecially when they meet in one
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:101580:69"/>Perſorn. And herein methinks <hi>Eve</hi> was more excuſable then <hi>Adam,</hi> for here was a Lovely Serpent, a delicate Fruit pleaſing to the Eye, delightful to the taſte, and of a promiſing virtue; What Woman could well reſiſt thoſe Temptations? Now <hi>Adam</hi> had no more to tempt him, (as appears by the Text) then an implicit Love and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to his Wife, for <hi>ſhe gave it him,</hi> (without any perſwaſive induction that we read of) <hi>and he did eat.</hi> Now God did juſtly begin the puniſhment with the firſt offender (the Serpent) and gave ſentence on him for tempting before he did it on thoſe that were tempted, one being a premeditate, wilful and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronting act, againſt his poſſitive Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, the other occaſional.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thou art Curſt.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 28.</note> Curſing is an inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Revenge, and <hi>Revenge is mine, ſaith God.</hi> But becauſe 'tis ſweet and pleaſant to the taſt, and indeed hath a reliſh of Ambition, we Mortals) who have only power to intend, and not a poſitive power to act revenge) do La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh our ſpirits into execrations, which is an affront to the Deity, as high as can be given; and it is oft ſeen, that by them they heap Coales of fire on their
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:101580:70"/>own heads; for when there is ſuch a Concretion of Evil ſpirits (as attend Curſes) ſummon'd together, they muſt fix ſomwhere, and (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>A curſe cauſeleſs ſhall not take effect where it was intended:</hi> And then it muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily fall upon him that did intend it, which is but ſutable to Divine Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; and therefore in things provoking our paſſions we muſt follow Gods Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample herein, who firſt examined the fact by theſe Interrogatives, <hi>Where? Who? What?</hi> and thoſe acknowledged, he gave his Curſe, and not before: we are not to be guided by provocations, but deliberations; and the <hi>Targum</hi> ſays, <hi>God call'd theſe three, viz. Adam, Eve and the Serpent into Judgment before he gave his ſentence;</hi> and we ſee that a Curſe is a thing of that tranſendent Nature, even Man and Beaſt, and the Earth it ſelf, have felt th'effects of it. And though <hi>David (a Man after Gods heart)</hi> did abound with them, as we may read in his <hi>Pſalms,</hi> and imprecated God for their performance, and many of them granted; yet upon peruſal of the Hiſtory of his life we ſhall find many of them to take no effect on thoſe he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, and ſome of them Retorted on
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:101580:70"/>himſelf and family. God knows his own diſpoſures beſt, and that many times the ſucceſs of our Curſes would be the greateſt Curſe to our ſelves, for he will execute them his own way. So that we ſhew our duty and piety to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him in forbearing, and our greateſt folly in pronouncing them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Above all Cattel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 29.</note> 
                     <hi>and all beaſts of the field.</hi> By Cattel is meant tame Beaſts, and by Beaſts of the field, wild beaſts. (as I have ſhewn elſwhere.) Now in the firſt part of the third Chap. the Serpent is ſaid to be the ſubtileſt of the wild beaſts, and conſequently more ſubtile then the tame, for their want of fears, and their having (by a domeſtick At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance) almoſt all things neceſſary provided for them, they have need of that ſubtilty or craft which is requiſite for the wilder. However the Curſe ſeems firſt to deſcend on the tame beaſts, which in our Tranſlation is ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered inſtead of Cattel, <hi>Curſed be thou above thy fellows;</hi> to ſhew that the tame were his fellows, for therein was part of the Serpents ſubtilty, to be too ſubtil for the tame, by his diſſimulation of his tameneſs; and more ſubtile then the wild, by Contriving more inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:101580:71"/>I muſt confeſs I am poſed at the Almighties ſeverity herein, unleſs it were becauſe they were ſuch fools to aſſociate with a Beaſt of ſuch a ſubtile and trecherous nature; and it ought to be a <hi>Caveat</hi> to all innocents, to be circumſpect in their intermixture with ſuch dangerous Companions; yet this daily happens both in Families and States; which can carſe be prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but by a ſedulous care of our ſelves and actions, and well weighing the nature and inclinations of others; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is our Fate to be intermixed with ſuch, we muſh abſtract the wiſdom of the Serpent from his ſubtilty, and be as wiſe as he, and retain that innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy wherein we are Conſtituted, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be like the Dove, or Lamb, or ſuch other Creatures, whoſe gentle na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ought to be our examples.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>On thy Belly ſhalt thou go,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 30.</note> 
                     <hi>and Duſt ſhalt thou eat all the dayes of thy Life.</hi> The <hi>Targum</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> adds, <hi>Thy feet ſhall be cut off, and thou ſhalt caſt thy skin every ſeaven years, and there ſhall be de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ly poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in thy Mouth.</hi> Here the <hi>Targum</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains this Curſe by reading, that his feet ſhould be cut off, and that he ſhould caſt his skin, and his mouth
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:101580:71"/>be full of poyſon which intimates, that he had feet, and that his skin or beauty was permanent, and that his breath was ſweet and pleaſing before the curſe. Now it was not the want of feet that made the curſe, for many creatures have the like want, as Snakes and Inſects, yet are accompted perfect in their kind: Nor the eating duſt, for moſt do ſo; for what creature in ſome proportion doth not daily eat it? For though 'tis ſaid the <hi>Camelion</hi> lives by Aire, yet it is the Atomes or duſt in the aire that nouriſheth it: Nor caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the skin, for moſt creatures do ſo every ſeaventh year; and Phyſicians hold that the skins of ſerpents and Snakes ſo exuviated are very Medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, nor having poyſon in their mouth; for moſt Creatures in ſome proportion afford the like, both Man and Beaſt; but the changing of that due frame, proportion and conſtitution to another which is worſe, and that was, and ſtill is the curſe that hangs on us: For if our Eyes be made perſpicuous, our Eares Muſical, our Touch delicate, our Taſt diſtinctive, our ſmell pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervative, our Limbs ſtreight, and our Minde pure and ſerene, in bodies har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniouſly
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:101580:72"/>Compoſed; yet if we dim our Eyes, deafen our Eares, vitiate our touch, taſte, or ſmell, obfuſcate our mindes by the ill contracts or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits of our bodies; Theſe are the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes upon the uſe of forbidden fruits, that is, the uſe and habit of Evil Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; for to uſe our ſound and perfect conſtitutions otherwiſe then God by Reaſon prompts us to, is a decurtation of our feet, and an exuviation of our Conſtituted beauty, which ſills us with ſuch venomous qualities, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven our very Breaths are infections to thoſe who are more virtuous.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 3. Verſe 15.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And I will put Enmity between thee and the Woman,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 31.</note> 
                     <hi>and between thy ſeed and her ſeed, and it ſhall bruiſe his Head, and thou ſhalt bruiſe his Heel.</hi> The <hi>Targum</hi> of <hi>Onkelous</hi> reads the latter part of this verſe thus, <hi>Ipſe Recordabitur, He ſhall remember thee, and what thou didſt to him from the beginning, and thou ſhalt obſerve him in the end.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Targum</hi> of <hi>Jonathan</hi> renders that part thus; <hi>Et erit, And it ſhall come to paſs, when there ſhall be Sons of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man which obey the precepts of the Law,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:101580:72"/>they ſhall uſe their endeavour to ſtrike thee at thy head: but when they ſhall forſake the precepts of the Law, thou ſhalt ſtudy to bite them in their heels; but to them it ſhall be a medicine to thee, becauſe they applied the medicine to the heels in the days of the King Meſſias.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This Text is of an ambiguous na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but becauſe <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians</hi> make it the firſt Prophetick Text con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and having written ſomething of the Diverſity of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, I ſhall refer this to ſome other place, to be diſcourſed of more at large. And though my Notions herein may differ from other Writers, yet without prejudice I hope to Chriſtian Religion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 3. Ver. 16.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And to the woman he ſaid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 32.</note> 
                     <hi>I will greatly multiply thy ſorrows in thy conception, and in ſorrow ſhalt thou bring forth children.</hi> The <hi>Targum</hi> reads it, <hi>I will multiply thy affliction and pains by the bloud of thy vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginity and conceptiou:</hi> which ſhews, that as the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> without fraction of any Membranes, which cauſeth that virginate effuſion of bloud, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently pain; and alſo without pain in conception or eduction brought forth a
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:101580:73"/>child: ſo ſhould every woman ('tis ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd) have enjoyed the like benefit, had not this curſe come upon them. I confeſs, 'tis ſcarce conceivable how fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions or extenſions of parts could be without pain, but we ſee how Oyls and other Arts prove Emunctions and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitives. And we need not doubt of the Almighties power and kindneſs in imparting unto them ſuch knowledge, whereby they ſhould have enjoyed a progeny with pleaſure, both in Admiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; Ejection, Conception, and Emiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, without that Philoſophical doom (not onely upon Man but other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) that all creatures after <hi>Coition</hi> are ſad; which I will not diſpute whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it is becauſe the pleaſure is ſo ſhort, or ſome intermixture of pain con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>current or expectant; ſo that there is an immediate and inexpreſſible ſenſe of the departure of ſome Animal Spirits from them, which are to ſupply ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther body, as it were robbing them of their Native properties. But for her complying with the Serpent, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by diſobeying God and Man, ſhe is juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doomed to thoſe pains, which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly are no way compenſated with thoſe pleaſures which <hi>Tiriſius</hi> tells us
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:101580:73"/>of, for thoſe pleaſures which are, are rather Inductives, and inſnare into pains and tortures, then any real plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures: for we may obſerve, that thoſe who enjoy the moſt, are loaded with Diſeaſes and Diſtempers, either in Youth or Age, able to reſtrain the moſt Libidinous from enjoying their Phanſies more then Realities.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And thy deſire ſhall be to thy husband.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 33.</note> Our Tranſlation in the word <hi>Deſire</hi> follows the <hi>Hebrew;</hi> and Deſires are in <hi>Latin Deſideriae,</hi> derived from <hi>Sydera,</hi> the Stars; in which formerly, and now in this Age, we place ſuch an efficacy, as to think they have a power over, or vertue to guide our actions: and ſuch a deſire ought every woman to have towards her husband.</p>
                  <p>Other Tranſlators call Deſire <hi>Cupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditas,</hi> from <hi>Cupid,</hi> which is <hi>Cuipio:</hi> that is, that our deſires ſhould be to ſuch, as to whom we may attribute a Piety or Goodneſs: and upon the like account the wife ought to have her deſires to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her husband.</p>
                  <p>Others render the <hi>Latin</hi> for Deſire <hi>Amor,</hi> that is, <hi>a morte:</hi> that ſhe is to believe, he is of power to preſerve her even from dying by his vigilant care
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:101580:74"/>over her: and therefore ſhe ought to have her deſires towards him, even for her own preſervation.</p>
                  <p>Others read Deſire <hi>Converſio tua,</hi> &amp;c. that ſhe is to turn and move according as her husband thinks fit to govern: for going two ways can never be ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesful and is oppoſite to a Conjugated Love.</p>
                  <p>Others read <hi>Neceſſitus tua;</hi> that is, <hi>Neceſsaseſse;</hi> that is, there is ſo perfect a neceſſity in obedience, that it muſt be performed by the wife, leſt ſhe ceaſe to be, or at leaſt to enjoy any content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to her ſelf or husband.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Targum</hi> reads it <hi>Appetitus tua, (a petione;)</hi> that is, whatever ſhe deſires of her husband muſt be in a ſubmiſſive and petitionary way.</p>
                  <p>Now though our Verſion ſaith onely <hi>Thy deſire ſhall be to thy husband,</hi> it doth not exclude his to her, even in the ſame ſenſes as before recited: for doubtleſs as the queſtion is undecided, whether we ſee by Extramiſſion or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tromiſſion: ſo it is in the deſires be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Man and Woman, whether the object of him attracts her deſires, or the object of her attracts his; or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be an unexpreſſible uniting of
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:101580:74"/>viſuals in a moment; (by viſuals I mean the form and figure of what is ſeen, as well as that which ſees.) And it is hard to find out this Attraction by other demonſtration then this or the like Experiment: Take a piece of Iron untouch'd by a Loadſtone, and ſuch an other piece of Iron as hath been touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, of an equal weight with that which is untouch'd; lay theſe upon two pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Cork of equal weight, and flote them upon the edges of a veſſel of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: then fix a thred from ſide to ſide of the veſſel, at an equal diſtance from the two Irons, mounted on their Corks oppoſite to each other, and the Irons with their Corks will by an equal pace ſwim towards the thread or centre to meet each other, and then both will joyn with an amicable embrace, as if neither would yield to an Attraction, but by a ſtately, eaſie, and equal mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo mutually move to an union at their centre. And though 'tis ſaid, her <hi>deſire ſhall be to her husband,</hi> yet he is not to hide or retract his mutual and reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procal love and deſires; but to let them meet in one centre and conjugated affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="140" facs="tcp:101580:75"/>
                     <hi>And he ſhall rule over thee.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 34.</note> 
                     <hi>Regulabi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> in our Tranſlation; that is, he ſhall be as a King to guide thy publick affairs: <hi>&amp; dominabitur,</hi> ſays another; that is, he ſhall be a Director alſo in thy dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick concerns. Both which we tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate, <hi>He ſhall rule over thee;</hi> that is, be a rule or guide to thy actions. Or, as Stars are ſuppoſed to guide inferior bodies by their influence; ſo by his pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety and exemplary life to direct and guide her to an upright converſation, and in all hazards of life and death to cheriſh or prevent them. And were this diſpoſition in husbands, and that imitation in wives, the curſe would be a bleſſing; but the curſe is ſtill in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractorineſs of obedience. And wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are ſtill ſubject to repeat what the Serpent taught, viz. <hi>that they may eat:</hi> that is, that they may taſt of forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fruit, and take irregular courſes, thinking to gain experimental know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and that they <hi>ſhall not die,</hi> or be accuſed thereby for diſobedience.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 3. Ver. 17.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And to Adam he ſaid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 35.</note> 
                     <hi>Becauſe thou haſt hearkened to the voice of thy wife, and haſt eaten of the tree the which I commanded
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:101580:75"/>thee, ſaying, Thou ſhalt not eat of it.</hi> It is the voice that gives the chief diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the ſeveral kinds of living crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and the <hi>ſpecies</hi> of thoſe kinds are alſo diſtinguiſhed by it; ſo that there is ſcarce any individual of any kind, which hath not ſome audible found or voice different from each individual of the ſame kind; and though each kind agree in the intention of their voice ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriate to each kind, ſo that they underſtand each other, as the Horſe his kind, the Sheep his; yet Man, who is the rational Judge, doth perfectly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend (even in his imperfect ſtation) that the individuals of each kind have different voices: even the Nightin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gales differ, though not in their Notes, yet in their Keys, ſome higher, ſome lower. But in all creatures which have Muſical voices Man undertakes the Umpirage: and in reſpect of his own race, there is no creature to whom he attributes ſo much pleaſure, as to the voice of a Woman; and the more if he hath ſome additional Affection for her perſon: for 'tis known, that their very ſpeech hath captivated ſome men, not for the Rhetorick of what ſhe ſpeaks, but the mere Phantaſm of her
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:101580:76"/>voice. And if we do this whileſt we are under this ſtate of Imperfection, who almoſt could blame <hi>Adam</hi> whileſt he had the perfection of Judgment, and ſhe the accompliſhment of what could make her a perfect voice, ſo far to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulge his harmonious mind as to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to it? So that certainly God was not angry with him for this, but is was for his hearkening to her voice of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation, to ſuch a voice as did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſe the appetite of <hi>Adams</hi> ear, (for that was diſpenſible;) but ſuch a voice as provoked him to an inordinate act, in doing what he was forbidden; for our delights and contentments ought to be guided, not by what is ſimply plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable and contenting to our ſelves, but what is juſt and ſutable to Gods commands.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Curſed be the ground for thy ſake.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 36.</note> We had need to take care of our actions, whenas we ſey by the Text, and daily ſee how many Innocents ſuffer by our miſactions. The <hi>Targum</hi> ſaith, that <hi>the ground was curſed becauſe it did not warn Adam of this tranſgreſſion.</hi> And it may be the Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> had his Phanſie from the <hi>Targum,</hi> that the Earth was a great <hi>animal,</hi> and that the breath
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:101580:76"/>thereof was the Sea, which cauſed the Ebbing and Flowing. If ſo then, as it had knowledge within it ſelf of all Gods commands, ſo it ought to have admoniſhed <hi>Adam,</hi> and not doing it occaſioned this curſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In ſorrow (or tears.)</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 37.</note> Tears and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows are ſynonimous, for we do not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs our ſorrows ſo effectually as by tears; for grones and ſighs are but eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porations of our troubled ſpirits, but tears are a more condenſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted evidence of our ſorrows, as if recollected and diſtilled from all the ſuffering parts of Man. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>David</hi> prays, that God would <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bottle his tears;</hi> of which I have ſpoke more in the Chapter of <hi>Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And though we oſt ſhed tears for joy, yet they give ſuch a compreſſure to all parts, that they ſeem to be derived ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the ciſtern of ſorrow then joy, becauſe there uſually follows ſuch an immediate diſcompoſure both to the body and mind of thoſe who ſhed them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Shalt thou eat thereof all the days of thy life.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 38.</note> The Chyle that feeds us in the womb, the Milk when we are born the
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:101580:77"/>varieties of food in our Youth and Age, is but a nimble tranſmutation of the Earth, ſo little, that the greateſt part in few hours naturally turns to earth again; and that which ſtays longer, (our Bloud, Fleſh, and Bones) is ſtill but earth in various forms and colours, even every minute ſubject to accidental alteratioas into its original maſs: this is our Curſe. But what food we ſhould have had void of ſuch tranſmutations or corruptions, nor Schools nor Human Reaſon can inform us, onely our Faith believes, that when the days of life are ended, that <hi>our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption ſhall put on incorruption, and our mortality immortality:</hi> in which ſtate we ſhall be above the uſe and decay of Elements, becauſe that Beautifical Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which we expect will make us per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, without any other ſupplement but it ſelf, which conſiſts not in fulneſs of any matter, but unexpreſſible Illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thorns and thiſtles ſhall it bring forth to thee.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 39.</note> We may obſerve that Gods curſes upon thoſe Innocents have ſome mixture of bleſſings; for the Earth is made part of our Human bodies, and Thorns and Thiſtles have their ſana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:101580:77"/>vertues on us, as well as prickles to hurt us. <hi>Spina</hi> ſignifies as well the Backbone, wherein our ſtrength and health conſiſts, as thoſe prickles which offend us. And <hi>Joſeph of Arimathea's</hi> Staff was transform'd into a Thorn ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then any other Shrub, as a Signal of his Profeſſion. And <hi>Tribulus</hi> (a Thiſtle) may as well be called <hi>Tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bulla,</hi> a threefold Ornament, intimating the Trinity, which ſhould be more diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to us, as Tribulations or Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And theſe <hi>Tribuli</hi> (or Thiſtles) have their virtues too as well as their offences: and it is remarkable, that one of the kinds of theſe Thiſtles is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Chriſts Thiſtle</hi> by the Herballiſts, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuppoſition that the Crown where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Chriſt was in part crucified, was made of the pricky ſubſtance of that Thiſtle. So that as the Earth was cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in bringing them forth, yet they had ſome kind of honour to be made uſe of upon ſo ſignal an occaſion. And Thorns are of that great uſe in this part of the world, as that whereas before things ſeemed to have a Community, now by Incloſures and Fences made of them each man enjoys his own proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with more ſecureneſs. And the
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:101580:78"/>Thiſtles give a teſtimony of the rich' neſs of the ground where they grow and by Tranſplantation turn to an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual nouriſhment, as Artichokes, &amp;c. Thorus and Thiſtles do not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude more pleaſant Plants, for amongſt Gods curſes there are bleſſings, and his mercies flouriſh with his juſtice.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 3. Ver. 18.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And thou ſhalt eat the herb of the field.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 40.</note> Soon after Man was created, in the 29th. verſe of the firſt Chapter, ſaith God to <hi>Adam, I have given you every herb, and it ſhall be to you for meat:</hi> there the Injunction was upon the Herb, that it ſhould be for the food of man; but here 'tis ſaid, <hi>Thou ſhalt eat the herb of the field,</hi> and here the Injunction was up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Adam</hi> to eat. He was at ſome liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty before to eat, but now his food is reſtrained; and therefore ſome do que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion whether we do not multiply <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> tranſgreſſion by our continued eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of other creatures, which were not then allowed to us: for if we conſider the numerous living creatures, whoſe bloud is ſhed to fill our Appetites, we have nothing almoſt to plead for the doing ſo but Cuſtom, or ſome neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:101580:78"/>to leſſen the number of thoſe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, leſt they ſhould grow ſo numer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous as to deſtroy thoſe herbs of the field that ſhould feed us; or their Carca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes by death be more offenſive then the Ordure which we extracted from them. So that by this extravagancy of food we ſeem to continue our curſe, in that we cannot frame and comply our Appetites to that which doubtleſs would be moſt beneficial to our tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers; eſpecially if we conſider the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of herbs, either in their flowers, brauches, or roots, not onely ſanative, but more ſafely nutrimental to our health then any other food.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 3. Ver. 19.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the ſweat of thy face ſhalt thou eat bread, untill thou return unto the ground.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 41.</note> As Tears proceed from the motions of Joy and Sorrow, and ſeem to be extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted from the moſt internal parts, and ſo diſtilled from the eye, the moſt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate part of Man: ſo Sweat by labour or pain is the extraction of the outward parts into a liquid matter, paſſing through the Pores, to eaſe it ſelf by diſcharging that oily and watery ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. Now ſome parts are more apt
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:101580:79"/>then others to vent it, and ſuch in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick are called the Sudatory parts, as the Armholes, &amp;c. becauſe being na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally kept more warm, the Pores are more paſſable: Now the Brow or Face being more bony then thoſe, yet do as quickly ſend forth that humour as the other parts, and the rather be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Spirits run towards the Brain, and that Pan hath many Sutures about it, through which that humour is more quickly vented. And there is ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the word <hi>Sudor</hi> Sweat, and <hi>Suturae</hi> Sutors; for through thoſe the Brain doth more eaſily purge itſelf by Sweats; and they more commonly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Brow, near which the Sutures are, then any other part.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thou ſhalt eat bread.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 42.</note> It is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that Bread (as we now take it) was known in Paradiſe; therefore the word <hi>Cibum</hi> is more uſed by Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlators then <hi>Panem:</hi> that is, whatever food he ſhould eat for the future, he was to labour and take pains for it, and that muſt neceſſarily produce ſweat to the brow or face.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Untill thou return to the ground:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 43.</note> 
                     <hi>for of duſt thou wert made, and to duſt thou ſhalt return again.</hi> Concerning theſe read
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:101580:79"/>my Diſcourſe of Immortality. The <hi>Targum</hi> adds, <hi>And from duſt thou ſhalt riſe again, that thou mayeſt give a reaſon for all things thou haſt done in the day of the great judgment.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 3. Ver. 20.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And Adam called his wife Eve (or Eva) becauſe ſhe was the mother (filiorum) of all (the ſons of men) living.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 44.</note> If we will give credit to the Hiſtory of other Nations, there were other people then in being, and many years before; but the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> (ſay they) were the ſelect people from which God did derive that Church, which hath ſpread over the greateſt part of the world; firſt by <hi>them,</hi> then the <hi>Patriarchs,</hi> then the <hi>Jews,</hi> then <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> and the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Jacobines</hi> aſſume an Intereſt, and do as hardly admit us as we them to the undeniable Progeny of thoſe two Anceſtors. But all agree, that at one time or other we came from the earth both by Father and Mother; and by experience we agree thither we ſhall return again: and moſt agree to a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of rewards or puniſhments for our virtues or offences.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="verse">
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:101580:80"/>
                  <head>Cap. 3. Ver. 21.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And to Adam and his wife the Lord God made coats of skins, and clothed them.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 45.</note> Our <hi>Engliſh</hi> cannot render the words better then <hi>coats</hi> and <hi>clothed;</hi> though we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſuppoſe that there were either <hi>coats</hi> or <hi>clothes</hi> in the infancy of the world, unleſs we will make it an argument for the <hi>Prae-Adamites:</hi> but according to the <hi>Arabic</hi> they were clad with the Hides of Beaſts. But the <hi>Targuim</hi> of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>z</hi> ſaith, <hi>God took off the Serpents skin which tempted them, and put it on them:</hi> and it was but juſt that the Tempter ſhould be ſo ſerved; and 'tis wiſhed thoſe garments have not infuſed ſuch a continued ſubtilty into their ſucceſſive Generations, that the moſt part of the world conſiſts of Subtilty and Cheats even to this day, and their former gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Onyx</hi> or Virtue is now ſcarce known to us but by its name.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 3. Ver. 22.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the Lord God ſaid,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 46.</note> 
                     <hi>Behold, the man is become like one of us, to know good and evil: and now leſt he put forth his hand, and take alſo of the tree of life, and live for ever.</hi> The tree of good and evil, and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:101580:80"/>the tree of life, have been diſcourſed of in the precedent Sections: that which may be added concerning the tree of life is, that it ſhould have ſuch virtue as to make <hi>Adam</hi> by his eating thereof live for ever. It is much that Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhould ſo puzzle the world, whenas we ſee here that it had been gained merely by the ſenſe of taſting or eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; for certainly even the beſt things we know or can attain to come firſt to our Senſes, then to our Reaſon and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellect; yea, even the greateſt Notions of Faith have their original from ſome Senſe, becauſe by being ſenſible of things which Senſe illuſtrates to us, we believe greater that are not ſo ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible: And Eternity it ſelf is appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by us with the contemplation of a Beatifical Viſion, which we ſee comparatively by thoſe glorious crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of light, &amp;c. which with varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of contentments we daily behold; and ſo by the gradations of whatever we ſee, touch, taſte, hear, or ſmell, the Contemplative man may mount them to ſuch a pious degree, that every ſenſe will as it were injoy a preſent eternity, which doth not altogether conſiſt in an undetermined continuance, but in a
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:101580:81"/>continuance which infolds all imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry contentments, which can be gradual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuppoſed by the moſt elevated ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. And though <hi>Adam</hi> was debarred from eating of this tree, yet our Divines ſay, that we now eat it Sacramentally; &amp; without a Manducation there can be no Sacramental Faith. So that Senſe is the firſt act which leads us to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effable higher ſenſe, communicated to us by that tree of life of which we ſo eat; and this gives us ſo perfect a ſenſe of eternity, that this thin ſhadow of Mortality cannot keep even the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent fruition from our ſenſes, and thoſe ſenſes wrap us in their preſent enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For we ſee in common Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that Salts (and things of ſuch agile natures) paſs with eaſe through ſeveral Mediums: ſo may our Seaſes if they will imploy their activities other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then to carnal uſes. Which <hi>Adam</hi> not doing,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 3. Verſe 23.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Therefore the Lord God ſent him forth to till the ground,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 47.</note> 
                     <hi>from whence he was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</hi> It appears by the ſeventh verſe, that <hi>Adam</hi> was made of the duſt of the ground, not within the circuit of the
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:101580:81"/>Garden or <hi>Paradiſe;</hi> and in the 15. ver. that he was put into Paradiſe, and there to dreſs and keep pleaſurable what God had made pleaſant to him: but here in this three and twentieth he is put out of the garden to till that ground from whence he was taken; and there by tilling to adde Art to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, to change his pleaſure into labour, and his eaſe into induſtry. He, who was the firſt man, had but a ſmall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of felicity; and we, who are his ſucceſſors, feel the momentarineſs of our contentments here; they paſs away like a flaſh of Lightning, which vaniſheth with its ſight. Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to Honour do but tumble us ſo many degrees lower, Riches ſill us with cares, Plenty with diſeaſes, Pleaſures with ſorrows; and the ſame duſt that in the Sunſhine of Proſperity is raiſed beyond its centre, is by the Showres of Adverſity turned into mire and dirt, and made ſo contemptible, that all paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers by do ſhun it. And thus by a cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular motion we are made, exhal'd, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt, and involved in the reſtleſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon maſs of earth, undiſtinguiſhable from all things. But in our ſouls, which ſeem to have nothing to do here,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:101580:82"/>but to attend the motions of our duſt, and to give an account of every atom thereof, when the Cherubims ſhall be permitted to admit us into that heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> which we believe is reſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for us.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 3. Ver. 24.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>So he drove out the man,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 42.</note> 
                     <hi>and he placed at the eaſt end of the garden of Eden Cheru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bims, and a flaming ſword which turned every way, to keep the way of the tree of life.</hi> The <hi>Arabick</hi> Tranſlation ſaith <hi>Angels</hi> inſtead of <hi>Cherubims,</hi> which word <hi>Angels</hi> in a general notion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes all the Degrees of Angels: now the Schoolmen agree that there are nine Orders of them, <hi>viz.</hi> (according to <hi>Dionyſius</hi>) <hi>Seraphims, Cherubims,</hi> and <hi>Thrones, Archangels, Angels,</hi> and <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues; Dominations, Principalities,</hi> and <hi>Poteſtates.</hi> Yet they do not all agree in the ranking them; for ſome place Cherubims in the laſt Order but one: but whether firſt or laſt, we find the Order of Chetubims onely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to this ſervice. And as for the Flaming Sword, the word <hi>Verſatilis</hi> is uſed here for Turning every way, and is the ſame word which deſcribed the Serpent that tempted <hi>Eve, viz. Serpens
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:101580:82"/>verſatilis,</hi> and thereupon it may well be conjectured, that by this flaming ſword, &amp;c. is meant an order of evil Angels, appointed alſo to guard the way to the tree of life. For as there are Nine Orders of good Angels, ſo the Schools make nine Orders of Evil Angels, viz. <hi>Belzebub, Diabolus,</hi> and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lial; Aſmodeus, Sathan,</hi> and <hi>Merim; Abaddon, Aſteroth,</hi> and <hi>Mammon.</hi> Now of theſe <hi>Merim</hi> (the ſixth Order) is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Daemon Igneus,</hi> and is that Order (ſay they) which guides the Lightning and Thunder, and all ignital motions: and the ſtudy of Divination by fire is called <hi>Piromancy.</hi> So that this Tree being kept by Evil Angels, Intimates to us that Immortality ſhould not be gained by any of the race of Humanity, untill God thought fit to open the way to it, and diſmiſs thoſe Guards, and then the Good ſhall eat of that tree of Life, and the one thereby enjoy their endleſs felicities, and the others their endleſs miſeries, if <hi>Origens</hi> Opinion be not more favourable to the latter. But concerning Angels I have written elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="1" type="verse">
                  <pb n="156" facs="tcp:101580:83"/>
                  <head>Cap. 4. Verſe 1.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And Adam knew his Wife,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 49.</note> 
                     <hi>and ſhe conceived and bare Cain, and ſhe ſaid, I have gotten a man of the Lord.</hi> The <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabic</hi> Tranſlation ſaith <hi>Coivit</hi> inſtead of <hi>Cognovit;</hi> however both words ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Doing the Act of Generation, which is ſtill but a Tilling of earth, according to command. For how many have died in the very act, either by ſuffocating of the Spirits, or too violently tranſmitting them? But I obſerve, that the word <hi>Cognovit</hi> is uſed by almoſt all <hi>Latine</hi> Tranſlators, and I conceive juſtly rendered from their Original, which comes from <hi>Cognitio, Knowledge.</hi> And therefore we need not wonder that ſo many Philoſophers did contend, that the Venereal Senſe ſhould be ordained a Sixth Senſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (as I ſuppoſe) all our Knowledge is made Derivative by that act. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the commixture of Spirits in Coi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion make ſuch Congratulatory ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions to each other, that their very ſouls ſeem to be in an Extacy, whilſt the ſpirits are thus in Communication, and mutually imparting, as it were the Method of Creation, now in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:101580:83"/>to be traduced into a procreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. By the way I obſerve 'tis ſaid, that God drove out the Man, but the Womans expulſion not mentioned; yet here ſhe ſhewed the firſt example of her goodneſs and kindneſs, without Cumpulſion to follow and accompany him in all his labours and misfortunes, which is the moſt excellent property of a wife: yet ſhe was no ſooner come into the wide world, but ſhe ſhewed her Ambitious mind; for the <hi>Targum</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> reads this, <hi>and Adam knew his wife, who deſired an Angel:</hi> and that <hi>Targum</hi> ſaith, that ſhe Conceived and brought forth <hi>Cain</hi> and ſaid, <hi>I have got a Man, or Angel of the Lord;</hi> from whence that opinion might ariſe, That Mens bodies were only priſons here below for Angels, and that which we call ſouls are no other then impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned Angels, and that after this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finement they return again to the Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifical viſion. However her ambition was puniſht in her production of <hi>Cain,</hi> who ſet the firſt bad example of Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty and Imhumanity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="verse">
                  <pb n="158" facs="tcp:101580:84"/>
                  <head>Cap. 4. Ver. 2.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And ſhe again bore his brother Abel:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 50.</note> 
                     <hi>and Abel was a keeper of ſheep, and Cain a tiller of the ground.</hi> We find nothing in this Text of the Education of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> two ſons in their Infant years; but ſo ſoon as they were fit for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, <hi>Adams</hi> diſcretion guided the choice, and <hi>Eves</hi> fondneſs did not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct it, (which is a good rule for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers:) He ſaw the mild nature of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel,</hi> and robuſtous nature of <hi>Cain,</hi> (as is evident by their ſtory.) And it is ſaid here by the <hi>Septuagint, Fact us eſt</hi> inſtead of <hi>Fuit; Abel</hi> was made, that is, <hi>Abel</hi> by that nature which God had infuſed into him was made fit for that Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: And <hi>Adam</hi> perceiving his ſons temper purſued it, and made <hi>Abel,</hi> that is, imployed him in that calling which was ſutable to his nature. And the like <hi>Adam</hi> did by his ſon <hi>Cain,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his nature. We cannot force the temper or natural inclinations of our children, but when we know them, we ſhould rather improve then divert their honeſt inclinations; and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe two Imployments, as they were at firſt inſuſed into the two ſons
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:101580:84"/>of <hi>Adam,</hi> ſo there is room enough for all their poſterity to take a ſhare of them. For if we conſider the Paſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rul life of <hi>Abel,</hi> which is not onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to Sheep, for <hi>paſtor</hi> is as well a Herdſman as a Shepherd, but hath a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of inſpection into all ſuch Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as keep together in Flocks and Herds; which indeed is moſt uſual in tame beaſts: and from thence we learn Wiſdom, Sagacity, Sobriety, Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and almoſt all Moral vertues; by them we come to know Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the effects of Union, which keeps them from danger; and indeed almoſt all Phyſical Notions, as well Terreſtrial as Celeſtial: and therefore it is no marvel that a Paſtoral life hath ſuch real and univerſal Encomiums, ſeeing it affords not onely all the varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that Contemplation can afford or adminiſter to us, but withall ſo multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farious a mixture of the Active life, that nothing can be more ſatisfactory to us; eſpecially if we conſider the Products of thoſe Creatures which are under their Tuition, whether alive or dead, by their Wool, Hair, Ordure, Teeth, Fat, Entrals, &amp;c. (of which I have writ elſewhere.) Next, if we
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:101580:85" rendition="simple:additions"/>conſider the Agricoliſt from <hi>Cain,</hi> where Induſtry, Art, and Nature do concur; how many various Productions there are to encourage Labour and Art by ſeveral Grains, Trees and their Fruit, Quarries, Minerals, and Earths, we may ſafely conclude that there is no Conſtitution but may be fitted with a ſutable Imployment, both advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to themſelves and others. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can any Parent be to ſeek in their election and recommendation of Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment to their Children, becauſe their Infant years ſeem as it were to be allowed to the Parent, during that time to weigh and conſider of Imployments adequated for them. Now thoſe other Profeſſions, which fill the world with Conteſts, are not the proper Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which were tranſmitted to us by <hi>Abel</hi> and <hi>Cain,</hi> but rather adventitious and intruſive; and we may ſee by their ſtories how dangerous it was and hath been to admit a Diverſion from thoſe Original Rudiments, eſpecially in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Religion their pretence, as will be ſhewn in the next Diſcourſe between <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3-17" type="verses">
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:101580:85"/>
                  <head>Cap. 4. ver. 3. to 17.</head>
                  <head type="sub">A Digreſſion concerning <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And Cain offered to the Lord of the fruit of the ground,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 51.</note> 
                     <hi>and Abel of the firſtlings of his flock; and the Lord accepted Abels, and not Cains. Whereupon Cain was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and upon diſpute with Abel ſlew him, for which God was diſpleaſed, and baniſhed him. But yet Cain ſeemed to repent of the fact, whereupon God in favour ſet a mark upon him that none ſhould kill him: and he went and lived in the eaſt of Eden, where he begot children, built a city, and called it by his ſons name.</hi> What had <hi>Cain</hi> to do with a voluntary oblation of his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, (for as yet we ſee no order therein from God) as if he took a pride in them? <hi>Abel</hi> had as much reaſon to begin as he, but <hi>Abel</hi> did not meddle in ſuch matters, till <hi>Cain</hi> ſet him an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: and this may be the chief rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why <hi>Cainn</hi> ſacrifice was rejected, whatever <hi>Joſephus</hi> affirms; for hereby he did intrude to that which did not concern his vocation, and afterwards as it were to ſit in judgment with God Almighty, by diſputing what Sacrifice was acceptable, and what not, and why
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:101580:86"/>God refuſed one and accepted the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and which ſhould be beſt the Contemplative or Active life. In which controverſie methinks I hear <hi>Cain</hi> (as diſcontented at Gods refuſal) ſay to <hi>Abel;</hi> Is this that juſt God our father <hi>Adam</hi> tells us of? Was it Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in that God, think you, to puniſh him ſo ſeverely for eating a little fruit; whereas he that had power to make him, had as much power to hinder him from committing that offence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Creator? Was it Juſtice, think you, to baniſh him from all fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licities, and make him the ſubject of all miſeries, who but a little before was made his Image and ſimilitude? How can it conſiſt with a Divine Power to be ſo inconſtant? Or was it Juſtice towards me, that ſeeing we were commanded to till the ground in the ſweat of our brows; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that command I have dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and delved, and from my induſtry, and meerly from a pious mind, have dedicated my Labours to him as an acceptable ſacrifice; was it Juſtice in him to refuſe my ſacrifice, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of yours, brother <hi>Abell?</hi> for you lead a meer Lazy life, and offered no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:101580:86"/>as the Iſſue of your ſweating Labours, or worthy to be eſteemed a ſacrifice; yet doth this God accept of your Lazineſs, and reject my Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry. And therefore (ſaith <hi>Cain</hi>) I underſtand no more than this, (which is the <hi>Targum</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>) that there is a God that created the world; but yet he governs without any relation to good works, and is meerly partial; for elſe why ſhould he accept thine, and not accept mine? And the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> makes him more paſſionate, and affirms, that there is no judge of good or bad, nor no world to come, nor reward for the juſt, nor puniſhment for the wicked, nor that the world was created or governed by his mercy, becauſe (ſaith he) my of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering is not accepted, and thine is. But <hi>Abel</hi> was as poſitive (in which the <hi>Targums</hi> agree) who replied and ſaid, There is a God; that he is no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepter of perſons; that there will be a day of Judgment; and that he is a Righteous Judge; and that there is another world to come; and that there is a reward for the juſt, and a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the wicked: and this affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative was ſealed with <hi>Abel's</hi> blood;
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:101580:87"/>for in this heat of conteſt <hi>Cain</hi> ſlew him, and thereby made him the firſt Martyr for Religion. And thus we ſee how the Diſputes of the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial parts of it introduced the queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Fundamentals, (as at this day:) and here we ſee Diſputes turn'd into Paſſion, Paſſion to Rebellion, (the younger Brother, that is, the inferiour againſt the elder or ſuperiour;) Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion to Murder, and almoſt the higheſt Murder, Fratricide. And yet it is a Riddle to us, how God diſpoſeth of his Juſtice; for notwithſtanding <hi>Cain</hi>'s great offences againſt God and Man, by murthering his Innocent Brother, by his rugged anſwer to God, (<hi>Am I his Keeper?</hi>) and by his deſpair of God's Mercy; Yet I ſay, <hi>Cain,</hi> being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced (as appears by his acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) that he had finned both in ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding bloud, and denying God's Power, Goodneſs and Juſtice, order and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and that his ſin was beyond for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs, and greater than he could bear; God was ſo merciful as to ſet a mark upon <hi>Cain,</hi> to keep him from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: and <hi>Cain</hi> had ſo much glory in the world as to build a City for a Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to his poſterity; whilſt innocent
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:101580:87"/>
                     <hi>Abel</hi> never obtained any higher Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial than a great ſtone called by that name, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.8. and that bloud which lay weltering in the duſt, was called the bloud of Righteous <hi>Abel, Mark</hi> 23.35. neer 4000 years after the ſhedding of it. From whence it may be obſerved, that unleſs we know the time, circumſtances, occaſions, and ſecret reaſons and deſigns of God's diſpoſures, we cannot make any true collections who are good or bad by outward appearances, actions, or acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents; for the good endure Miſeries, and are puniſh'd with infamous death; the bad go free from impunities, and enjoy felicities, Titles, Honors, Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, and paſs in quiet to their graves, and both good and bad have ſometimes a ſhare of both. Nor is it poſſible to make a Judgment or theſe Rewards, becauſe no man can punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally know the exact time of anothers Converſion or Perverſion; that ſecret is only known to God himſelf, and we are not to doubt of Gods Power or Juſtice from the Conſequences of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane felicities or infelicities; or think that preſent Rewards are Gods appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bations, or infelicities his inflictions:
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:101580:88"/>nor ought we to trouble our ſelves with the Method or differences of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens devotions, but we are to mind our own quiet or induſtrious Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, there being ſufficient choice (as I ſaid) out of thoſe principles of Paſturage and Agriculture to buſie all ſorts of ingenious Natures and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, without medling with any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie in Devotions, or queſtioning of God's acceptation of what we or others do, being done with outward Conformity of worſhip, and inward clear intentions to pleaſe him. For the buſineſs of Religion is a particular Imployment not pertaining to Paſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage or Agriculture, which, as I ſaid, contains all Temporal Imployments. And when men did multiply, God did think fit to ſet up <hi>Melchiſedeck,</hi> which was thought to be <hi>Seth,</hi> becauſe men for the future ſhould not make their voluntary Oblations without directions from ſuch a function as was properly ordained for it. And after him the <hi>Levitical</hi> Order, purpoſely to direct and inſtruct men in their duty of Devotion and Spirituals. And as <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> were puniſh'd for intruding into their Function (which may ſeem to be then
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:101580:88"/>diſpenſible, in reſpect there were none ordained to it,) ſo it is as inconſiſtent and dangerous for that Order to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with the Functions of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel,</hi> unleſs it be by way of inſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or contemplation of God's Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but not of occupation or mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Functions; for by one the State is deſtroyed, by the other the Church. And I further obſerve, that the firſt Prieſt we read of was King of <hi>Salem,</hi> to ſhew that the directions in that fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction did proceed from the King or Government, which is beſt able to judge of its own Method in offering to God what is fit and conſonant to its conſtitution: and the <hi>Order</hi> of Prieſts are to give their ſutable inſtructions, ſo as theſe different Vocations may neither interfere nor incroach on each other, as properly belonging to the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Magiſtrate to keep them in a true Balance.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 5. Verſe 3.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And Adam lived a hundred and thirty years, and knew his wife again,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 52.</note> 
                     <hi>and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got a Son in his Likeneſs, after his Image, and called his name Seth. For ſhe ſaid, God hath appointed me another ſeed inſtead
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:101580:89"/>of Abel, whom Cain ſlew.</hi> I obſerve that theſe two exemplary Parents did not torment themſelves with paſſion for the murther of their eldeſt, and deprivement of their youngeſt ſon; or that they (as it were) loſt them in the prime of their youth, when they had been inſtructed in civil and Religious duties, and were Capable of ſuch Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments (as may be collected by the Text;) or for the want of ſuch aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciates and aſſiſtants to their injoyned Labours: None of theſe (I ſay) did promote a paſſion in them, or any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctancy againſt their Creators diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, it ſeeming equal to have no Children, or to have them with the care of Education and the anxieties in the loſs of them, or the diſcontents which may happen by their ill deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; but with patience and ſilence they undergo what God thought fit to permit, and a bleſſing did follow it; for he had another ſon in his Likeneſs after his Image, which (ſaith the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum</hi>) was like him in features, and like <hi>Abel</hi> in goodneſs of diſpoſition; for as <hi>Abel</hi> was a keeper of Sheep, and <hi>Cain</hi> a husbandman, this ſon <hi>Seth</hi> (as is conceived by ſome) was that <hi>Melchiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deck,</hi>
                     <pb n="169" facs="tcp:101580:89"/>as I ſaid, who was a Prieſt of the Living God. And thus in ſome meaſure every mans Patience and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion begets ſome Reward, which hath a ſimilitude to his expectation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 5. verſe 4.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And the dayes of Adam after he begat Seth were eight hundred years,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 53.</note> 
                     <hi>and he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat Sons and Daughters.</hi> According to ſome Rabbins <hi>Adam</hi> had thirty ſons and thirty daughters; and though it be ſaid here, he begat ſons and daughters; yet it doth not exclude ſuch danghters as were begotten before <hi>Seth,</hi> which thoſe Rabbins ſay were two, <hi>Calma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> and <hi>Deborah,</hi> and that they were the Wives of <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel,</hi> and if ſo, then probably when <hi>Abel</hi> was ſlain <hi>Cain</hi> took them both to be his wives; and then admit that they were all four born within four years of <hi>Adams</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſion out of Paradice, then within thirty years they might be all four ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of procreation, and have Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; ſo that the pre-Adamite needs not ſeek for the aſſiſtance of another Nation to People the Land of <hi>Nod,</hi> or the City of <hi>Enoch,</hi> ſince upon an eaſy multiplication in leſs then one hundred
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:101580:90"/>years, they and their progeny might eaſily produce and carry thither above five thouſand perſons.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="verse">
                  <head>Cap. 5. verſe 5.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And all the days of Adam were nine hundred and thirty years.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 54.</note> Eternity is ſo Circular, that a thouſand years are but as a day, and a day but as a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years; our knowledge of it is in the Abſtract, and therefore there is framed to us ſome <hi>Epoches</hi> and progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes by which this Eternity moves in its Circle; and to paſs by Minutes, Hours, and thoſe ſmaller gradations, we come to days, weeks and moneths, and years; and we make the Year to conſiſt of Moneths, the Moneths of Weeks, and the Weeks of days. Now thoſe who are not guided by thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions, do make a diverſion from theſe equal paths wherein Eternity would guide us; and thoſe who ſeem to be confounded in their va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Commenſurations; for ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted four weeks or eight and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty days to be a year, others ſeven moneths or eight and twenty weeks; others accounted their years by Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, others by Summors; ſome by
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:101580:90"/>Nights and Dayes artificial, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing I preſume the Winter to be the dead time of the year, and the Night no part of our life, and therefore ought not to be Computed within the compaſs of the Living year. But in later Ages the year was ſettled ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Natural day, conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of four and twenty hours, and the Sun and Moon dividing it into twelve Moneths, or thirteen Moones, or fifty two Weeks; within the year contained three hundred ſixty five dayes; but there happening ſix hours over in the yeare (to ſupply all defects by way of Intercalation) they have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded one day at the end of every fourth year, which is called the <hi>Biſſeztile</hi> or Leap year, becauſe in that year by that addition of one day there happens two days which muſt neceſſarily be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Sextilis Calend arum Martii,</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the interpoſition of that day, conſiſting of the forty ſix hours inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed; ſo that all thoſe leſſer Compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of the year being reconciled to my hand, I may go clearly upon the Literal ſenſe (as I have hitherto done in theſe diſcourſes) and affirm, that <hi>Adam</hi> lived Nine handred and thirty
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:101580:91"/>years, accounting the years either ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Julian</hi> or <hi>Gregorean</hi> Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlements, one being but 186. days more then the other in 930. years: For were it moneths or quarters, <hi>Mahala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> and <hi>Enoch,</hi> who begat children at ſixty five years, would not have been out of their Infancy when they are ſaid to beget Children: nor do I ſee any ground why we ſhould doubt that they lived ſo many years (accounting accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our Computations) when as they were neerer to the original perfection wherein <hi>Adam</hi> was made, and knew the ſanative virtues of all things; nor had they thoſe temptations of Exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancies which grew up with the exube<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rancy of the world. Beſides, we ſee even in our times to what great Ages Men and Women have arived even to two and three hundred years, though Climes, conſtitutions, vitiations by food, and other inordinacies do diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temper that harmony of nature, by which our forefathers did ſubſiſt.</p>
                  <p>Now nine hundred and thirty years want but ſeventy of a thouſand, and a thouſand are but as a ſpan; the ſpan is but what it can graſp, and why ſhould we labour to graſp that which
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:101580:91"/>(whether we hold or not) is equal at preſent, but diſadvantagious not only in the riddance of Anxieties, but alſo procraſtinating thoſe happy Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which even Common Reaſon guides us to believe. For though there is no mention made in our Tranſlations how <hi>Adam</hi> was diſpoſed of after he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet the <hi>Targum</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſays, <hi>Mortuus eſt, &amp; collectus fuit e medio Mundi:</hi> And it is ſufficient he was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the midſt of the troubles and anxieties of the world. And there can be no doubt, but that he who was impriſoned here nine hundred and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years for his offence, and had worn the badges of mortality in the skins of dead Beaſts for his cloathing, and digg'd his grave ſo oft in cultivating the Earth, as a reward for his fruga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and induſtry (after his death) enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſuch quiet felicities as I hope will be given to all ſuch as ſhall live and die here in a clear ſubmiſſion to our Creators Will.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And he died.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">§ 55.</note> We read of three ſorts of death; the Violent, which befel <hi>Abel;</hi> the Natural, <hi>Adam;</hi> and the Tranſmutative, <hi>Enoch:</hi> yet theſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions relate only to the manner,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:101580:92"/>for death is the ſame to all; and as the Poet ſaith, there are a thouſand ways to it. If it be forced, 'tis ſtill a death; or tranſmuted, (which is a kind of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible force) it is ſtill a death; or according to the extent of Nature, when ſhe or the ſoul being weary of the confuſions of this life, retires and hides it ſelf from performing any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther offices to the body; it is ſtill a death. And though <hi>Adam</hi> is ſaid to live nine hundred and thirty years, which is three hundred thirty nine thouſand ſix hundred thirty ſix days, (in which I compute the Biſſextile days) and if thoſe days be accounted by hours, and thoſe hours by minutes; yet it may truly be ſaid, that ſo many minutes as he lived, ſo many minutes he died; for the Caſualities which occaſion death are as many as thoſe which attend our lives, and therefore he which lives longer than another, paſſeth by only ſo many more Caſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; his life is not the longer, though prolonged, becauſe death hath ſtill an Intereſt in every prolongation, and is ſo clearly concerned, that 'tis not to be judged, who is living or who dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. At our Birth we break the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:101580:92"/>of Death, and lie at the mercy of Midwives, or other Keepers for our Evaſions; in our Infancy, Nurſes and Tutors; in our Youth, our Extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancies; in our riper years, our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion and indiſcretion, madneſs and ſobriety, are equal attendants; in Age, diſeaſes and infirmities are ready to uſher us to the Grave (a more ſevere Priſon;) and yet with little difference, for the grave of the womb gives life to us, and the other by our death gives life to multitudes of vermine; they by Corruption enrich the Earth, the Earth by that fertility affords us food, that food ſupports life: And ſo there is a Circulation of Generation and Corruption; and thoſe poſſibilities being in either, 'tis hard to judge which is living which dying. And it is not only thus in Terreſtrials, but even in Celeſtials: The day dies, the night produceth another, that dies again. And ſo in thoſe glorious Creatures in the heavens there is alſo a viſible Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of living and dying, and our life and death is but as night and day. And it ſeems an incivility towards God, or rather an affront to his diſpoſure, to deſire a long life, as if we would
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:101580:93"/>afford no room to our ſucceſſors, or permit God to be ſeen by any but our ſelves in his unexpreffible variations. And therefore the moſt conſonant way to our Immortality is to live in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued mortification: For ſo we ſhall live by dying, and die by living.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="commentary">
               <head>Of Life, Death, Reſurrection, and Immortality: As alſo of the Chemiſtry of Nature operating in our ſouls and bodies by which they are forced to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn.</head>
               <head type="sub">1 Cor. 15.22.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FOr as in Adam all die, ſo in Chriſt (the ſecond Adam) all ſhall be made alive,</hi> or have reſurrection from the dead. The joynt operation of mans <hi>ſoul</hi> and <hi>body</hi> is called <hi>Life;</hi> the Ceſſations of thoſe joynt motions <hi>Death.</hi> The ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and conſtant <hi>exchanges</hi> which Nature admits of are <hi>perplexities;</hi> for nothing in <hi>life</hi> is pleaſure but the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of an <hi>equal</hi> and <hi>contented mind;</hi> knowing our ſelves totally, or in our
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:101580:93"/>particles, to be every minute hurled about with the viciſſitude of <hi>Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions;</hi> the Ceſſation, (or at leaſt our want of knowledg what is done in the grave) ſeeming to be our <hi>quiet:</hi> But how far, or how long it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues 'tis hard to judge, ſeeing our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted parts are hourly traverſing into various <hi>Productions,</hi> of which we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, and into which we return again. But by reaſon of this Ceſſation or ſeeming <hi>ſeparation</hi> (not only of <hi>ſoul</hi> and <hi>body,</hi> but of the parts of the body into millions of <hi>forms</hi>) we (to ſupport our belief in the <hi>union</hi> of our parts) ſeek after the progreſſes and inclinations of other Creatures to theirs, (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their ſeveral Contingent ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions;) and therefore I think fit to ſet down ſeveral obſervables. And in the firſt place that Experiment of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving a <hi>Plant</hi> out of its <hi>aſhes</hi> is a noble piece of <hi>Chemiſtry,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dr.</hi> Browns Religio Medici.</note> and ſerves well to this purpoſe. And though ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vived <hi>Plant</hi> may want ſome of its <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents,</hi> yet the very <hi>revivification</hi> of it, if it gains not a full ſatisfaction to <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality,</hi> yet it affords us a fair teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the poſſibilty of our <hi>Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection;</hi> for then all the <hi>Accidental
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:101580:94"/>defects</hi> of nature ſhall be <hi>volatile,</hi> but the virtues and perfections of nature <hi>fixed.</hi> Indeed if <hi>we</hi> could find out by art a <hi>revivification</hi> of <hi>Vegetables</hi> in all their <hi>accidents,</hi> we ſhould make <hi>Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality</hi> too common: it is enough if a man can make any experimental in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement to his <hi>faith,</hi> and give an imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to future <hi>perfection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The whole Art of <hi>Chemiſtry,</hi> what is it (as I conceive) but to diſſolve the nature of a Creature, and to <hi>recollect</hi> it again, if not into its ſuperfluous acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, yet into a noble Evidence of its virtues? And this is done not ſo much by the force of <hi>Arts,</hi> as by the ſecret inſtinct and greedineſs of its own diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to unite its ſcattered nature. And that which is worthy of obfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation for our uſe in this <hi>Art</hi> is, Let the groſs body of any Creature be <hi>diſſolved</hi> or <hi>diſsected</hi> into many parts, that remaining part which is viſible to us, after its <hi>diſſolution,</hi> may by art be made to repreſent the form of it ſelf whilſt it had an entire being. This may be ſeen from the <hi>diſtillation</hi> of <hi>Plants,</hi> (that is, the Extract of them:) As for example; Make of <hi>Roſemary</hi> ſuch a Liquor as we call the <hi>ſulphur,</hi> by
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:101580:94"/>ſome the <hi>eſſence</hi> or <hi>ſpirit</hi> of it, and put it into a Viol or <hi>glaſs</hi> cloſed up, as <hi>Chemiſts</hi> do, after a little ſetling it ſhall by a certain kind of <hi>vapour</hi> or <hi>miſt</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent to the eyes the very ſhape of <hi>Roſemary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this may be more eaſily illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by another Experiment: About the ſpring time (when the bark begins to run,) take a young <hi>Aſh,</hi> and ſaw it off about a foot from the ground; then make a <hi>Concave</hi> hole in it, and cover it, and the ſappy <hi>juice</hi> or <hi>bloud</hi> of it will riſe up and fill the hole: then Lave out ſo much water as riſes in it, and put it into a glaſs, and ſtop the glaſs, as <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> do, by cloſing the Metal of the glaſs, and every ſpring you ſhall diſcern in the glaſs as it were an <hi>Aſh</hi> tree. Now I cannot tell whether the <hi>Miſt</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in <hi>Geneſis</hi> was the <hi>Eſsence</hi> with which God then indued all <hi>Vegetables,</hi> making them conſpicuable to Man, which before was not. And by this we may judg of the <hi>rational</hi> and <hi>vegetative</hi> ſoul; this had perfection of <hi>information</hi> from this <hi>Miſt</hi> which watered the Earth: The other from the <hi>breath</hi> of the Almighty. And whether by this breath is meant a <hi>miſty</hi> and <hi>wateriſh hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour</hi>
                  <pb n="180" facs="tcp:101580:95"/>(if with reverence we may ſo conceive of the divine breath, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to my former opinion) is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain: But if either, then the Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of the <hi>one</hi> may well advance the belief of the <hi>other.</hi> And if this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment ſhould hold in mans body as in Vegetables, how eaſie is it to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the manner of mans reſurrection, when by God <hi>Chemiſtry</hi> the <hi>Eſsence</hi> of each man in an inſtant repreſents to God (or to Man, being made capable of ſuch a ſight) the true <hi>Effigies</hi> and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion</hi> of his <hi>body?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in this notion, why may not I make uſe of that Metaphorical Speech of <hi>David? Put my tears into thy bottle, O Lord;</hi> which <hi>tears</hi> were the tears of <hi>Compunction</hi> and ſorrow for ſin, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from a <hi>Contrite heart,</hi> and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout brain, not from the Redundancy of a ſalt <hi>humour:</hi> ſo that I may call ſuch tears the very <hi>Liquor of life.</hi> Now whether ſuch Cordial tears, if they were put into a glaſs, would repreſent <hi>Man, David</hi> (that underſtood the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of <hi>God</hi>) knew beſt. And the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment were not unworthy the <hi>Tryal</hi> by a <hi>Penitent Chriſtian,</hi> to <hi>weep</hi> till he ſaw himſelf in his own <hi>tears.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:101580:95"/>there is ſeldom in man that true <hi>diſtillation</hi> or extract of <hi>tears</hi> which there ought to be, the experiment may be fallible.</p>
               <p>But that which may more eaſily be tried, is to take a <hi>Starling,</hi> and cover it with two <hi>wooden</hi> hollow diſhes, and it will weep it ſelf to death; and that Liquor were a fit ſubject for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periment of ſenſitive ſouls, till we can meet with a more certain one for the rational. But to go a little further with ſome notions or fancies concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Reſurrection.</p>
               <p>If by a <hi>Cabaliſtical Geometry</hi> it could be found out how many humane <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi> the <hi>Earth</hi> could afford out of its <hi>bulk,</hi> of which mens bodies were at firſt, are ſtill, and ſhall be (as it were) remade, allowing to each humane <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> ſuch a proportion of its mould or duſt as will make it ſuitable to the moſt perfect <hi>pattern,</hi> (for the beſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines hold we ſhall riſe with perfect <hi>bodies,</hi> and of ſuch perfect <hi>dimenſions</hi> as I have writ in a former Chapter in this book) I believe the general <hi>reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection</hi> might then be known. If alſo by an Hiſtorical Accompt it might be given in how many ſuch parts of the
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:101580:96"/>Earth have been already <hi>informed</hi> by ſouls, and how much ſtill remains to be <hi>informed.</hi> But becauſe <hi>Art</hi> may be fallible in ſo great a work of <hi>Phancy,</hi> we muſt ſubmit to <hi>Faith;</hi> by which I believe, that when the whole Earth ſhall be diſpoſed into <hi>bodies,</hi> that which we call the General <hi>Reſurrection</hi> will follow: And that when <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> ſhall paſs away, the <hi>bodies</hi> of the wicked ſhall remain in the place of the <hi>Earth,</hi> which ſhall be their <hi>Hell;</hi> and the bodies of the juſt in the place of the <hi>Coeleſtial Orbs,</hi> which ſhall be their <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This kind of <hi>Reſurrection</hi> or reſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our <hi>Earth</hi> doth not croſs the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> but confirm them; which ſayes, the <hi>Earth ſhall be no more,</hi> and that it ſhall be <hi>Conſumed</hi> by <hi>fire:</hi> for by this <hi>reſumption</hi> or <hi>transformation,</hi> the <hi>Earth</hi> ſhall (as it were) be turned into <hi>nothing,</hi> becauſe its parts ſhall become <hi>another thing.</hi> And there is a neceſſity that <hi>fire</hi> ſhould do this, for we ſee how <hi>metals</hi> will admit ſeveral <hi>mixtures</hi> with other <hi>metals;</hi> but let <hi>fire</hi> come once to diſſolve them, and they will all run with violence each to his proper <hi>kind.</hi> Now ſeeing this, I can eaſily believe
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:101580:96"/>that each <hi>body</hi> (though divided into <hi>Millions</hi> of <hi>parts</hi>) in the general <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flagration</hi> will run nimbly through all <hi>mediums</hi> to that <hi>ſoul,</hi> which once in one <hi>bulk</hi> they own'd, and which I ſtill be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve with a <hi>diffuſive virtue</hi> conſtantly hovers over it in its <hi>diſſections.</hi> And in this <hi>diſſolution</hi> or <hi>mutation</hi> (to confine my ſpeculations to what our Divinity imparts) the <hi>godly,</hi> being of a more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined <hi>metal,</hi> ſhall run <hi>one way,</hi> and the <hi>ungodly</hi> (as <hi>David</hi> ſays) ſhall be put away like droſs.</p>
               <p>Now that our Terreſtrial bodies ſhall not be <hi>conſumed</hi> or annihilated by this <hi>fire,</hi> I have ſeen experimented in <hi>Iron Kilns,</hi> (where the Iron ſtone is diſſolved) there you ſhall very often find large pieces of <hi>Charcole</hi> fall down with the <hi>Liquid Iron</hi> into the Furnace,<note place="margin">This Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cole is made of the <hi>Withy</hi>-tree, which grows fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in <hi>Worceſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire,</hi> where I firſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved it.</note> and from thence, when the Iron is let forth, it will ſwim out with it, but floting on the top of the Iron; and thoſe pieces of Charcole the fire hath no power over, or doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume.</p>
               <p>But that which gives a more deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate reliſh to the ſoul is another tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial Experiment, that if a <hi>Combuſtible matter</hi> be joyned to that which is not
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:101580:97"/>ſo <hi>Combuſtible,</hi> the leſs <hi>Combuſtible</hi> will preſerve the <hi>Combuſtible</hi> from deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. As for example:</p>
               <p>Take a piece of <hi>Thred,</hi> and tie it cloſe about a piece of Iron, and the flame of a <hi>Candle</hi> will never burn it; ſo out <hi>bodies</hi> (though combuſtible) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then joyned to our <hi>ſouls</hi> of a <hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual</hi> and <hi>uncombuſtible</hi> matter, will be preſerved from deſtruction and power of the <hi>Fire.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And though theſe Concluſions by <hi>Fire</hi> be pertinent to the manner of our <hi>reſurrection</hi> in ſo many variations, yet becauſe the <hi>reunion</hi> of our parts is the knottieſt piece of our belief, I ſhall aſſiſt mine with two Obſervations, concerning the <hi>Magnetick</hi> and <hi>concate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating virtue</hi> of moſt Creatures, either entire, or in parts; by which may be ſeen their inclination to <hi>union.</hi> As in the greedy ſociety of <hi>men</hi> to <hi>men,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>fat</hi> men to <hi>lean,</hi> and lean to fat, either to <hi>ſupply</hi> the defect, or <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct</hi> the <hi>ſuperfluity</hi> of either; <hi>beaſts</hi> to <hi>beaſts, Fowls, Fiſhes, Trees, Herbs,</hi> and <hi>Stones,</hi> to their <hi>kind;</hi> or in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring or dividing of moſt of theſe, how ſenſibly the <hi>parts</hi> divided ſeem to covet and fly to a <hi>Rejunction:</hi>
                  <pb n="185" facs="tcp:101580:97"/>as may be experienced in our diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred parts, but more fully in <hi>Snakes, Eels, Worms,</hi> (whoſe divided parts will run to each other.) The Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment is more eminent in two pieces of <hi>raw Beef</hi> (cut from one Beaſt) put into a pot of water, wherein adding a competent proportion of <hi>Comfrey,</hi> let them boyl a while, and they will cloſe together; but if the fleſh be from two beaſts, the <hi>Comfrey</hi> will not cement them. But the Demonſtration is more noble in <hi>Metals,</hi> of which take ſeveral pieces of <hi>Gold, Braſs, Silver, Iron, Tin;</hi> make them into the ſhape of <hi>Pins,</hi> two of each ſort, and lay them gently upon water in a <hi>Baſon,</hi> (and if it be carefully done they will not ſink;) then you ſhall perceive, that as they <hi>float,</hi> they will naturally hunt about to find each its <hi>proper kind;</hi> As <hi>Braſs</hi> to <hi>Braſs, Tin</hi> to <hi>Tin,</hi> &amp;c. and drawing near to their own, will ſeem to <hi>embrace</hi> with a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain joyful violence. The ſecond ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation is of water: Take of that which runs through ſeveral <hi>Minerals,</hi> and diſtil it, and when the <hi>liquid</hi> part is evaporated, the <hi>fixt</hi> matter that remains will lie in diſtinct <hi>parts,</hi> according to the number of <hi>Minerals</hi> which the
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:101580:98"/>water hath paſſed through. Thus our bodies, like ſeveral <hi>Liquors</hi> of different weight, (though jumbled together) will of themſelves return to their due <hi>place,</hi> and <hi>poſition;</hi> and though they be <hi>promiſcuouſly</hi> toſſed and uſed for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent by the ſeveral contrary and oblique courſe of the <hi>ſphears,</hi> and other <hi>interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,</hi> yet the firſt mover once ceaſing and giving ſtop to the reſt, all nature will return to a quiet <hi>harmony,</hi> and every <hi>Genius</hi> to embrace its own <hi>indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viduals:</hi> Or elſe I conceive that the <hi>Compoſition</hi> of <hi>Man</hi> (in his ſecundary productions ſince his Creation) being meerly compacted of <hi>variated</hi> or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted <hi>Elements;</hi> which makes ſome incline to <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> others to <hi>Ruſticity;</hi> ſome of the diſpoſition of <hi>Birds,</hi> others of <hi>Beaſts.</hi> Having thus paſt through the whole nature of <hi>other Creatures,</hi> as <hi>Trees, Flies, Worms, Birds, Beaſts, Earth, Water, Air,</hi> and <hi>Fire,</hi> &amp;c. All ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, from whence innumerable <hi>ſpecies</hi> are derived, ſhall at the laſt <hi>Conflagra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> or general <hi>Reſurrection</hi> be diſſolved into <hi>humanity,</hi> to make each man more or leſs <hi>intelligible,</hi> according to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of thoſe <hi>individuals</hi> of which he hath had an <hi>ingroſsment</hi> or <hi>participation.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb n="187" facs="tcp:101580:98"/>
            <head>Epilogue.</head>
            <p>THeſe ſeveral <hi>Philoſophical Notions</hi> ſupport my <hi>Faith</hi> in the belief of Divine <hi>Matters.</hi> If there be any man of ſo ſtedfaſt a <hi>faith,</hi> who cares not for the uſe of <hi>Reaſon, Senſe,</hi> or <hi>Phancy,</hi> in the conceiving of theſe and other <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries,</hi> I commend and admire him; he may in time remove <hi>Mountains:</hi> for my part, God hath made me a <hi>Rational Creature,</hi> and in Divine matters, what cannot be comprehended by my <hi>Reaſon,</hi> I ſhall implore his grace to give me <hi>faith</hi> to believe the <hi>poſſibility</hi> of them. In the mean time I ſhall be humble in my <hi>Enquiry</hi> after them, and if I may borrow ſomething from Nature, and from <hi>Phancy,</hi> from <hi>Sence,</hi> or <hi>Reaſon,</hi> to inſtruct me in ſuch <hi>Myſteries</hi> I ſhall not neglect them: But I ſhall ſtudy by not knowing them, to keep my <hi>Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">For the Etymolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of <hi>Phanſee</hi> is no mere than I would <hi>fain ſee.</hi>
               </note> rather than to loſe it by too cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious a <hi>ſpeculation.</hi> My <hi>Knowledge in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> my <hi>Phanſie, Senſe,</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> ſhall be all ſubject to <hi>Faith;</hi> not doubting
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:101580:99"/>but <hi>Faith</hi> will afford them all ſuch a <hi>ſupernatural Light</hi> as ſhall be profitable to their dull conſtitutions. The <hi>know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Nature</hi> is <hi>fallible; Senſe, Phanſie,</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> may be deceived; but true <hi>Faith</hi> cannot: Therefore they ſhall al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways follow my <hi>Faith.</hi> In which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit if they meet with any ſtop, I will give them leave to ſtay awhile, but not too long, leſt they loſe <hi>her way, her guide,</hi> and <hi>her object.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:101580:99"/>
            <head>The INDEX.</head>
            <list>
               <label>A.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>ADam, <hi>pag. 149.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Affections, <hi>139.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Angels, <hi>154, 157.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Apparel, <hi>150.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Appetite, <hi>138, 141.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Art, <hi>82.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>B.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>BAſe, <hi>15.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Beaſts, <hi>96, 130.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Birds, <hi>96.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Breath, <hi>13.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>C.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>CArnality, <hi>35.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cattel, <hi>ſee</hi> Beaſts,</item>
                     <item>Circumſpection, <hi>131.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Coition, <hi>156.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Colours, <hi>96.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Contentment, <hi>27.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Creation, <hi>1, 2, 17, 28, 30.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Cupidity, <hi>137.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Curſing, <hi>129, 133, 142.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>D.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>DArkneſs, <hi>ſee</hi> Light:</item>
                     <item>Day, <hi>49, 98, ſee</hi> Years.</item>
                     <item>Death, <hi>51, 98, 173.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Deſire, <hi>137, 138.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Diſobedience, <hi>ſee</hi> Obedience.</item>
                     <item>Devil, <hi>93.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Dominion, <hi>84.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Duſt, <hi>21, 29.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>E.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>EArth, <hi>144.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Eye, <hi>33.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Education, <hi>158.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Evil, <hi>ſee</hi> good.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>F.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>FAith, <hi>171, 187.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Fear, <hi>118.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Felicity, <hi>153.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Food, <hi>144, 146, 148.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Fruit, <hi>ſee</hi> Trees and Plants, <hi>102.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>G.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>GArden, <hi>26.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Garments, <hi>111</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>God, <hi>28, 52, 53, 112, 117.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Gold, <hi>ſee</hi> Minerals, <hi>19, 20, 40.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Good, <hi>100.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>H.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>HErbs, <hi>95, 96, 146.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Hermaphrodite, <hi>79.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Husband, <hi>140.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>I.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>INduſtry, <hi>43. 152.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Image, <hi>77.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>K.</label>
               <item>KNowledge, <hi>58.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb facs="tcp:101580:100"/>
               <label>L.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>LAW, <hi>45.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Life, <hi>ſee</hi> Soul and Trees, <hi>54, 158, 172, 176.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Light, <hi>49.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Love, <hi>108.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>M.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>MAn, <hi>9, 10, 20, 21, 29, 76, 79.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Marriage, <hi>70, 72.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Meſſias, <hi>134.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Midſt, <hi>34.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Minerals, <hi>34, 185.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Months, <hi>ſee</hi> Years.</item>
                     <item>Multiplying, <hi>82.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>N.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>NAkedneſs, <hi>75.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Names, <hi>58.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Navigation, <hi>41.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Neceſſity, <hi>138.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Noſes and Noſtrils, <hi>24.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Nothing, <hi>57.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Numbers, <hi>8, 14, 15, 16, 18, 19, 20, 36, 38, 52, 53.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>O.</label>
               <item>OBedience, <hi>45, 57, 97, 98, 100, 102, 109, 123, 136, 140.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>P.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>PAradiſe, <hi>ſee</hi> Garden.</item>
                     <item>Paſſion. <hi>114.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Patience, <hi>168.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>People, <hi>169.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Plants, <hi>ſee</hi> Trees, <hi>29, 32, 34, 144.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>R.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>REaſon, <hi>151, 187.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Religion, <hi>161.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Reſurrection, <hi>176.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Rib, <hi>ſee</hi> Bones, <hi>16, 63, 65, 68.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Rivers, <hi>36, 40.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>S.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>SAcrifice, <hi>87.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Serpent, <hi>93, 94, 124.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sin, <hi>124, 128, 129, ſee</hi> Vertue and Vice.</item>
                     <item>Sleep, <hi>62.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sorrow, <hi>143.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Soul, <hi>18, 25, 133, 176.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Speech, <hi>126, 127.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Spirit, <hi>26, 31.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Stones, <hi>38, 40.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Sweat, <hi>147.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>T.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>TEars, <hi>143.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Temptation, <hi>95, 96.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Time, <hi>ſee</hi> Years.</item>
                     <item>Trees, <hi>34, 35, 40, 45, 48. 52. 116, 151. ſee</hi> Plants.</item>
                     <item>Tryals, <hi>112.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>V.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>VErtue and Vice, <hi>121.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Voice, <hi>140, 112.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Voluptuouſneſs, <hi>137.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>W.</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>Wife, <hi>107. See</hi> Marriage and Man and Obedience.</item>
                     <item>Woman, <hi>55, 56, 57, 65, 69, 70, 80, 128, 135, 137. See</hi> Man.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <label>Y.</label>
               <item>YEars, <hi>170.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
